I'd like to revisit a deceptively simple question
that I asked in the very first video of this
series,
What are vectors?
Is a two-dimensional vector for example, fundamentally
an arrow on a flat plane that we can describe
with co-ordinates for convenience?
Or, is it fundamentally that pair of real
numbers, which is just nicely visualised as
an arrow on a flat plane?
Or are both of these just manifestations of
something deeper?
On the one hand, defining vectors as primarily
being a list of numbers feels clear-cut and
unambiguous.
It makes things like four-dimensional vectors
or one hundred-dimensional vectors
sound like real, concrete ideas that you can
actually work with.
When otherwise, an idea like four dimensions
is just a vague, geometric notion that's difficult
to describe
without waving your hands a bit.
But on the other hand, a common sensation
for those who actually work with linear algebra,
especially as you get more fluent with changing
your basis,
is that you're dealing with a space that exists
independently from the co-ordinates that you
give it,
and that co-ordinates are actually somewhat
arbitrary,
depending on what you happen to choose as
your basis vectors.
Core topics in linear algebra, like determinants
and eigenvectors,
seem indifferent to your choice of co-ordinate
systems.
The determinant tells you how much a transformation
scales areas,
and eigenvectors are the ones that stay on
their own span during a transformation.
But both of these properties are inherently
spacial, and you can freely change your co-ordinate
system
without changing the underlying values of
either one.
But, if vectors are fundamentally not lists
of real numbers,
and if their underlying essence is something
more spacial,
that just begs the question of what Mathematicians
mean when they use a word like space or spacial.
To build up to where this is going, I'd actually
like to spend the bulk of this video talking
about something
which is neither an arrow, nor a list of numbers,
but also has vector-ish qualities:
functions.
You see, there's a sense in which functions
are actually just another type of vector.
In the same way that you can add two vectors
together, there's also a sensible notion for
adding two functions,
f and g, to get a new function, (f+g).
It's one of those thing where you kind of
already know what it's gonna be, but actually
phrasing it is a mouthful.
The output of this new function at any given
input, like -4, is the sum of the outputs
of f and g,
when you evaluate them each at that same input,
-4.
Or, more generally, the value of the sum function
at any given input x is the sum of the values
of f(x) + g(x).
This is pretty similar to adding vectors co-ordinate
by co-ordinate,
it's just that there are, in a sense, infinitely
many co-ordinates to deal with.
Similarly, there's a sensible notion for scaling
a function by a real number,
just scale all of the outputs by that number.
And again, this is analogous to scaling a
vector co-ordinate by co-ordinate,
it just feels like there's infinitely many
co-ordinates.
Now, given that the only thing vectors can
really do is get added together or scaled,
it feels like we should be able to take the
same useful constructs and problem solving
techniques
of linear algebra, that were originally thought
about in the context of arrows in space,
and apply them to functions as well.
For example, there's a perfectly reasonable
notion of a linear transformation for functions,
something that takes in one function, and
turns it into another.
One familiar example comes from calculus:
the derivative.
It's something which transforms one function
into another function.
Sometimes in this context, you'll hear these
called operators instead of transformations,
but the meaning is the same.
A natural question you might want to ask,
is what it means for a transformation of functions
to be linear.
The formal definition of linearity is relatively
abstract and symbolically driven
compared to the way that I first talked about
it in chapter 3 of this series,
but the reward of abstractness is that we'll
get something general enough to apply to functions,
as well as arrows.
A transformation is linear if it satisfies
two properties, commonly called additivity
and scaling.
Additivity means that if you add two vectors,
v and w, then apply a transformation to their
sum,
you get the same result as if you added the
transformed versions of v and w.
The scaling property is that when you scale
a vector v by some number,
then apply the transformation,
you get the same ultimate vector as if you
scale the transformed version of v by that
same amount.
The way you'll often hear this described is
that linear transformations preserve the operations
of
vector addition and scalar multiplication.
The idea of gridlines remaining parallel and
evenly spaced is that I've talked about in
past videos
is really just an illustration of what these
two properties mean in the specific case of
2D points in space.
One of the most important consequences of
these properties,
which makes matrix-vector multiplication possible,
is that a linear transformation is completely
described
by where it takes the basis vectors.
Since any vector can be expressed by scaling
and adding the basis vectors in some way,
finding the transformed version of a vector
comes down to scaling and adding the transformed
versions of
the basis vectors in that same way.
As you'll see in a moment, this is as true
for functions as it is for arrows.
For example, calculus students are always
using the fact that the derivative is additive
and
has the scaling property, even f they haven't
heard it phrased that way.
If you add two functions, then take the derivative,
it's the same as first taking the derivative
of each one
separately, then adding the result.
Similarly, if you scale a function, then take
the derivative, it's the same as first taking
the derivative,
then scaling the result.
To really drill in the parallel, let's see
what it might look like to describe the derivative
with a matrix.
This will be a little tricky, since function
spaces have a tendency to be infinite-dimensional,
but I think this exercise is actually quite
satisfying.
Let's limit ourselves to polynomials, things
like x^2 + 3x + 5 or 4x^7 - 5x^2.
Each of the polynomials in our space will
only have finitely many terms,
but the full space is going to include polynomials
with arbitrarily large degree.
The first thing we need to do is give co-ordinates
to this space, which requires choosing a basis.
Since polynomials are already written down
as the sum of scaled powers of the variable
x,
it's pretty natural to just choose pure powers
of x as the basis function.
In other words, our first basis function will
be the constant function, b_0(x) = 1.
The second basis function will be b_1(x) = x,
then b_2(x)=x^2, then b_3(x)=x^3, and so on.
The role that these basis functions serve
will be similar to the roles of i-hat, j-hat
and k-hat
in the world of vectors as arrows.
Since our polynomials can have arbitrarily
large degree, this set of basis functions
is infinite.
But that's okay, it just means that when we
treat out polynomials as vectors,
they're going to have infinitely many co-ordinates.
A polynomial like x^2 + 3x + 5, for example,
would be described with the co-ordiantes 5,
3, 1,
then infinitely many zeros.
You'd read this as saying it's 5 times the
first basis function, plus 3 times that second
basis function,
plus 1 times the third basis function, and
then none of the other basis functions
should be added from that point on.
The polynomial 4x^7 - 5x^2 would have the
co-ordinates 0, 0, -5, 0, 0, 0, 0, 4, then
an infinite string of zeros.
In general, since every individual polynomial
has only finitely many terms, it's co-ordinates
will be some finite
string of numbers, with an infinite tail of
zeros.
In this co-ordinate system, the derivative
is described with an infinite matrix, that's
mostly full of zeors,
but which has the positive integers counting
down on this offset diagonal.
I'll talk about how you could find this matrix
in just a moment, but the best way to get
a feel for it,
is to just watch it in action.
Take the co-ordinates representing the polynomial
x^3 + 5x^2 + 4x + 5,
then put those co-ordinates on the right of
the matrix.
The only term which contributes to the first
co-ordinate of the result is 1x4,
which means the constant term in the result
will be 4.
This corresponds to the fact that the derivative
of 4x is the constant 4.
The only term contributing to the second co-ordinate
of the matrix-vector product is 2x5,
which means the coefficient in front of x
in the derivative is 10.
That one corresponds to the derivative of
5x^2.
Similarly, the third co-ordinate in the matrix-vector
product comes down to taking 3x1.
This one corresponds to the derivative of
x^3 being 3x^2.
And after that, it'll be nothing but zeros.
What makes this possible is that the derivative
is linear.
And, for those of you who like to pause and
ponder, you could construct this matrix by
taking the derivative
of each basis function, and putting the co-ordinates
of the results in each column.
So, surprisingly, matrix-vector multiplication
and taking a derivative, which at first seem
like completely different
animals, are both just really members of the
same family.
In fact, most of the concepts I've talked
about in this series with respect to vectors
as arrows in space,
things like the dot product or eigenvectors,
have direct analogues in the world of functions.
Though sometimes they go by different names,
things like 'inner product' or 'eigenfunction'.
So, back to the question of what is a vector.
The point I want to make here is that there
are lots of vector-ish things in maths,
as long as you're dealing with a set of objects
where there's a reasonable notion of scaling
and adding,
whether that's a set of arrows in space, lists
of numbers, functions or whatever other crazy
thing
you choose to define, all of the tools developed
in linear algebra regarding vectors,
linear transformations, and all that stuff,
should be able to apply.
Take a moment to imagine yourself right now,
as a mathematician developing the theory of
linear algebra.
You want all of the definitions and discoveries
of your work to apply to all of the vector-ish
things
in full generality, not just to one specific
case.
These sets of vector-ish things, like arrows
or lists of numbers or functions, are called
vector spaces,
and what you as the mathematician might want
to do is say,
"Hey everyone!
I don't want to think about all the different
types of crazy vector spaces that
you all might come up with, so what you do
is establish a list of rules that vector addition
and scaling
have to abide by.
These rules are called axioms, and in the
modern theory of linear algebra, there are
8 axioms
that any vector space must satisfy, if all
of the theory and constructs that we've discovered
are going to apply.
I'll leave them on the screen here for anyone
who wants to pause and ponder, but basically,
it's just a checklist, to make sure that the
notions of vector addition and scalar multiplication
do the things that you'd expect them to do.
These axioms are not so much fundamental rules
of nature, as they are an interface between
you,
the mathematician discovering results, and
other people who might want to apply those
results
to new sorts of vectors spaces.
If, for example, someone defines some crazy
type of vector space, like the set of all
pi creatures,
with some definition of adding and scaling
pi creatures, these axioms are like a checklist
of things
that they need to verify about their definitions,
before they can start applying the results
of linear algebra.
And you as the mathematician, never have to
think about all the possible crazy vector
spaces people might define,
you just have to prove your results in terms
of these axioms, so anyone who's definitions
satisfy those
axioms can happily apply you results, even
if you never thought about their situation.
As a consequence, you'd tend to phrase all
of your results pretty abstractly, which is
to say,
only in terms of these axioms,
rather than centring on a specific type of
vector, like arrows in space, or functions.
For example, this is why just about every
textbook you'll find will define linear transformations
in terms of additivity and scaling, rather
than talking about gridlines remaining parallel
and evenly spaced,
even though the latter is more intuitive,
and at least in my view, more helpful for
first time learners,
even if it is specific to one situation.
So the mathematicians answer to "what are
vectors?" is to just ignore the question.
In the modern theory, the form that vectors
take doesn't really matter, arrows, lists
of numbers, functions,
pi creatures, really it can be anything so
long as there is some notion of adding and
scaling vectors
that follows these rules.
It's like asking what the number 'three' really
is.
Whenever it comes up concretely, it's in the
context of some triplet of things, but in
maths,
it's treated as an abstraction for all possible
triplets of things, and lets you reason about
all possible triplets,
using a single idea.
Same goes with vectors, which have many embodiments,
but maths abstracts them all into a single,
intangible notion of a vector space.
But, as anyone watching this series knows,
I think it's better to begin reasoning about
vectors in a concrete,
visualisable setting, like 2D space with arrows
rooted at the origin.
But as you learn more linear algebra, know
that these tools apply much more generally,
and that this is the underlying reason why
textbooks and lectures tend to be phrased,
well, absractly.
So with that, folks, I think I'll call it
an end to this essence of linear algebra series.
If you've watched and understood the videos,
I really do believe that you have a solid
foundation
in the underlying intuitions of linear algebra.
This is not the same thing as learning the
full topic, of course, that's something that
can only really come from
working through problems, but the learning
you do moving forward can be substantially
more efficient
if you have all the right intuitions in place.
So, have fun applying those intuitions, and
best of luck with your future learning.