Welcome back to what is now the second to last in the Lockdown Math series.
So we've been talking a lot about exponential functions and complex numbers and the interplay of the two of them,
and I thought what might be a very nice culminating topic to help bring it all together and show really the full breadth of what
exponential functions are and what they can be would be to talk about raising i to the power i.
Now this is a, this is a funny little expression because
usually if we think about powers, if we were doing something like i to the fourth,
you know, we know how to think about it in terms of repeated multiplication. We're just multiplying something by itself four different times.
And in general you'd like to think of i to the x as some variant of that,
but as soon as x becomes a complex number, we should realize that it's really nothing
like the above. So it's really nothing like this.
Instead, the way that we think about it is going to have to be very related to the way that we think about raising e
to various different numbers, e being that kind of home base for us. And in fact if we go,
let's not show where things are going too much here,
if we go ahead and rewrite that base i in terms of e,
it can help us make sense out of this expression. But I don't want to do that,
I want you to do that for me. So if you head on over to 3b1b.co.live, link is in the description,
it'll forward you on over to item pool,
which now asks us
write a value of x so that e to the x is equal to i.
That way we'll be able to replace it in the base of our expression.
And then once we do that, maybe we can use our knowledge of e and
exponentials of e in order to make some sense out of this expression. Now
let me just add as a quick reminder while everyone is rolling in with answers for that, that when we write e to the x and
complex numbers are in the mix, we are no longer talking about repeated multiplication.
And instead I think the healthiest way to think about it is that e to the x is a shorthand
for this polynomial that I might call exp.
It's the it's sort of the main exponential function. All other exponential functions derive from this in a way that I'll describe later on in
this episode actually.
And it's it's a lovely polynomial.
It's 1 plus x plus x squared over 2 plus x cubed over 6. Each term looks like a power of x divided by
the factorial of that power.
So the reason for doing that is then it can actually make sense to plug in things like
complex values. And one of the things that we looked at earlier in the series was how if you're plugging in imaginary values,
you know, let's say I go over here and I'm gonna plug in i
where i is the square root of negative 1 times some value theta,
we can very literally read off what it means to exponentiate it in that context.
For example, this very first term 1 we might think of as a vector pointing from 0 to 1.
The next term which is some scaled version of i, well
it's a 90 degree rotation of that first vector scaled a little bit differently.
Then the next vector is a 90 degree rotation of that scaled differently. And depending on what this value theta equals,
the way that these things scale is going to look very different. And it's in general a difficult thing to think about,
but it's at least a sensible thing to think about, right? So that when we go to our expression
e to the x and we're going to start thinking about i and various complex numbers,
it makes sense computationally what it means.
And then there's going to be a separate illustration that I'll pull up in a moment for how it makes sense in terms of intuition
what it means.
But first let's just see how people are doing on our
live quiz finding a value of x so that e to the x is equal to i.
Now,
how have people done here?
Okay, so
the top answer is in a sense absolutely correct you could say. By definition, the natural log is the inverse function of
exponentiation. So
whatever the answer is here, we should be able to write it as natural log of i. The problem is that's not really helpful,
it's not going to move us forward,
because if we if we tried to use that, you know, we pop over here and we say instead of writing
i I'm going to write e to the natural log of i and
then I'm going to be raising that to some kind of power. It begs the question and the only thing I can really do from
here is simplify that down to be i which sort of gets us nowhere.
So to move forward and to think is there a number, some concrete point on the plane that I can plug in?
For that we'd want to look at,
oh, I accidentally skipped ahead of my questions here.
Let me go back, pull up people's answers.
Got a little excited, a little trigger-happy with some of my clicking around here and
the second most common answer is something that's going to actually help us move forward here, which was one half of i times pi.
And then that's the same as what was written, what was categorized as the third most common one, one half pi times i,
just swapping the two numbers there and
I think, yeah, I think the one following that I'm guessing people either forgot to mention the i
but let's just, let's just write that out and kind of see where this moves us. One half i times pi.
Now if you're confused about where that came from, I think this is a good time to remind ourselves of
Euler's formula and what it's really saying. It's one half pi times i where again,
computationally, this very literally means if we plug in pi over 2 for theta here, which would be something like
1.57 or so. Let me see if I can, I don't think I'll be able to get it right on the head,
but something in the 1.57 range. If you were to play out this whole sum,
the claim of saying that e to the pi halves i equals i is that
when you play all of this out and you add all of the terms together, you're going to get to the top here.
But usually this is kind of a complicated way to think about it.
People don't want to pull up this whole polynomial and imagine the spiraling sum.
I think it's helpful just in case you find yourself doubting the
the reality of what we're talking about or the fact that it's something sensible.
Almost always, anytime that people are thinking about complex exponentials, instead they find themselves thinking something like
e to the i times theta,
they just immediately know,
maybe not immediately, but you come to immediately know of Euler's formula. That it's telling you you walk a distance theta
around the unit circle, which is to say an angle of theta radians,
and whatever point you're sitting at on the complex plane, that's the output. So people who knew about this would say, hmm,
i as a number is also sitting on the unit circle,
so I just have to walk an angle of 90 degrees, pi halves radians. And from here
we can actually move forward and get kind of a funny-looking answer.
Because that i will hop to the inside and we'll be looking at e to the pi halves times i squared.
i squared is negative 1 by definition, so this looks like e to the negative pi halves.
That is a purely real number. You could just plug that into your calculator, and it's actually around
0.2 or so. It's about a fifth, which is weird
that you take an imaginary number and raise it to an imaginary power and that gets you a real number.
Maybe it feels a little bit weird that e and pi have shown up. Not that much if we're thinking in terms of
Euler's formula and all of that, but I
kind of want to go deeper on this one, right?
I think it's one thing to plug in some numbers and see what pops out.
And there's a couple great videos who have talked about i to the i from some of my favorite channels. Stand Up Math
with Matt Parker, he talked about i to the i, did a beautiful job.
Black Pin Red Pin did another i to the i video, truly great.
One thing that I try to,
you know, I try to do is add something into the mix if I'm talking about a topic that others already have. And in this
case, I think one of the most interesting questions you can ask before we jump in, I mean
there's lots of interesting things about this expression i to the i,
but if we're seeking intuition, thinking about how i is a 90 degree rotation,
right, that's the way that it acts when we're multiplying things on the complex plane.
We think of it very intuitively as the thing that upon multiplication turns stuff 90 degrees or pi halves radians.
So when you look at this expression that i to the power i equals e to the negative pi halves,
it begs the question in what sense do two 90 degree rotations
combine to make this real number, this very specific real number of e to the negative pi halves, around 0.2079
on and on. And
it's like those games that sometimes you play with arithmetic where someone says, oh, I'll give you the numbers 1, 3, 4, and 6,
see if you can combine them in some way with addition, multiplication, division, to get some other specific number.
Like 24, in that case is a particularly fun puzzle. In this case, it's kind of like that style of puzzle on steroids.
How do we take the idea of a 90 degree rotation and
combine it with itself twice in some mathematical sense such that we get out this number e to the negative pi halves?
Where is that intuition coming from? And the first step, I would say,
is to remind ourselves of the intuition for why it is that Euler's formula works.
Why it is that I can take an expression like e to the pi halves i and say that that's the same thing as i.
You know, I just showed what it means in a very
computational sense, what the claim is with this spiraling sum, but that tells us nothing about why.
Why it would be the case that this is how things behave.
Now I've at this point made, you know, quite a number of videos on variants of this,
but I think the quickest one is to think of it dynamically somehow.
So if we take an expression like e to the i times t and we're thinking of that as describing a dynamic,
you're going to have a position that changes over time.
Then what I'll do is I'm going to start drawing that with a blue vector and we know as an initial condition
that when we raise e to the 0 that's at 1. So where we are at time t equals 0 is equal to 1.
But let's say that's all we know, right?
We haven't been told about Euler's formula or how we should be thinking about it with circles or anything like that.
That's just where we're starting. Well, one thing we might know is that e to the x is its own derivative.
So if we're thinking of dynamics here, we might ask about the velocity of our position taking its derivative and
because e to the x is its own derivative, this is quite nice. The outer expression is going to stay the same.
And then the inner expression as we're applying the chain rule is just i times t. So we multiply the whole outer thing by i.
And this gives us a literal way to read
the equation in terms of dynamics, right?
What we're saying is take whatever your position vector is, if you rotate that 90 degrees you apply this action of i,
that's going to give you the velocity vector.
So wherever you're standing, draw a vector from 0, the origin, up to where you are,
rotate that vector 90 degrees, that gives you your velocity. And that's enough to tell you how to move,
assuming you know that where you're starting. And
of course we have to draw this out in the complex plane, the fact that we've rotated 90 degrees already brings us there. And
I could draw out a bunch of different potential position vectors,
you know,
suggestively maybe putting them on a circle and saying really imagine yourself sitting at any one of those and
following the rule for this dynamic. And what it would tell you is, okay, I've got to sit there,
rotate my vector 90 degrees, that describes my velocity.
And it doesn't necessarily have to be any one of the points on that circle. Any point in the plane, if you were following this
dynamic, you say rotate that vector 90 degrees, which if we're drawing a vector field,
we often scale down, and it's all well and good. And here you could phrase this question without even talking about
exponentials or complex numbers or anything like that. And in fact, I'm going to go back to the quiz just to
really emphasize that Euler's formula and what it's claiming and then how we apply it to expressions like i to the power i
is very, it's really intuitive as soon as we're putting some dynamics into it. And we can ask questions removed from the idea of exponentials
that actually have the same substance in their answers. So here,
I want you to imagine starting a walk from the point 1,0 on the coordinate plane
in such a way that at all moments your velocity vector is a 90 degree
counterclockwise rotation of the vector drawn from 0,0, the origin, up to where you are.
After pi halves units of time, where will you be on the plane?
Okay, so kind of think about that. Think about that dynamic and where you'll end up after a little bit of time.
While you answer, let me see if we have any questions that have popped in from the audience.
No questions at the moment,
at least that I see. So if ever you do want to ask, go to Twitter, use the hashtag locked down math.
Those will be forwarded to me and then sometimes they'll be on the screen that I can pull up here.
And that always makes for a fun time.
For example, it seems like now we actually have one which is how about other solutions to the expression x equals i such as 5 pi halves?
Oh, I'm so glad you asked. I'm so very glad you asked. We will certainly be talking about that.
And if you just hold on for like one little moment,
that's exactly what we're going to get to. So
I'll keep that on file for us to pull up in a little moment.
But right now while we're just trying to get intuition around the first,
you know, there will be multiple answers. The first answer we saw was e to the negative pi halves. Let's
consider this lake question.
So it seems like
most of you correctly said that this would get you at the coordinates 0, 1.
It's essentially walking you a quarter of the way around. I said lake question.
I'm sort of picturing in my head as a big circular lake that you're going for a walk around
because when you have this rule for dynamics where your position vector
rotated by 90 degrees gives you your velocity vector,
that is circular motion
because the tangent line to a circle is always perpendicular to its radius. So this rule of motion
corresponds with walking around a circle and that's kind of the intuition for Euler's formula, right?
You keep increasing that value of t and this dynamical rule,
if e to the i t is going to behave according to the derivatives that we expect of a function like e to the t
necessarily walks you around a circle. So in particular,
when we're wondering how long does it take to get to i,
you would basically say just wait for an amount of time equal to, well, whatever the angle to get up there is, pi halves.
Okay, so in this case we're thinking pi halves. Let me see if I can get it exactly on the dot. Okay, 1.57.
We're thinking of pi halves as kind of an amount of time for these dynamics to get you on the number i.
And that gives us the first half of our intuition if we want to go back to our formula and we're asking in what sense do
two 90 degree rotations combine to make e to the negative pi halves?
Once we're thinking of our dynamics here as
each one of your velocity vectors as a 90 degree rotation of your position,
this base i,
the way that we're kind of thinking about it reading it off as something with meaning rather than just a number, is that as
a point on the plane, it's where you get after traveling for pi halves units of time
according to the dynamics of this expression, according to the idea that your velocity is always a 90 degree rotation of your position.
Okay, so that's awfully nice. And in fact, there's already sort of two different i's at play here, which, or I guess
there's three different i's at play. We have this base, which is describing the 90 degrees that we walk around the circle.
We have the i that's sitting here, which is describing the rule of
rotating your velocity vector 90 degrees.
But now we're going to introduce another i, which essentially has this effect of changing what your dynamics are.
Because as we go from e to the i times t and
instead we, you know, raise things to another power of i, which I'll just write with a little
caret i, if we take e to the i t and we alter what that expression is by raising it to the i,
what we get is e to the negative t.
Okay, so we have e to the negative t and
if we try to interpret that with the same sort of dynamics that we had above in terms of a velocity and a position,
what that's telling us is
that the derivative of
our new dynamic e to the negative t is equal to
well now the constant sitting in front of t is negative 1, so our chain rule will have it be negative 1 times
itself
times e to the negative t. So whatever your position is, now your velocity is negative 1 times itself.
So the effect of raising to another power i is kind of like we took the dynamics,
we looked at every velocity vector, and we said rotate another 90 degrees so that in this context it would actually be
in the beginning a velocity vector pointing backwards
with one unit. So if you're starting off at the number 1, your initial velocity is to walk straight towards 0 and
as you walk even lower, if you were sitting at 1 half, then you would still be walking towards 0,
but now your velocity vector would be negative 1 times where you are, which is negative 1 half.
And what this means for the actual motion that this would imply, you might kind of imagine it,
I haven't animated this nicely yet or anything,
but if you look at this whole vector field and you ask each one of those vectors,
take wherever you are and rotate another 90 degrees
counterclockwise, they would all be pointed in towards the origin.
So if you were to have a little dot move in such a way that its velocity always matches whatever
vector it's sitting on top of, what you would end up with
is something where with each time step,
it kind of takes a step towards 0 and it just, with each of your time steps, is walking towards 0 and each step
has a size that gets smaller and smaller as you actually approach 0.
And of course in practice this would be a bunch of infinitesimal steps rather than
very concrete sizing. You might be very exact about it if you wanted and say what we're looking at is
scaling down by some number just less than 1 and we're doing this n different times and then we're
going to multiply that by however much time we're waiting.
And you take this as a limiting expression.
That's just what we talked about in the compound interest lecture, if you're curious.
And it's kind of the standard way to talk about e to powers is this sort of limit.
You could also have that t living on the inside here instead if you wanted.
But now if we think about
our original point i, our base, what that meant, it was saying look at our dynamics and
it's the point you get to when you wait pi halves units of time.
So the effect of raising to the i changes our dynamics in such a way that instead of walking around a circle
we're doing this kind of exponential decay. We're moving towards 0 at a slowing and slowing rate. And the place that you end up
after pi halves units of time will be e to the negative pi halves
around 0.2079.
So, you know, that's a little bit of intuition for in what sense do two 90 degree rotations combine to get you this very specific
value. One of them changes your dynamics and the original one came from the idea of walking pi halves radians.
So I think that's kind of satisfying in its own way because otherwise when you look at the expression i to the i
equals e to the negative pi halves, it's like what does any of this mean?
This doesn't correspond to any, you know, thing that might see in the real world.
But thinking through the intuitions actually have you thinking through things like what are the dynamics of circular motion?
What are the dynamics for exponential decay? Things that come up in the real world all the time.
But there is a potentially more pressing question
which was raised and let's see if it's still up there.
Well, whoever asked it a little bit earlier. What about other solutions to e to the x equals i?
I think that's that's actually spot-on. And in fact, let me let me ask other people to contribute some
solutions here. So let's let's go to our quiz.
Let me go to
question number three
which is going to be very similar
to a question that was already seen which is to write a value of x
other than the one we just saw x equals pi halves times i so that e to the x equals i.
And feel free to be as creative as you want to try to get an answer that other people haven't written, right?
Just to really emphasize that there are actually quite a few different options here and then in a moment
we'll talk about why there are quite a few options if it's not already clear.
But I'll give you a moment to think of which of the many possible values of x you could choose is the one that you
want to put your fingerprint on that you want to be contributing to the live stats page that we're seeing right now.
I'll give you a little moment.
And as you're answering that we've got a question coming in that says wouldn't it be more accurate to say that i to the power i is
i different 90 degree rotations, not two 90 degree rotations. After all it's multiplying by i. That's the rotation.
So if we stretch the meaning of words too thin aren't we multiplying by i i times?
I mean, I think the most honest answer here is just no not at all.
No offense meant but that's just not what exponentiation actually means as soon as we're extending to the idea of complex numbers.
I
get the intent you kind of want to stretch the meaning of taking i to the i it's as if you're multiplying by itself i
different times, but I cannot think of a way that that actually like satisfactorily makes sense in my mind.
What I do think makes some sense is to try to think of the function i to the x.
Say what properties do we want this function to have and in the context of counting numbers, you know
if n and k are just things like 3 and 5 we know that it should satisfy this idea of
multiplying the outputs correspond to adding the inputs.
So we want to say if this is any kind of function and I you know
I've said this in many different forms in many different places
we want it to satisfy the property that when you add the inputs you multiply the outputs. That to me is
kind of what exponentiation is more so than trying to stretch the idea of repeated multiplication.
So
like if it I mean correct me if I'm wrong if you can definitely if you can find some way where
if you read this off in a stretching language context saying we're taking a 90 degree rotation and applying that i different times
that's not nonsense and that somehow like intuitively gets you to the answer e to the negative pi halves.
I'm all ears, but I think the healthier relationship to have is to say we have this central property for exponentiation
which definitely holds in the context of repeated multiplication
but to extend beyond the places where repeated multiplication makes any sense because it just it just doesn't make sense
when we're talking about something that's not a counting number like i or other crazy things that we exponentiate in math like matrices
focus focus on the property more so than
what some people think of as the origins of that property or the original intuition behind it.
And an interesting question will be you know is is there just one such function that feels reasonable to write for this
because you know if we're gonna write it as i to the x not only should it satisfy this it should also satisfy
you know when we plug in the number one
we get i
presumably i to the power one however we're thinking of this function should be i.
Is there just one such function or are there multiple such functions?
That's what the quiz question is starting to get at and we've got lots of different answers which always makes me happy
so let's see some of the variety that people have thrown in here. So we've got 5 pi i halves great that absolutely is another
value that we could plug in for x here and just to spell out that a little bit more
visually if we were to look back at our circle here where we've at the moment walked
for an amount of time equal to pi halves which is
1.57 what if instead we took another full turn and we go another pi halves to get us to pi
which you know we might kind of record that's where the e to the pi i value is
we walk another pi halves we walk another pi halves which at this point
we would have gone a full circle getting us back to one and then we walk for five pi halves
which numerically is about 7.85
yeah, that absolutely is another number that gets us on top of i and if we were to go through the whole rigmarole of
re-expressing i to the power i
by first writing e to the 5 pi halves i
to the power i
those i's multiply to become negative and we'd be looking at e to the negative 5 pi halves
which is a very different number right we can actually calculate this
I'm not sure off the top of my head, but let's take a look at a Desmos. Maybe go over here
Let's ask it. What is e to the negative 5 pi halves 0.000388
Okay, 0.000388
much smaller number
0.000388
Which begs the question of okay i to the i what are you right?
Are you about a fifth like we saw before around 0.2, or are you this much smaller number and in terms of our intuition?
It's basically
a question of how we're interpreting that base i right are we thinking of it as you wait about
1.57 units of time and then you translate your dynamics into something that looks like decay
rather than spinning and see where you decay to after that amount of time which is 0.2 or
Do you wait even longer for about 7.85 units of time which is 5 pi halves and what see what happens when you decay for?
That long which gets you to a much smaller number
But that's not the only answer that we could enter right we have other people coming in here with negative 3 halves times i pi
Which you know in terms of a unit circle?
We could think of as saying hey if I want to get to I rather than walking
90 degrees pi halves radians that way what if I walk
270 degrees the other way
3 pi halves radians which maybe I'll think of as negative because the convention is usually that counterclockwise is positive
That absolutely is another way to express it and that would get us a different answer if we had e to the negative
3 pi halves i
All to the power i we go through the same game now the i squared cancels with a negative
that's already there, and we have a positive 3 pi halves and
Numerically this gets us an even different looking answer from what we had before
Which if we go over and we say hey, what is
e to the 3 pi not 3 o 3 pi halves
111 point 3 1 very different kind of number than what we saw before
111 point what was it 111 point 3 1 great 111 point 3 1 or so
And again in terms of the intuition what you might be asking there is suppose we have this rotating dynamic
But we move backwards in time we see how long ago in time what I have to be
Such that if I played things forward from there
I would land on the number one my initial condition and
You have to go back in time 3 pi halves units
And then if you were to translate to the decay dynamics
Which is what raising to the eye is doing in this context you say if I'm starting at the number one
But I want to move backwards in time and say
Where should I have started if I want to decay down such that I end up at the number one?
After 3 pi halves units of time the answer is evidently starting at around a hundred and eleven for that kind of exponential decay
And you can see where this is going where there's actually infinitely many different values that we could
Plug in for X if we're thinking of e to the X as being I and people have entered a lot more here
Excuse me throwing my pin onto the ground as one does
classic for third place
9 pi halves great choice
1729 pi halves y'all are my favorite lots and lots of different options infinitely many different values which feels a little
Disconcerting at first right because we look at an expression
That seems like you know there's just gonna be some computation
I just plug that into my calculator and see what pops out and we've got multiple different values for it
So what's going on here right? What's going on and I think?
This really cuts to the idea of how we think about
Exponential in general right but before that I do want to emphasize that this isn't the only time in math
Where we come across a kind of ambiguity for how to interpret something?
I think because if I say something like what is the square root of 25?
You know I think a lot of us say well
It's five
But if we are saying you know
What should the square root be it should be some number X such that when you square it you get 25?
Well there's two different answers to that
Who's to say that our conventions should be that the square root function is positive gives us a positive number rather than?
Negative five so we have one expression that seems like it wants to have multiple different values
Right and this can actually happen in another context where instead of square roots
What if I was asking for the fourth root of something like 16?
Usually we would think of this as positive number two
Right two is a number such that when you multiply by itself four times you get sixteen seems like a decent answer to a fourth
Root, but if we're thinking of this as answering the question what number to the fourth equals 16?
There there is another answer to this we could also say
Negative two that's a number that when you multiply by itself four times you get sixteen
But there's another answer you could say two times. I that seems valid, but there's another answer you could think negative two times
I all four of these numbers satisfy that property so who's to say that?
The fourth root of 16 should be 2 and the answer ends up being well
We adopt a convention when there's multiple options like this when you have a multi-valued function
We often just choose one of those values to be what we mean when we want to treat it as a function as something with
a single input and a single output
in fancier lingo
This comes up all the time when we're dealing with complex numbers the idea of something as an operation kind of wanting
To have multiple values you'll sometimes hear the phrase branch
Where you choose a branch of the square root function?
Which is to say you choose a certain convention?
In real numbers it's nice and easy sometimes because you say just choose the positive one
But there's no notion of which complex numbers are like the positive complex numbers when we want to take square roots just to give one
Example let's say we wanted to take the square root of I
And we want to know what should that be?
Because there's multiple different answers
You know we think of I again is this 90 degree rotation
And if we were thinking of it as a 90 degree rotation it feels like the square root should be
You know something sitting at a 45 degree angle
Maybe that's the square root of I which we could write out very explicitly as root 2 over 2
root 2 over 2 I
That's just using trigonometry
but if we were thinking of I instead as being a
Negative 270 degree rotation it feels like half of that doing half of that operation should actually get us on the other side
Maybe the number sitting down here should be the square root of I and that's actually just the negative of what we saw before
Negative root 2 over 2 minus root 2 over 2 times I
Now in the context of real valued functions we can say yeah
Just choose the square root to be whatever the positive answer is but which of these do you consider the positive answer?
You know maybe it feels like what we should consider this upper one because its coordinates have positive numbers
But however you try to define positive in a nice way here
That's going to be consistent you know for example two positive numbers should always multiply to make a positive number
You're not really going to be able to do it the way that you can for real numbers
And in fact this phenomenon here where we're taking roots is actually the same as the phenomenon
We were just looking at when we were talking about multiple values for I raised to the power of I
Because forget I raised to the power of I let me ask what much might look like it's a much simpler question
Of taking 2 to the power 1 half ok what's 2 to the 1 half?
And I think you say well
We know what this is we kind of define it to be the square root of 2 all is well and good
But what if I said let's approach this the same way that we were approaching our I to the I expression I want to first
Express things as e to the something
right and
Then I'm going to raise that to the 1 half by multiplying the 1 half into the exponent
And I say okay, I can I guess I can do that e to the what is equal to 2 well
That's the natural log of 2
It's a constant which is around 0.69
or so
If we raise e to that power we'll get 2 so we could be thinking of this as e to the natural log of 2
times 1 half and if you wanted to if you
Were thinking of e to the x?
You know this might be kind of overkill in the context of real numbers
But if you were thinking of e to the x as shorthand for this x function you could plug in the value
0.69 times 1 half which I guess would be around 0.345
Ish something like that
You plug in that very concrete value into your polynomial see what it outputs, and it will output around 1.414 a
Nice real number square root of 2 what you would expect
But if we do the same thing we were just doing with I and
Acknowledging that there's actually multiple different answers when we want to write something as e to a power we could also write this
This might seem funny, but we could write it as e to the natural log of 2 plus 2 pi I
That whole thing raised to the 1 half
Right after all this value will come to equal to you could break it down as it's e to the natural log of 2
Multiplied by e to the 2 pi I
This one just has the effect of rotating things 360 degrees, so it's just going to equal 1
So we're looking at 2 times 1 great that feels like a valid substitution
and yet when we play the same game of
Taking this and raising it to a power and treating that by multiplying the power into the exponent look at what happens
We have e to the natural log of 2
times 1 half
plus
Well, what's 2 pi I times 1 half well that will be pi times I
Now this first part e to the natural log of 2 times 1 half that will end up being the familiar
Square root of 2 that's all well and good, but we're going to be multiplying that by e to the pi I
Right and quite famously e to the pi I is negative 1
So in this case it seems to be suggesting that if we are solving this expression 2 to the 1 half
By playing around with the different answers we could plug in for something like e to the
X equaling 1 half what we end up with is another answer what we might traditionally write as this negative square root of 2 and
Here I mean it's a little funny for it to have multiple values to look at 2 to the 1 half and say that's not equaling
One thing but based on choices we make it could equal
multiple different things
But the two things that it could seem quite reasonable
If there's going to be anything that 2 to the 1 half is it seems like it should either be
The positive square root that we're familiar with or the negative variant of that that doesn't actually seem like such a problem
And in fact we could um we could play this game even further where let me ask you for even more creative answers to
This expression because maybe we can find other funny powers of something like 2 to the power
X as we start plugging in various different values of X based on what substitution we make if we're
Abiding by the same rules that we were using in evaluating I to the power I
So this time the question asks or it specifies that one solution of the equation e to the x equals 2 is the real number
Natural log of 2 ok that one we know it. It's not boring, but it's boring in comparison to what else we can do
Can you think of another one and can you write some other?
answer to the question e to the x equals 2 and
Again creativity is welcomed, so I will give you another little moment for that
I
Will go ahead and lock in some answers here if that's alright with you
I'm not sure how much time it necessarily takes to do the math entry depending on what device you're looking at
but
Don't be too stressed if it's before you got the chance to
Into the question that you want into the answer that you want it to answer
So it looks like 131 of you have entered the variant where we take
Ln of 2 and we add 2ii and I guess I am in writing this question
Mistakenly like marked one of the answers as being correct when in fact there's quite a few different correct ones
So that's on me for the fact that I don't know if it looks to any of you like oh
It's red you got it wrong when you entered Ln of 2 plus 42. I pi which is of course a great choice
But you could also have something like 4 pi I plus the natural log of 2 or 6 pi I
Or really any integer multiple of 2 pi I if you add that it doesn't affect e to the X
Because it just has the effect of multiplying by e to the 2 pi I
Which is the effect of multiplying by 1 and again this has kind of a funny consequence where it seems to output kind of reasonable
Results when we do it as another example
It looks like the second most common entered expression there was that we might replace 2
So let's think we're thinking of 2 to the power of 1 4th, okay
there was a suggestion that we replaced 2 with e
to
the natural log of 2 plus 4 pi I
Okay
Plus 4 pi I and we raise all of that
To the 1 4th right well if you were to play the same game you would get e
To the natural log of 2 times 1 4th, and we'd be multiplying by e to the pi I
Now the first part of that is going to be the usual positive
Fourth root of 2 the thing we mean when you plug in an expression like fourth root of 2 into a calculator a nice small
Positive number, but then this second part is negative 1 so it seems to be saying
You know if we were to interpret 2 in this different way raising it to the 1 4th
You know it's not the usual answer that we get but it's a reasonable answer. It's another number that when you
Raise it to the fourth power you get 2
And if we had done this with even different values if instead we had been using
2 pi I
You know it's kind of fun to think about how that would have changed things if instead of 4 pi I we had been adding
Well, then over here. We would have been looking at pi halves times I and instead of multiplying by
Negative 1 we would have instead been multiplying by I
Which again is a valid answer it seems like a reasonable output for something like 2 to the 1 4th
So when you're looking at the fact that I to the power I seems to have multiple different values for it
Right we have this funny phenomenon where we could plug in e to the 5 pi halves I
Negative 3 pi halves I and we get what seemed like wildly different answers something super small something super big all very different from the
1 5th approximately 1 5th answer that we found before up here
It's exactly the same phenomenon as when you're asking something like what's 2 to the 1 4th and
Acknowledging that there's actually multiple different solutions to the expression X to the 4th equals 2
4 different solutions in fact and what you're looking at is the fact that there's multiple different solutions
To the expression e to the X equals some kind of base whether that base is I whether that base is 2
Whatever it might be and one way that we might
Think about this is that when you're dealing with real numbers things are just lovely things are nice
There's one-to-one relationships. You've got positives. It's great
Where if we want to think about exponential functions, let me just cover some of this stuff up
We have this nice back and forth where you can choose to express any exponential as a base to X like 2 to the X
Or you could express that same exponential as X of R times X which you know that is the polynomial that we refer to
Whenever implicitly refer to whenever we write something like e to the X
And there's a lovely back and forth because you can just take a natural logarithm of B
And it gives you one answer assuming that B is a positive number
And that's the same thing as saying that X of R is equal to B
So one way that I've talked about this earlier in the series is that if you were looking at the family of all possible
Exponentials right we could write them as X of R times X and change what R is
And this is exactly the same thing as writing e to the R times X if that's something you're more comfortable with
So e to the R times X X of R times X those are the same thing we could think about changing what that is
But on the other hand if you were to think about all possible exponentials as some base
Let me do base to the power of X and we're going to change what that base is
At first it feels like that's a different kind of expression to manipulate, but it's just another way of expressing the same family
And a way that you might think about this
For how do we think about what base does it correspond to if we're thinking a little bit more abstractly as
Exp of R times X and there's a reason I'm doing this because we're about to apply this to complex numbers where it's going to look
Weirder so follow through with me here if instead of looking at that base one thing I could do is say what is the value?
Of exp of R right which is basically this function, but when we plug in one so exp of R times one
if you prefer to think of it that way and
That is being represented by our green line and what you could see is okay if I get R that
Factor in front of X in my exponential function exp of R X to be zero point six nine
Which I know is around the natural log of two what this means is that?
X of one is about two and so this corresponds with the function that we would usually write as two to the power X
right
Okay, and basically as I change around my R
You know I could try to change it to something so that it looks like three so around one point one
That exponential looks like three which we would usually write as three to the power X
I would like to argue that it's a little bit healthier to think about
Varying this value R
rather than varying the base and the main reason is that as soon as we get to complex contexts, and we're thinking of
exponentiation
You have this overloading that goes on where if we change around what sits in front of the X
That's all well and good. I could have exp of R times X where maybe R is something like zero point six nine
But I could shift that down by two pi I
And that doesn't change the base that it would correspond to that would still correspond to two
Or it could shift it up by two pi I that doesn't change the base that it corresponds to because in all of those cases
When we plug in X equals one we get the same thing however
All of these for different values of X are distinct functions
This is why we saw multiple different values for I to the power I
Because I to the X is an ambiguous function in that context it would be unambiguous if we decided which value of R
Such that what we're representing is exp of R times X which value of R. Do we choose as soon as we choose one?
It's an unambiguous function
but at that point it just feels like maybe what we want is a
To stop thinking about things in terms of some base raised to the power X
Maybe as soon as we're in the context of complex numbers
We should just write them all as exp of some constant times X if for no other reason it makes crystal clear
How we actually plug in numbers if we want to do a computation or just to do math on top of it
we've got this nice infinite polynomial that we plug them into and
I'll make another case for you that this is this is maybe the the correct way to think about exponentials
As soon as we're extending into other domains things like complex numbers and for that let's just let's just back up
Go back to doorbell some things arrived go back to the original
Way that we extend the idea of exponentiation and just think of like what is 2 to the X
Right we know how to think about this for natural numbers. You know something like 2 to the 3
Repeated multiplication
How is it that you're first taught to think about something like 2 to the X for fractional amounts or
For negative amounts and things like that. Well. You're usually taught that
2 to the 1 half
should be something where
you know if I multiply it by itself and
This follows the usual rules that
Exponentials do with counting numbers where we're able to add things in that exponent
I should get 2 to the 1 so it should be some number that when I multiply it by itself I get 2 and
You know at that point you have a choice, maybe it's positive. Maybe it's negative
But if you always decide to make the positive choice
You're going to be able to get a nice continuous function out of this same deal if we ask about negative numbers
What should 2 to the negative 1 be well that should be something where when I multiply it by 2 to the 1?
It gets me 2 to the 0 and that's kind of the justification for our convention that negative exponents look like 1 half
But what's really going on here is we're saying whatever this is it should be some kind of function
That satisfies this property f of a plus b
equals f of a times f of b and
Moreover the fact that the base is 2 is basically telling us that it's not just any such function
It's a function where when we plug in 1 we get 2
And just as a little you know sanity check style question to see if you're following along with some of the implications here
I want to ask you what is
I won't call it like a softball, but this is this isn't meant to be like
An incredibly deep question necessarily. It's just more of a check if you're following along with
The idea of abstractly starting with properties of a function and then kind of deducing ways that we might want to write it down
based on those properties
If f of x satisfies this exponential property f of a plus b equals f of a times f of b for all inputs
And it also satisfies f of 1 equals 2 which of the following is true
Which is to say which of the following is necessarily true
No matter which such function you're starting with and those of you who remember which which lecture was it
It's whichever one we were talking about how to interpret what Euler's formula is really saying
I asked a question of this style where I neglected a single condition, you know
I didn't write down the fact that we want to make sure f of x is nonzero everywhere and then that caused some amount of
Confudlement which is cool get confudlement on screen that happens to all of us
But the the intent of it was to basically show that this abstract property of something that turns addition into multiplication is
Is enough to basically make you want to write the function as whatever it equals as one raised to some kind of power
This is the the spirit of the question
Now we've got a couple questions actually about power towers that seem to have popped up here which is great connected to last time
Let's let's hold off on the power tower question for just a moment so that we first get like a deeper feel of like
What exponentiation should mean here?
Because because we can be what I want to claim is we can answer it in like multiple different ways
So if you give me just one, we'll talk about power towers
And then just as a number line can be represented in a logarithmic scale can the same done be done for a complex plane?
Maybe mapping the complex plane onto an infinite cylinder in the logarithmic. That's yeah. Yeah
In fact, there's a visualization that I'm going to get to in just a moment here where we do something quite similar to that
Because what we'll do is play around with different exponential functions X of R times X
But we're going to change that value of R which is going to be represented by a little yellow dot
So we'll kind of talk through this
It's not going to map the whole plane, but just a couple sample points from the real axis and the imaginary axis
But the idea is that as we move around what that constant is
We're going to be able to kind of visualize the different things that it does to the plane and
Effectively it's like it's turning the x-axis into a logarithmic scale and then wrapping the imaginary axis along a circle
And then as soon as that value of R becomes imaginary it swaps the role of those
Real numbers get put on the circle and imaginary numbers get put on a logarithmic scaled
Positive axis so great question all three of which I guess are sort of jumping the gun ahead for where I want to go
But nice to see that's where people are thinking so in this one. Let's go ahead and just grade it
the idea is that
this this property of f of a plus B ends up letting you express a lot of different things purely in terms of
What f of 1 is and just to spell that out very?
explicitly
Something like f of 5 is the same thing as f of 1 plus 1 plus 1 plus 1 plus 1
Which is the same thing as f of 1 multiplied by itself 5 times because of this property
Which if f of 1 is 2 is the same as 2 to the power 5 and then something like f of negative 5
It should be the case that when we multiply it by f of 5
We get whatever f of 0 is and it's not immediately clear what f of 0 is but we could say that f of 1 plus 0 is
Equal to whatever f of 1 is times what f of 0 is but f of 1 is equal to 2
And so this is also equal to 2 so we're saying 2 is equal to 2 times something well that something has to be a 1
so in this context this guarantees that f of negative 5 is
2 to the negative 5 it's 1 over 2 to the 5th
We could explicitly write this as 2 to the negative 5 which is all to say
These two properties together make us really want to write the function as
2 to the X
Because any counting number that we put in it's going to satisfy
It's it's going to look like to multiply by itself that number of times any fractional number
We put in it's going to satisfy these properties that we wanted
And you might wonder is that unique and in the context of real valued functions it actually would be
But in the context of complex valued functions
There would be multiple such functions f that we could write for this one of which is what we were looking at before
Where we could have a function defined to be
exp of
the natural log of 2
plus 2 pi I
all of that times X
Okay, forgive the sloppiness here, I just get excited writing about this
And this is actually a different function as evidenced by what happens if you plug in X equals 1 half
We saw a little bit earlier how when you plug in 1 half what you get is the negative square root of 2
and then if you plug in 1 fourth you get
Not the fourth root of 2 but I times the fourth root of 2 so it is a different function
But it still satisfies these properties and it kind of makes us want to write it as 2 to the X
And it makes it suggest that maybe 2 to the X is an ambiguous bit of notation
And we should just write everything in terms of exp of R times something but you might wonder well
You know maybe we're just not being creative enough with all of the functions that satisfy this property
Maybe there's an ambiguity when we write exp of R times something and there's different values of R that could come into play
But I'm I'm just gonna put down a little claim and then maybe give like a sketch of what the proof would look like if you want
Which is that let's say you have some complex function F, and it satisfies the following properties first
You're able to take a derivative of it. It's differentiable which just keeps it from being some you know totally messy discontinuous thing
That's like taking on some random values depending on you know the span of whatever vector space over
I don't know fractional amounts you might want to think of in crazy ways. It's a nice function. That's differentiable
It's not equal to 0 everywhere
so the condition that sort of slipped my mind and I
Forget which lecture lecture for or something like that and then it has this central property that it turns addition into multiplication
If you have such a function I claim that there's a unique maybe I should really specify there exists a unique
Complex number R so that you could write F of X as basically being this exponential function of R times that value X
Which is you know basically saying that if you have X as a function this
infinite polynomial with nice derivative properties and all of that if you have this you have
Every exponential that you want in a very like abstract generic sense of the word exponential just based on a property that we could want
from it and the sketch of the proof would look something like this if
You want to first look at what is the derivative of this value which we're assuming exists everywhere, right?
And you explicitly write out what the limit of that is
I'll just talk through it very quickly here for those who want to like pause and think through the details feel free to
the central property that we have lets us
Expand out the F of X plus H term
So we're thinking you know a change slight change to the output over the change to the input that caused it. That's what DF DX
unwraps to and
Because we can factor that out. We can factor F of X out of the expression entirely and the whole limit is
expressed only in terms of H
Which if you think about what it means in the context of derivatives and the fact that F of 0 necessarily equals 1
This whole limiting expression
Is just some constant but more specifically it's whatever the derivative of our function at 0 is
So you have this funny thing where if you know its derivative at 0 that determines what its derivative is everywhere
And in the context of exponential functions
this is hopefully quite familiar because all that we're really saying is the derivative of an exponential function is
Proportional to itself and that proportionality constant is equal to whatever the derivative at 0 is this is all very
Abstractly phrased and such but but the purpose of it is to emphasize that it's not
necessarily just functions that we already think of as a to the power X
But it is a potentially much more broad class of functions that just satisfy this abstract property of turning addition into multiplication
But if you have that it actually guarantees that you also have a second derivative
And for that matter a third derivative and such because the derivative function is just proportional to itself
So in order to take the nth derivative you just look at
That proportionality constant and raise it to the power n and then from here
You could do a Taylor series expansion and I might leave that as sort of the advanced homework for those of you who are comfortable
with Taylor series in that idea
especially if you want to intermix the idea of any
Differentiable function that's differentiable in a sense of complex numbers, which is sort of a definitely college topic
You know you you could intermix the reasoning there as you want
But fuzzy reasoning is allowed in the context of someone who only knows about Taylor series and nothing else
to take this idea and look at the Taylor expansion for F and kind of justify the idea that
There's a unique complex number such that our function F can necessarily be written like this
And then the connection to normal exponentials is whenever you have such a value R
We do essentially what we do in the complex context of real numbers is if you look at exp of that function of that value R
and
Write that as a base. It feels like you should be able to write that as B to the X
But the whole the whole point here of course is that when we play this game
And you're trying to interpret something like I to the X that's an ambiguous function
Because there's lots of different values of R. We could interpret that to mean not just
exp of pi halves I times X, but we could also interpret it to mean
exp of 5 pi halves I
Times X and
These are separate functions
And there's an infinite family of separate functions that feel like we should write them as I to the X
So the expression I to the I unless you've adopted a standard for what that's necessarily going to mean
When you say it has infinitely many outputs another way to think of that is that
The function I to the X with the notation we have is a little bit ambiguous
Now with all of that let's let's just start visualizing some of this because I think that's fun
And you know you you tell me if this is if this is a helpful visual or a more confusing visual
but what we're going to do is look at this function exp of R times X, which is
Basically this is another way to write e to the power of X in fact
I think I I think I rendered a different animation at some point that specified that because I was planning on
Planning on doing that so let me oh yeah there you are get back in my file system get back to where you're supposed to
be
Get on in there is it complaining because there's multiple different
It's gonna be like there's a Oh replace it shows up on the other screen
Wait why is it yeah, okay replace?
Place whatever you see there
And now we go back to oh there we all of that all of that just so that I could have nicely written out
If you're uncomfortable with thinking of it as exp of R times X this infinite polynomial
Just in the back of your head e to the R times X and we're gonna vary around R
so I'm gonna follow the points of the imaginary axis, and I'm gonna follow the points of the real axis and
Let's see what this does
Well that's all kind of fast so let me think through it a little bit more slowly all of the negative numbers anything
That's a negative real number is going to get squished into the range between 0 and 1
Which should make sense e to the negative?
a to a negative real number is something between 0 and 1 and we're
Specifically tracking f of negative 1 which is going to show up around whatever 1 over e is around 30 0.37
f of 1 lands on e as
Expected that's what exp of 1 is
f of I is gonna land one radian around the unit circle, and it's kind of fun to follow along the whole
imaginary axis here how the imaginary axis gets
wrapped around a circle and
What happens as we tweak this value of R?
That's determining not just that we're talking about an exponential function, but which exponential function
There's a nice one-to-one correspondence between all the exponential functions. We might want and values of R here
It stretches things differently so when we put it up to 2
You know it stretches out the real axis a lot more so that f of 1 ends up around where e squared is a little
Above 7 f of negative 1 is much closer to 0 f of I is a 2 radian
Rotation around the circle f of negative I is a negative 2 radian rotation
And of course we can get to our favorite formula that if that were pi that we had as our scaling constant
Then the real axis gets stretched out quite a lot
You know f of 1 is sitting off at e to the pi which is very close to 20 plus pi
Which is always fun and f of negative 1 extremely close to 0 so it's really stretched out that real axis
And it's also stretched out things in the unit circle direction so that
Getting to f of I or f of negative I walks halfway around the circle, so that's all well and good now
How would we think about a function like?
2 to the X which is what?
We would also write as X of
X of the natural log of 2 times X so we kind of move our yellow dot representing the value of R
To around 0.69 still no imaginary part just a real number 0.69 or so
That's the natural log of 2 well you can see that f of 1 lands on 2
Which is why we want to call this function 2 to the X
f of 1 half actually sorry f of negative 1 lands right on 1 half f of I
It's some walk around the unit circle very specifically it's going to be 0.69 radians around the unit circle and
Now we could have a little bit more fun and say what would happen if we were to change this to instead of being
0.69 instead of being the natural log of 2 make it I times the natural log of 2 so that we're really thinking of
Something that might have an exponential base to it. This would be what we might think of is 2 times I
Raised to a power
Well if we move that yellow dot which is representing R off of the real axis and onto the imaginary axis it swaps the roles
of
the
teal dots and all of the maroon dots in this context which remember came from being the positive and imaginary axes and it should make
Sense that it swaps their roles because what does it mean if we take the input space and we multiply it by I?
It means we're rotating that input space so everything that was the real number axis
Turns into the imaginary axis and everything that was the imaginary axis is getting turned into the real axis
So for us what that means is our new exponential function where our value of R is now purely imaginary
Takes all of the real numbers
And it just wraps them around a circle and it takes all the imaginary numbers, and it's putting them onto the real number line
So in particular let's say we scale this thing up so that we're sitting at around pi halves times I
Well, what does that actually mean that means it takes the real number one?
To the value I which is the sense in which we want to write this function as I to the power X
Right it just tempts us to write it not as this abstract looking thing
X of R times X where R is equal to pi halves I don't know we just want to write it as I to the X
Even if that's a little ambiguous
what that really means is just that the function we're dealing with outputs I at 1 and
if it's an exponential function that
And we're asking what does it do to the value I?
What is I to the power I in this case it shoves it to around 0.2 around a fifth
But there's many different exponential functions that would have this property of putting f of 1 onto the number I
So if we were to scale it up even further
I don't think I have it animated here
But if we were to take that yellow dot and raise it up until it got to 5 halves times pi I
What you would see is that the unit circle?
Is rotated around on itself so that f of negative f of 1 would rotate around another 2 pi radians and land where it is
But it would stretch out the real axis a lot more
Which was the sense in which another output of I to the I is a much much smaller number
It was around what was it 0.0003 or so
But we can also see what I think is quite fun
What happens if we consider alternate expressions that we want to interpret as 2 to the power X right?
So when R is a purely real number the natural log of 2 kind of makes sense that when you plug it in here
The expression we get is what we want to write as 2 to the power X
But what if we start moving it in the imaginary direction? Okay, and what I'll first do is I'll move it up by pi I units
Now what's going on here?
We have X of R times X and R is equal to this value, which is the natural log of 2 plus pi times I
What that means is that when we plug in 1
f of 1 is at negative 2 so we want to write this function as negative 2 to the power X
right and that's actually something that
You know, it's it's a little deceptively simple when we write a negative number to a power
Negative 2
To the power X it doesn't at first look like this necessarily it brings us into the complex numbers in any way
but of course when we plug in even a value like
1 half
Where we're kind of asking for a square root of negative 2 we realize that we want to write this as something like I
times the square root of 2
But if you were to look at this function negative 2 to the power X in the full complex domain that it's dealing with
What you're looking at is a function that takes the value of 1 to negative 2
And if it does that what it does to the rest of the real number line is it kind of spirals it outward?
So we see that f of negative 1 sits at negative 1 half
About where you would expect if you were to follow to f of 1 half
It would sit exactly on the imaginary line and f of 1 half would be square root of 2
Well, my mouse is not where I want it to be. It would be around square root of 2
times I and
As you continue further on this is showing you all of the real value powers of negative 2 to the X it necessarily
spirals around
But we could also move our value of R even higher and get it up to around tau times I around six point two eight times
I and in that context this is another function that we would want to write as something like 2 to the X
because
For any whole number to whole number that you plug in for X it will look like repeated multiplication
And it even has kind of reasonable values for things like 1 half where it spits out the negative square root instead of a positive
Square root, but what it's actually doing is a transformation to the plane
Where it puts everything is the real number line ends up being a very tightly wound
Spiral that goes around and it just spirals in such a way that f of 1 lands right on the number 2
So it is in that sense that we could say
2 to the X is
Is plausibly interpreted as a separate exponential function from the one that we are traditionally used to
So I think with all of that I will I will leave things for today
And I'll just leave you with a couple lingering questions to think about okay, so
If you want to think of I to the I as being a multi-valued expression right you could you could say we adopt a convention
Fancifully you'd say you choose a branch of the natural logarithm function
And maybe that locks you into this being e to the negative pi halves
But if you say this kind of wants to be infinitely many different values like the various ones that we saw
How many values does 2 to the 1 third want to be in the same sense?
Where we are replacing 2 with various different
various different options for e to the X
Such that e to the X equals 2 how many different values does that want to be or how many values does 2 to the 3?
10ths want to be
Phrased differently of all of the let me say of all of the exponential functions
F of X which satisfy oh have I written it down somewhere
f of X that satisfies
All of these properties that I've written so if it satisfies all of these
and if f of 1 is equal to 2
Right how many different outputs are we going to get when we plug in X equals 3 10ths for the various options for what function?
That is and how many outputs are we going to get?
For 2 to the pi for the various functions that 2 to the X could represent if we're thinking of 2 to the X as some
kind of exponential function
Exponential in the sense of these sort of abstract properties
and
if we
yeah, if we if we have a
Class of different such functions, and we want to plug in pi it makes me laugh
Just because it's such a I know kind of a funny answer that pops out as you're trying to think about it
so those are the questions that I'll leave you with and I think this is you know my
My central question in approaching today's lecture was whether I wanted it to be
Kind of describing like these abstract properties of exponential functions
And it's just cool to me that starting from those abstract properties you get locked into the idea of e to the rx or more
Just you know I think more honestly written exp of r times x for different values of r
That it locks you in that far
But it doesn't lock you in as far as having an unambiguous
Notion of what 2 to the power x should be much less something like I to the power x
The risk in that of course is that sometimes people don't love abstraction and sometimes
It doesn't come off as approachable
But if that's the case you know you just let me know I think I think there's a whole interesting circle of thoughts that surrounds
All of this stuff to include power towers because if you want to
Actually talk about power towers like we were last time in the context of complex numbers or even with negative bases
You have to be thinking through things like this, so it was a question that we had up on screen
Yeah, what happens if we do this for I to the power I?
Titration you know let's just try this let's just go ahead and try a power tower
Where we're raising I to a given power and see what what pops out of it, so it wasn't planning on doing this
But we can we can always pull up Python and essentially do what we were doing last time
So the way that this would work is we were starting off with some base value and then for some kind of range
What were we doing we were taking a and we're going to reassign it to be whatever
The base which in this case is I raised to the power of a should be
Okay, cool, so we're going to do that and then we're going to print off the value of a let's just do this for
Yeah, it's a much bigger number like 200
So it seems like what happens is
There's potential for chaos with these things like sometimes. It's not that you've landed on a stable a
Stable value or it's not even that you've diverged it could be that you're bouncing between a cycle of values or
That you're like literally bouncing in a way. That's it's not periodic or anything and it's actually chaotic I
Suspect that doesn't happen for I but it's a thing to potentially look out for it looks like it does kind of stabilize
Maybe there's some little subjection to numerical error
But we stay pretty consistently around something with a real part of 0.43 and 0.36
Now what I would want to emphasize though is this expression
So let's set a back to be equal to 1 this expression of taking I to the power of a remember
That's a little bit ambiguous. It depends on what choice of the function. I we actually have so let me let me import
NumPy so I have the exponential function let me go
For our big range like we had before
Rather than writing it as you know something that's like I to the power of X
I'm gonna write it as the exponential function of a different constant
right a
Different constant that I'm gonna make I want it to be 5 pi halves, so I'll do 5
pi
halves times I so it's a complex number and
It's got 5 pi halves as the imaginary part
So this is 5 pi halves times I and what am I doing?
I'm exponentiating that so I want to multiply a onto the inside there, okay?
This is basically another way that you could interpret the expression I to the X
Thankfully you would say you've chosen a different branch of the natural log function
But it is another function which we could iterate on itself and see what happens and we might get a different result
Very interesting okay, so we actually have a different result. It looks like what ends up happening is it bounces between two values
Oh
Wow is it period three that's interesting period three implies chaos, so we've got seven point three five then zero then point nine nine
So it looks like it gets into the cycle of bouncing between three separate values even though
In theory in both of those cases we were doing something that was I to the X iterated on itself it has everything to do
With what actual function you think I to the X is referring to so in that sense
The power tower question is ambiguous
Usually you just choose it to be the pi halves I variant, but it's more fun to see that it can be multiple things all right
We have addition multiplication exponentiation titration can we think of something in between?
halfway between multiplication and exponentiation oh
that's an
I mean
I love the spirit of it because each one of them it comes down to like a discrete step of
You're repeating the previous operation, but oftentimes in math when you have something initially defined in terms of repetition like
Exponentiation you can extend it beyond that I can't think of anything off the top of my head, but that's an interesting question
I don't know if that's been
That's an extended notion. I mean you have things like fractional derivatives you have things like fractional and complex exponents
So it doesn't seem outlandish
But I'm not familiar with one myself
And then lastly do complex numbers to the power of complex number values arise in physics, and if yes
How does one decide which values are valid so I?
Can't think of if they necessary that's right scene switching. I can't think of if they
Come up in physics in like a direct sense, and this is probably just because I'm not a physicist so I
Would say like ask ask your neighborhood physicist and see see what they have to say
I mean clearly
The point of teaching the lesson here is that the thoughts that you have to go through to make sense out of it do build
a stronger relationship with exponentials things like it's not just more natural to represent them as e to the rx
Once you get to complex numbers you kind of have to represent them that way whereas previously in like physics or other real-world contexts
It's something that's just nice