I have two seemingly unrelated challenges for you. The first relates to music, and the
second gives a foundational result in measure theory, which is the formal underpinning for
how mathematicians define integration and probability. The second challenge, which I'll
get to about halfway through the video, has to do with covering numbers with open sets,
and is very counterintuitive. Or at least, when I first saw it, I was confused for a
while. Foremost, I'd like to explain what's going on, but I also plan to share a surprising
connection that it has with music. Here's the first challenge. I'm going to play a musical
note with a given frequency, let's say 220 Hz. Then I'm going to choose some number between
1 and 2, which we'll call R, and play a second musical note whose frequency is R times the
frequency of the first note, 220. For some values of R, like 1.5, the two notes will
sound harmonious together, but for others, like the square root of 2, they sound cacophonous.
Your task is to determine whether a given ratio R will give a pleasant sound or an unpleasant
one just by analyzing the number, and without listening to the notes. One way to answer,
especially if your name is Pythagoras, might be to say that two notes sound good together
when the ratio is a rational number, and bad when it's irrational. For instance, a ratio
of 3 halves gives a musical fifth, 4 thirds gives a musical fourth, 8 fifths gives a major
sixth, and so on. Here's my best guess for why this is the case. A musical note is made
up of beats played in rapid succession, for instance 220 beats per second. When the ratio
of frequencies of two notes is rational, there's a detectable pattern in those beats, which
when we slow it down, we hear as a rhythm instead of as a harmony. Evidently, when our
brains pick up on this pattern, the two notes sound nice together. However, most rational
numbers actually sound pretty bad, like 211 over 198, or 1093 divided by 826. The issue,
of course, is that these rational numbers are somehow more complicated than the other
ones. Our ears don't pick up on the pattern of the beats. One simple way to measure complexity
of rational numbers is to consider the size of the denominator when it's written in reduced
form. So we might edit our original answer to only admit fractions with low denominators,
say less than 10. Even still, this doesn't quite capture harmoniousness, since plenty
of notes sound good together even when the ratio of their frequencies is irrational,
so long as it's close to a harmonious rational number. And it's a good thing too, because
many instruments, such as pianos, are not tuned in terms of rational intervals, but
are tuned such that each half step increase corresponds with multiplying the original
frequency by the 12th root of 2, which is irrational. If you're curious about why
this is done, Henry at MinutePhysics recently did a video that gives a very nice explanation.
This means that if you take a harmonious interval, like a fifth, the ratio of frequencies when
played on a piano will not be a nice rational number like you expect, in this case 3 halves,
but will instead be some power of the 12th root of 2, in this case 2 to the 7 over 12,
which is irrational, but very close to 3 halves. Similarly, a musical fourth corresponds to
2 to the 5 twelfths, which is very close to 4 thirds. In fact, the reason it works so
well to have 12 notes in the chromatic scale is that powers of the 12th root of 2 have
this strange tendency to be within a 1% margin of error of simple rational numbers.
So now you might say that a ratio R will produce a harmonious pair of notes if it is sufficiently
close to a rational number with a sufficiently small denominator. How close depends on how
discerning your ear is, and how small a denominator depends on the intricacy of harmonic patterns
your ear has been trained to pick up on. After all, maybe someone with a particularly
acute musical sense would be able to hear and find pleasure in the pattern resulting
from more complicated fractions, like 23 over 21, or 35 over 43, as well as numbers closely
approximating those fractions. This leads me to an interesting question.
Suppose there is a musical savant who finds pleasure in all pairs of notes whose frequencies
have a rational ratio, even the super complicated ratios that you and I would find cacophonous.
Is it the case that she would find all ratios R between 1 and 2 harmonious, even the irrational
ones? After all, for any given real number, you can always find a rational number arbitrarily
close to it, just like 3 halves is really close to 2 to the 7 over 12.
So, this brings us to challenge number 2.
Mathematicians like to ask riddles about covering various sets with open intervals, and the
answers to these riddles have a strange tendency to become famous lemmas of theorems. By open
interval, I just mean the continuous stretch of real numbers strictly greater than some
number a, but strictly less than some other number b, where b is of course greater than
My challenge to you involves covering all of the rational numbers between 0 and 1 with
open intervals. When I say cover, all this means is that each particular rational number
lies inside at least one of your intervals. The most obvious way to do this is to just
use the entire interval from 0 to 1 itself and call it done, but the challenge here is
that the sum of the lengths of your intervals must be strictly less than 1.
To aid you in this seemingly impossible task, you're allowed to use infinitely many intervals.
Even still, the task might feel impossible, since the rational numbers are dense in the
real numbers, meaning any stretch, no matter how small, contains infinitely many rational
numbers. So how could you possibly cover all of the rational numbers without just covering
the entire interval from 0 to 1 itself, which would mean the total length of your open intervals
has to be at least the length of the entire interval from 0 to 1? Then again, I wouldn't
be asking if there wasn't a way to do it.
First, we enumerate the rational numbers between 0 and 1, meaning we organize them into an
infinitely long list. There are many ways to do this, but one natural way that I'll
choose is to start with ½, followed by ⅓ and ⅔, then ¼ and ¾, we don't write down
¼ since it's already appeared as ½, then all reduced fractions with denominator 5,
all reduced fractions with denominator 6, continuing on and on in this fashion. Every
fraction will appear exactly once in this list in its reduced form, and it gives us
a meaningful way to talk about the first rational number, the second rational number,
the 42nd rational number, things like that.
Next, to ensure that each rational is covered, we're going to assign one specific interval
to each rational. Once we remove the intervals from the geometry of our setup and just think
of them in a list, each one responsible for one rational number, it seems much clearer
that the sum of their lengths can be less than 1, since each particular interval can
be as small as you want and still cover its designated rational. In fact, the sum can
be any positive number. Just choose an infinite sum with positive terms that converges to
1, like ½, plus ¼, plus ⅛, plus ⅛, on and on, then choose any desired value of epsilon
greater than 0, like 0.5, and multiply all of the terms in the sum by epsilon so that
you have an infinite sum converging to epsilon. Now, scale the nth interval to have a length
equal to the nth term in the sum. Notice, this means your intervals start getting really
small really fast, so small that you can't really see most of them in this animation,
but it doesn't matter, since each one is only responsible for covering one rational.
I've said it already, but I'll say it again because it's so amazing, epsilon can be whatever positive number we want, so not only can our sum be less than 1, it can be arbitrarily small.
This is one of those results where even after seeing the proof, it still defies intuition.
The discord here is that the proof has us thinking analytically, with the rational numbers
in a list, but our intuition has us thinking geometrically, with all the rational numbers
as a dense set on the interval, where you can't skip over any continuous stretch because
that would contain infinitely many rationals. So let's get a visual understanding for
what's going on.
Brief side note here, I had trouble deciding on how to illustrate small intervals, since
if I scale the parentheses with the interval, you won't be able to see them at all, but
if I just push the parentheses together, they cross over in a way that's potentially confusing.
Nevertheless, I decided to go with the ugly chromosomal cross, so keep in mind, the interval
this represents is that tiny stretch between the centers of each parenthesis.
Ok, back to the visual intuition.
Consider when epsilon equals 0.3, meaning if I choose a number between 0 and 1 at random,
there's a 70% chance that it's outside those infinitely many intervals.
What does it look like to be outside the intervals?
The square root of 2 over 2 is among those 70%, and I'm going to zoom in on it.
As I do so, I'll draw the first 10 intervals in our list within our scope of vision.
As we get closer and closer to the square root of 2 over 2, even though you will always
find rationals within your field of view, the intervals placed on top of those rationals
get really small, really fast.
You might say that for any sequence of rational numbers approaching the square root of 2 over
2, the intervals containing the elements of that sequence shrink faster than the sequence
converges.
Notice intervals are really small if they show up late in the list, and rationals show
up late in the list when they have large denominators.
So the fact that the square root of 2 over 2 is among the 70% not covered by our intervals
is in a sense a way to formalize the otherwise vague idea that the only rational numbers
close to it have a large denominator.
That is to say, the square root of 2 over 2 is cacophonous.
In fact, let's use a smaller epsilon, say 0.01, and shift our setup to lie on top of
the interval from 1 to 2 instead of from 0 to 1.
Then which numbers fall among that elite 1% covered by our tiny intervals?
Almost all of them are harmonious.
For instance, the harmonious irrational number 2 to the 7 twelfths is very close to 3 halves,
which has a relatively fat interval sitting on top of it, and the interval around 4 thirds
is smaller, but still fat enough to cover 2 to the 5 twelfths.
Which members of the 1% are cacophonous?
Well, the cacophonous rationals, meaning those with high denominators, and irrationals that
are very very very close to them.
However, think of the savant who finds harmonic patterns in all rational numbers.
You could imagine that for her, harmonious numbers are precisely those 1% covered by
the intervals, provided that her tolerance for error goes down exponentially for more
complicated rationals.
In other words, the seemingly paradoxical fact that you can have a collection of intervals
densely populate a range while only covering 1% of its values corresponds to the fact that
harmonious numbers are rare, even for the savant.
I'm not saying this makes the result more intuitive, in fact, I find it quite surprising
that the savant I defined could find 99% of all ratios cacophonous, but the fact that
these two ideas are connected was simply too beautiful not to share.