I've got that wanderlust, I'm gonna walk the scene We will get back to this buddy at the
end of the video But before that I want to tell you about the Summer of Math Exposition
number 2 So last year we did the Summer of Math Exposition number 1 Which was essentially
an open invitation for people to make explanatory math content That they might have
thought about making before But just get an excuse for us to all do it at the same time
and together The way we did it is we framed it as a contest So we had different
participants, a lot of them were videos, not all of them were videos We had a process
for selecting winners And aside from the competition aspect of it Which is really just
an excuse to have a deadline and have that little extra push to try to make something as
good as you can The most exciting part was just how many really solid pieces of content
came out of that In fact I was curious the other day and I went to look at the analytics
and just looking at the video content Mainly because that's where it's easiest to count
the total number of hits on it Of all of the video submissions to the first Summer of
Math Exposition If we count up all the views that they accumulated It's over 15 million
total views there So we want to do it again If you have some kind of math explainer that
you've been thinking about making and posting online in some capacity Whatever that is
And if you want to use the Summer as an excuse to make it happen There are really just
three main bits of logistics Number 1, subscribe to the official mailing list that we're
going to use for it All of the official communication about things like timelines,
rules for submissions, answers to any questions that people might have had All of it's
going to live there Secondly, the submission deadline is August 15th So try to finish
whatever you're making maybe 5 days before that Because we have to be immovable with some
kind of line And August 15th is going to be that line And then if you want to engage with
other people who are also participating in the event Maybe share some of your work or
get some feedback or just chat about math in general There's a Discord for it And last
year the Discord was really the lifeblood of the whole event I mean,
we had the announcement, we had the choosing of the winners But all of the real community
components of it happened on that Discord in between But with this year I also wanted to
add one tiny little twist to the whole event So I've always thought it might be nice to
somehow play matchmaker between domain experts People like mathematicians or professors
of other kinds Or teachers or professionals The people who have the know-how and the
experience with respect to some technical topic They know the best stories to tell But
maybe they don't have the time to actually put together a video Or they don't have the
video-making skills and content creation skills And then pair them together with content
producers Whether that's people who are really interested in making videos,
video editing, animation Or maybe web developers interested in interactive blog posts
Game developers, artists, whatever the form of content creation might be Because if you
limit your scope to the world of online educational content creation by individuals You
have to live in this little intersection here Between the people who have good lessons
to teach And then the people who have the time and the interest And then the technical
know-how to put together that content But with well-organized collaboration You can get
a lot of good content out of the union of those two sets Rather than just the
intersection And I think a shining example of this would be the entire channel number
file Where you've got Brady, who's a very talented journalist and interviewer and film
creator, videographer And he goes and interviews the various experts out there And a lot
of the experts wouldn't be making their own videos But by pairing together with Brady
they get a really polished and well-thought-out product from it all Another interesting
example of a collaboration like this one is Let me see, what was it called?