I've got that wanderlust, I'm gonna walk the scene
We will get back to this buddy at the end of the video
But before that I want to tell you about the Summer of Math Exposition number 2
So last year we did the Summer of Math Exposition number 1
Which was essentially an open invitation for people to make explanatory math content
That they might have thought about making before
But just get an excuse for us to all do it at the same time and together
The way we did it is we framed it as a contest
So we had different participants, a lot of them were videos, not all of them were videos
We had a process for selecting winners
And aside from the competition aspect of it
Which is really just an excuse to have a deadline and have that little extra push to try to make something as good as you can
The most exciting part was just how many really solid pieces of content came out of that
In fact I was curious the other day and I went to look at the analytics and just looking at the video content
Mainly because that's where it's easiest to count the total number of hits on it
Of all of the video submissions to the first Summer of Math Exposition
If we count up all the views that they accumulated
It's over 15 million total views there
So we want to do it again
If you have some kind of math explainer that you've been thinking about making and posting online in some capacity
Whatever that is
And if you want to use the Summer as an excuse to make it happen
There are really just three main bits of logistics
Number 1, subscribe to the official mailing list that we're going to use for it
All of the official communication about things like timelines, rules for submissions, answers to any questions that people might have had
All of it's going to live there
Secondly, the submission deadline is August 15th
So try to finish whatever you're making maybe 5 days before that
Because we have to be immovable with some kind of line
And August 15th is going to be that line
And then if you want to engage with other people who are also participating in the event
Maybe share some of your work or get some feedback or just chat about math in general
There's a Discord for it
And last year the Discord was really the lifeblood of the whole event
I mean, we had the announcement, we had the choosing of the winners
But all of the real community components of it happened on that Discord in between
But with this year I also wanted to add one tiny little twist to the whole event
So I've always thought it might be nice to somehow play matchmaker between domain experts
People like mathematicians or professors of other kinds
Or teachers or professionals
The people who have the know-how and the experience with respect to some technical topic
They know the best stories to tell
But maybe they don't have the time to actually put together a video
Or they don't have the video-making skills and content creation skills
And then pair them together with content producers
Whether that's people who are really interested in making videos, video editing, animation
Or maybe web developers interested in interactive blog posts
Game developers, artists, whatever the form of content creation might be
Because if you limit your scope to the world of online educational content creation by individuals
You have to live in this little intersection here
Between the people who have good lessons to teach
And then the people who have the time and the interest
And then the technical know-how to put together that content
But with well-organized collaboration
You can get a lot of good content out of the union of those two sets
Rather than just the intersection
And I think a shining example of this would be the entire channel number file
Where you've got Brady, who's a very talented journalist and interviewer and film creator, videographer
And he goes and interviews the various experts out there
And a lot of the experts wouldn't be making their own videos
But by pairing together with Brady they get a really polished and well-thought-out product from it all
Another interesting example of a collaboration like this one is
Let me see, what was it called?
How to construct a leech lattice
It's on the channel for Richard Borcherds
Who's a Fields Medalist mathematician
Who makes a lot of his own videos
Just kind of overhead shot lectures
But this one was a partnership with someone who went in and took one of those lectures
But added some animations and visuals on top
To really help clarify what was being said
Because the whole thing is about lattices in 24 dimensions
Which is hard to picture
It's a very pleasing construction of them
Which is both described and illustrated very beautifully
And to incentivize more collaborations like that one
We've put together a simple space to help people find collaborators
More on that in a moment
And then at least one of the winners that we choose this year
Will be from the set of people who've found a collaborator in this way
And also I will throw my hat into this bunch
And try to partner with some of the people in that space
To maybe make a 3Blue1Brown video
So the way this will work
Might look a little bit weird at first but bear with me
We've set up a GitHub repo
And we're going to use GitHub issues on that repository
As a way of organizing requests for collaboration
So let's say you're a mathematician
You have some idea for a good piece of expository content
Maybe it's a video you think should get made
Or an interactive blog post
But you want to find someone to help you actually carry it out
You would go and create a new issue
You would use the template for a topic seeking a producer
And then you just fill it out with all the details of your idea
And the more details the better
Let's say I was going to partner with some mathematician to produce something
I would be interested in seeing a pretty good outline of the idea
Why it's important, maybe even a storyboard in there
And then on the flip side if you want to produce some kind of content
You know you're an artist or an animator or a video creator
But you're more interested in getting content ideas from the experts than from yourself
You would also create an issue
Use the producer seeking topic template
And then fill that out
So then if you're looking for a collaborator
So let's say I'm going there, I'm looking for mathematicians with interesting ideas
Or artists and animators that I might want to work with
You can take a look at all of the open issues
And the reason for using GitHub for this
Even though that might feel a little bit weird
Is that the tools seem right for what we want
In terms of having a dedicated conversation for each thread
Having nice math embedding in each one of them
Making it easy to link between them
And once you've found your collaborator and you're no longer looking for one
You can close the issue
If that's a totally wild way to do it, feel free to complain at me
But for my part at least, over the next week or two
I'll be in there, I'll take a look through what the requests for collaboration are
I think it would be fun for me at least to find some domain expert
With an interesting topic that I wouldn't have known to produce
And then I was thinking of also finding someone who's interested in content creation
Seems like they have at least a little bit of a portfolio
Such that I can tell if the style would mesh well with whatever topic from the domain expert I end up finding
And then I would be there as a kind of producer and extra collaborator
And we could post the final product on 3Blue1Brown
And so that's the added twist
But other than that, same deal as last year
Again this time we'll choose at least five different winners
And again Brilliant has generously offered to contribute $5,000 for prizes to the winners
So we'll give $1,000 to each one
Also this year, slightly different twist
Each winner will be sent a golden pie creature
Of which only five exist in the whole world
So if that's not enough to get you to contribute, I don't know what will
Other than that, again, all of the official details are in the email list
Take a look at that first post to get all the details that I probably forgot to mention in this video
And honestly, I'm really excited to see what people make
Thanks for watching!