Two years ago, almost to the day actually, I put up the first video on this channel,
about Euler's formula, e to the pi i equals negative one.
As an anniversary of sorts, I want to revisit that same idea.
For one thing, I've always wanted to improve on the presentation, but I wouldn't rehash
an old topic if there wasn't something new to teach.
You see, the idea underlying that video was to take certain concepts from a field in math
called group theory, and show how they give Euler's formula a richer interpretation
than a mere association between numbers.
And two years ago, I thought it might be fun to use those ideas without referencing group
theory itself, or any of the technical terms within it.
But I've come to see that you all actually quite like getting into the math itself, even
if it takes some time.
So here, two years later, let's you and me go through an introduction to the basics
of group theory, building up to how Euler's formula comes to life under this light.
If all you want is a quick explanation of Euler's formula, and if you're comfortable
with vector calculus, I'll go ahead and put up a particularly short explanation on
the screen that you can pause and ponder on.
If it doesn't make sense, don't worry about it, it's not needed for where we're
going.
The reason I want to put out this group theory review, though, is not because I think it's
a better explanation.
Heck, it's not even a complete proof, it's just an intuition really.
It's because it has the chance to change how you think about numbers, and how you think
about algebra.
You see, group theory is all about studying the nature of symmetry.
For example, a square is a very symmetric shape, but what do we actually mean by that?
One way to answer that is to ask about what are all the actions you can take on the square
that leave it looking indistinguishable from how it started.
For example, you could rotate it 90 degrees counterclockwise, and it looks totally the
same to how it started.
You could also flip it around this vertical line, and again, it still looks identical.
In fact, the thing about such perfect symmetry is that it's hard to keep track of what
action has actually been taken, so to help out I'm going to stick on an asymmetric
image here.
We call each one of these actions a symmetry of the square, and all of the symmetries together
make up a group of symmetries, or just group for short.
This particular group consists of 8 symmetries.
There's the action of doing nothing, which is one we count, plus 3 different rotations,
and then there's 4 ways you can flip it over.
In fact, this group of 8 symmetries has a special name, it's called the dihedral group
of order 8.
That's an example of a finite group, consisting of only 8 actions, but a lot of other groups
consist of infinitely many actions.
Think of all possible rotations, for example, of any angle.
Maybe you think of this as a group that acts on a circle, capturing all of the symmetries
of that circle that don't involve flipping it.
Here, every action from this group of rotation lies somewhere on the infinite continuum between
0 and 2 pi radians.
One nice aspect of these actions is that we can associate each one of them with a single
point on the circle itself, the thing being acted on.
You start by choosing some arbitrary point, maybe the one on the right here.
Then every circle symmetry, every possible rotation, takes this marked point to some
unique spot on the circle, and the action itself is completely determined by where it
takes that spot.
This doesn't always happen with groups, but it's nice when it does happen, because
it gives us a way to label the actions themselves, which can otherwise be pretty tricky to think
about.
The study of groups is not just about what a particular set of symmetries is, whether
that's the 8 symmetries of a square, the infinite continuum of symmetries of the circle,
or anything else you dream up.
The real heart and soul of the study is knowing how these symmetries play with each other.
On the square, if I rotate 90 degrees and then flip around the vertical axis, the overall
effect is the same as if I had just flipped over this diagonal line.
So in some sense, that rotation plus the vertical flip equals that diagonal flip.
On the circle, if I rotate 270 degrees and then follow it with a rotation of 120 degrees,
the overall effect is the same as if I had just rotated 30 degrees to start with.
So in this circle group, a 270 degree rotation plus a 120 degree rotation equals a 30 degree
rotation.
And in general, with any group, any collection of these sorts of symmetric actions, there's
a kind of arithmetic, where you can always take two actions and add them together to
get a third one, by applying one after the other.
Or maybe you think of it as multiplying actions, it doesn't really matter.
The point is that there is some way to combine the two actions to get out another one.
That collection of underlying relations, all associations between pairs of actions and
the single action that's equivalent to applying one after the other, that's really what
makes a group a group.
It's actually crazy how much of modern math is rooted in, well, this, in understanding
how a collection of actions is organized by this relation, this relation between pairs
of actions and the single action you get by composing them.
Groups are extremely general.
A lot of different ideas can be framed in terms of symmetries and composing symmetries.
And maybe the most familiar example is numbers, just ordinary numbers.
There are two separate ways to think about numbers as a group.
One where composing actions will look like addition, and another where composing actions
will look like multiplication.
It's a little weird, because we don't usually think of numbers as actions, we usually
think of them as counting things.
But let me show you what I mean.
Think of all the ways you can slide a number line left or right along itself.
This collection of all sliding actions is a group, what you might think of as the group
of symmetries on an infinite line.
And in the same way that actions from the circle group could be associated with individual
points on that circle, this is another one of those special groups where we can associate
each action with a unique point on the thing that it's actually acting on.
You just follow where the point that starts at 0 ends up.
For example, the number 3 is associated with the action of sliding right by 3 units.
The number negative 2 is associated with the action of sliding 2 units to the left,
since that's the unique action that drags the point at 0 over to the point at negative
2.
The number 0 itself is associated with the action of doing nothing.
This group of sliding actions, each one of which is associated with a unique real number,
has a special name, the additive group of real numbers.
The reason the word additive is in there is because of what the group operation of applying
one action followed by another looks like.
If I slide right by 3 units, and then slide right by 2 units, the overall effect is the
same as if I slid right by 3 plus 2, or 5 units.
Simple enough, we're just adding the distances of each slide.
But the point here is that this gives an alternate view for what numbers even are.
They are one example in a much larger category of groups, groups of symmetries acting on
some object, and the arithmetic of adding numbers is just one example of the arithmetic
that any group of symmetries has within it.
We could also extend this idea, instead asking about the sliding actions on the complex plane.
The newly introduced numbers i, 2i, 3i, and so on on this vertical line would all be associated
with vertical sliding motions, since those are the actions that drag the point at 0 up
to the relevant point on that vertical line.
The point over here at 3 plus 2i would be associated with the action of sliding the
plane in such a way that drags 0 up and to the right to that point.
And it should make sense why we call this 3 plus 2i.
That diagonal sliding action is the same as first sliding by 3 to the right, and then
following it with a slide that corresponds to 2i, which is 2 units vertically.
Similarly, let's get a feel for how composing any two of these actions generally breaks
down.
Consider this slide by 3 plus 2i action, as well as this slide by 1 minus 3i action, and
imagine applying one of them right after the other.
The overall effect, the composition of these two sliding actions, is the same as if we
had slid 3 plus 1 to the right, and 2 minus 3 vertically.
Notice how that involves adding together each component.
So composing sliding actions is another way to think about what adding complex numbers
actually means.
This collection of all sliding actions on the 2d complex plane goes by the name the
additive group of complex numbers.
Again, the upshot here is that numbers, even complex numbers, are just one example of a
group, and the idea of addition can be thought of in terms of successively applying actions.
But numbers, schizophrenic as they are, also lead a completely different life as a completely
different kind of group.
Consider a new group of actions on the number line, all ways that you can stretch or squish
it, keeping everything evenly spaced, and keeping that number 0 fixed in place.
Yet again, this group of actions has that nice property, where we can associate each
action in the group with a specific point on the thing it's acting on.
In this case, follow where the point that starts at the number 1 goes.
There is one and only one stretching action that brings that point at 1 to the point at
3, for instance, namely stretching by a factor of 3.
Likewise, there is one and only one action that brings that point at 1 to the point at
1 half, namely squishing by a factor of 1 half.
I like to imagine using one hand to fix the number 0 in place, and using the other to
drag the number 1 wherever I like, while the rest of the number line does whatever it takes
to stay evenly spaced.
In this way, every single positive number is associated with a unique stretching or
squishing action.
Now notice what composing actions looks like in this group.
If I apply the stretch by 3 action, and then follow it with the stretch by 2 action, the
overall effect is the same as if I had just applied the stretch by 6 action, the product
of the two original numbers.
In general, applying one of these actions followed by another corresponds with multiplying
the numbers they're associated with.
In fact, the name for this group is the multiplicative group of positive real numbers.
So multiplication, ordinary familiar multiplication, is one more example of this very general and
very far-reaching idea of groups, and the arithmetic within groups.
We can also extend this idea to the complex plane.
Again, I like to think of fixing 0 in place with one hand, and dragging around the point
at 1, keeping everything else evenly spaced while I do so.
But this time, as we drag the number 1 to places that are off the real number line,
we see that our group includes not only stretching and squishing actions, but actions that have
some rotational component as well.
The quintessential example of this is the action associated with that point at i, one
unit above 0.
What it takes to drag the point at 1 to that point at i is a 90 degree rotation.
So the multiplicative action associated with i is a 90 degree rotation.
And notice, if I apply that action twice in a row, the overall effect is to flip the plane
180 degrees, and that is the unique action that brings the point at 1 over to negative
1.
So in this sense, i times i equals negative 1, meaning the action associated with i, followed
by that same action associated with i, has the same overall effect as the action associated
with negative 1.
As another example, here's the action associated with 2 plus i, dragging 1 up to that point.
If you want, you could think of this as broken down as a rotation by 30 degrees, followed
by a stretch by a factor of square root of 5.
And in general, every one of these multiplicative actions is some combination of a stretch or
a squish, an action associated with some point on the positive real number line, followed
by a pure rotation, where pure rotations are associated with points on this circle,
the one with radius 1.
This is very similar to how the sliding actions in the additive group could be broken down
as some pure horizontal slide, represented with points on the real number line, plus
some purely vertical slide, represented with points on that vertical line.
That comparison of how actions in each group breaks down is going to be important, so remember
In each one, you can break down any action as some purely real number action, followed
by something specific to complex numbers, whether that's vertical slides for the additive
group, or pure rotations for the multiplicative group.
So that's our quick introduction to groups.
A group is a collection of symmetric actions on some mathematical object, whether that's
a square, a circle, the real number line, or anything else you dream up.
And every group has a certain arithmetic, where you can combine two actions by applying
one after the other, and asking what other action from the group gives the same overall
effect.
Numbers, both real and complex numbers, can be thought of in two different ways as a group.
They can act by sliding, in which case the group arithmetic just looks like ordinary
addition, or they can act by stretching-squishing-rotating actions, in which case the group arithmetic
looks just like multiplication.
And with that, let's talk about exponentiation.
Our first introduction to exponents is to think of them in terms of repeated multiplication.
The meaning of something like 2 cubed is to take 2x2x2, and the meaning of something like
2 to the 5th is 2x2x2x2x2.
And a consequence of this, something you might call the exponential property, is that if
I add two numbers in the exponent, say 2 to the 3 plus 5, this can be broken down as the
product of 2 to the 3rd times 2 to the 5.
And when you expand things, this seems reasonable enough, right?
But expressions like 2 to the ½, or 2 to the –1, and much less 2 to the i don't
really make sense when you think of exponents as repeated multiplication.
What does it mean to multiply 2 by itself half of a time, or –1 of a time?
So we do something very common throughout math, and extend beyond the original definition,
which only makes sense for counting numbers, to something that applies to all sorts of
numbers.
But we don't just do this randomly.
If you think back to how fractional and negative exponents are defined, it's always motivated
by trying to make sure that this property, 2 to the x plus y equals 2 to the x times
2 to the y, still holds.
To see what this might mean for complex exponents, think about what this property is saying from
a group theory light.
It's saying that adding the inputs corresponds with multiplying the outputs, and that makes
it very tempting to think of the inputs not merely as numbers, but as members of the additive
group of sliding actions, and to think of the outputs not merely as numbers, but as
members of this multiplicative group of stretching and squishing actions.
It is weird and strange to think about functions that take in one kind of action and spit out
another kind of action, but this is something that actually comes up all the time throughout
group theory.
And this exponential property is very important for this association between groups.
It guarantees that if I compose two sliding actions, maybe a slide by negative 1 and then
a slide by positive 2, it corresponds to composing the two output actions, in this case squishing
by 2 to the negative 1 and then stretching by 2 squared.
Mathematicians would describe a property like this by saying that the function preserves
the group structure, in the sense that the arithmetic within a group is what gives it
its structure, and a function like this exponential plays nicely with that arithmetic.
Functions between groups that preserve the arithmetic like this are really important
throughout group theory, enough so that they've earned themselves a nice fancy name, homomorphisms.
Think about what all this means for associating the additive group in the complex plane with
the multiplicative group in the complex plane.
We already know that when you plug in a real number to 2 to the x, you get out a real number,
a positive real number in fact.
So this exponential function takes any purely horizontal slide and turns it into some pure
stretching or squishing action.
So wouldn't you agree that it would be reasonable for this new dimension of additive actions
slides up and down to map directly into this new dimension of multiplicative actions, pure
rotations.
Those vertical sliding actions correspond to points on this vertical axis, and those
rotating multiplicative actions correspond to points on the circle with radius 1.
So what it would mean for an exponential function like 2 to the x to map purely vertical
slides into pure rotations would be that complex numbers on this vertical line, multiples of
i, get mapped to complex numbers on this unit circle.
In fact, for the function 2 to the x, the input i, a vertical slide of one unit, happens
to map to a rotation of about 0.693 radians, that is, a walk around the unit circle that
covers 0.693 units of distance.
With a different exponential function, say 5 to the x, that input i, a vertical slide
of one unit, would map to a rotation of about 1.609 radians, a walk around the unit circle
covering exactly 1.609 units of distance.
What makes the number e special is that when the exponential e to the x maps vertical slides
to rotations, a vertical slide of one unit, corresponding to i, maps to a rotation of
exactly one radian, a walk around the unit circle covering a distance of exactly one.
A vertical slide of two units would map to a rotation of two radians.
A three unit slide up corresponds to a rotation of three radians.
A vertical slide of exactly pi units up, corresponding to the input pi times i, maps to a rotation
of exactly pi radians, halfway around the circle, and that's the multiplicative action
associated with the number negative one.
Now you might ask, why e?
Why not some other base?
The full answer resides in calculus, that's the birthplace of e, and where it's even
defined.
Again, I'll leave up another explanation on the screen if you're hungry for a fuller
description and if you're comfortable with the calculus, but at a high level I'll say
that it has to do with the fact that all exponential functions are proportional to their own derivative,
but e to the x alone is the one that's actually equal to its own derivative.
The important point that I want to make here though, is that if you view things from the
lens of group theory, thinking of the inputs to an exponential function as sliding actions,
and thinking of the outputs as stretching and rotating actions, it gives a very vivid
way to read what a formula like this is even saying.
When you read it, you can think that exponentials in general map purely vertical slides, the
additive actions that are perpendicular to the real number line, into pure rotations,
which are in some sense perpendicular to the real number stretching actions.
And moreover, e to the x does this in the very special way that ensures that a vertical
slide of pi units corresponds to a rotation of exactly pi radians, the 180 degree rotation
associated with the number negative one.
To finish things off here, I want to show a way that you can think about this function
e to the x as a transformation of the complex plane.
But before that, just two quick messages.
I've mentioned before just how thankful I am to you, the community, for making these
videos possible through Patreon, but in much the same way that numbers become more meaningful
when you think of them as actions, gratitude is also best expressed as an action.
So I've decided to turn off ads on new videos for their first month, in the hopes of giving
you all a better viewing experience.
This video was sponsored by Emerald Cloud Lab, and actually I was the one to reach out
to them on this one, since it's a company I find particularly inspiring.
Emerald is a very unusual startup, half software, half biotech.
The Cloud Lab that they're building essentially enables biologists and chemists to conduct
research through a software platform instead of working in a lab.
Scientists can program experiments, which are then executed remotely and robotically
in Emerald's industrialized research lab.
I know some of the people at the company, and the software challenges they're working
on are really interesting.
Currently they're looking to hire software engineers and web developers for their engineering
team, as well as applied mathematicians and computer scientists for their scientific computing
team.
If you're interested in applying, whether that's now or a few months from now, there
are a couple special links in the description of this video, and if you apply through those,
it lets Emerald know you heard about them through this channel.
Alright, so e to the x transforming the plane.
I like to imagine first rolling that plane into a cylinder, wrapping all those vertical
lines into circles, and then taking that cylinder and kinda smooshing it onto the plane around
zero, where each of those concentric circles spaced out exponentially correspond with what
started off as vertical lines.