Here's an art puzzle that feels impossible but is secretly related to some deep math.
Try creating a picture that has at least three colors, so that any point that's on the
boundary of one color is on the boundary of all of them.
So for example in this diagram with red, green, and blue, the middle point is on the boundary
of all three colors, so it's fine, but this whole line of points here is disallowed, since
they're all on the boundary of red and green, but not blue.
Likewise these other two border lines are disallowed.
So maybe you try to correct that, you go and add a bunch of blue blobs on the boundary
of the red and green, and do something similar on the other border lines, but now the smaller
boundaries of those blobs would cause a problem, so maybe you try to correct that even further
and keep iterating and iterating.
This might feel impossible, and with smooth shapes it is, but there are actually infinitely
many solutions.
One example is a family of figures known as Newton fractals.
What's very fun is that the diagrams are closely tied to a kind of chaos, a chaos that emerges
from a common algorithm that's used all over the place in engineering to find numerical
solutions to equations.