Hello and welcome to the very first episode of Lockdown Math.
So in this first lecture, what I'm going to talk with you guys about is the
quadratic formula. And traditionally, I think the quadratic
formula is one of the most famously memorized things in high school. We almost
all kind of have this song that sings in our head
related to it. And yet, if you actually ask someone,
how often do you expect you're going to be using this in the real world?
I mean, how many people are going to give an answer that's greater than zero to
that question? Now what I want to do is give you guys a
lesson regarding the quadratic formula that's a little bit different from the
traditional approach. And the main thing I want to focus on is
connecting it to other common patterns in math
that are useful for general problem solving. Now the tactic that I'm going to
talk through, it's not the usual completing the squares bit that some
people will learn in high school. And when you learn that, you often think,
okay, in principle, I could re-derive the quadratic formula,
but frankly, it's going to be a bit of a pain. What I will talk about is somewhat
similar to something that Po-Shen Lo put out a
couple months ago. For those of you who don't know him, he
has a YouTube channel, but more than that, he's the coach of the USIMO team,
and he has a company called X-Pi, does a lot of great math stuff.
So he talked about kind of an alternate way that we could teach the quadratic
formula. The way I'm going to talk about it is a
little bit different from how he did, but certainly very similar in spirit.
Again, the upshot that I want you guys to come away with is the fact that
you should connect this to other common patterns in math so as to make yourself
a better problem solver. And that should be the main takeaway
lesson for, you know, this particular topic. Now,
these lectures in general, I'm going to be shooting for something
roughly on the order of an hour for each one of them, and the dynamic that I'm
going for is one where there's questions that I'm asking the
audience, and then the audience interacts with it in a very, well, in a
very live way. Now, the thing about live stuff, though,
is sometimes it doesn't go the way that you intended.
So the general technology that we're going to have for this is going to
involve me pulling up some kind of question, like,
for example, right here, the question is asking kind of
facetiously about your relationship with the quadratic formula,
and I even had this going over the intro animation for you guys.
And then what you see is the statistics associated with what the
answers, you know, other people are entering are,
and they'll kind of get overlaid. We see the bars. At the moment, all you see are
question marks. We don't know what the most common answer was,
but at some point I can choose to grade that, and then we'll see.
Except for the fact that it looks like there's quite a few of you guys, and it
is giving our servers a little bit of trouble.
So we have a couple people who are going to be working on that in the
background. In the meantime, I'll just be asking the
questions that are pushing us through the lesson.
For future streams, this will hopefully be a much more dynamic situation where
as you answer, we're kind of grading it and you see how it's going.
For this particular one, who knows? Some magic might happen halfway through.
But there's a lot of excitement among you guys right now, which is awesome,
and I love that. And let's see if we can translate that into some of the math
itself. So one of the questions that I was going
to ask is, how many times do you expect to use
the quadratic formula? And when we were doing this a little bit
earlier with a couple people, for sure the most common answer was
zero. Zero times is when I think I'll use the quadratic formula
outside of school. And a funny story about that, I actually
was once giving this talk at Pixar where I brought it up as this example of
something that we teach every student, and it's unclear why.
They're not going to use it. And I should have known better than to say this to a
bunch of engineers at Pixar, because one of them looked at me and he
was like, oh, I'll have you know, I actually use the quadratic formula all
the time. His name was Tim Babb, and he very kindly
sent over basically a storyboard for a video, something I think he was pitching
me on. And the basic idea, he was talking
through an image that he created purely with computer graphics. I think
this is totally beautiful. You would think that this is a photograph
of some reflective billiard balls, but this is entirely computer graphics.
And the tactics used behind this involve something called ray tracing.
So the basic idea there is you sort of imagine
a camera shooting out a bunch of rays through each pixel
of your screen, and then depending on whether it hits the sphere and how it
hits the sphere, that tells you how to color each pixel.
Now part of that problem though is to know, hey, if I'm shooting a ray
in some direction, will it hit a given sphere?
And so what you might do is define a certain vector, you might imagine an
amount of time that the beam of light is moving,
and then you can come up with a graph for how close
is that ray to the sphere as a function of time. And in some cases, if it passes
through the sphere, you're going to have two solutions there.
And once you work out the math, it turns out this is a quadratic equation,
so what you need is a systematic way to plug in these solutions
to a quadratic equation, and it needs to be programmatic, it needs to be some
kind of formula because you're doing this for every single pixel on the
screen. You also need to be able to know is it
just glancing off of the sphere, or does it not go through it at all?
And again, all of that comes down to solving a quadratic.
And this particular engineer at Pixar, he did a loose back of the envelope
calculation for me that suggested the movie Coco probably
used the quadratic formula over a trillion times, just given how
many lights there are for every single frame in that shot.
So in some very real sense, the quadratic formula is useful
to the point of being used a trillion times to produce a movie.
Nevertheless, I don't necessarily think that's representative of
most people's future, and it could be the case that the reason we teach people
this formula is because maybe they happen to be that Pixar
employee. You never know what's going to be useful.
But I want to make the case again that we can connect it to other patterns and
problem solving bits in math. And the way that I'm going to go about
this is to start in a place that's frankly
completely unrelated to quadratics and quadratic functions.
I just want to talk about some mental math tricks, okay?
Because I think if you are thinking about arithmetic, something
very basic, something we do in elementary school, and you think about it
deeply enough, some of the patterns that you observe
become relevant to stuff that you're doing later on.
So for example, let's say I ask you to factor the number 35.
You know, it's easy to see that five goes into it, and
it goes into it seven times, each of those is prime, great.
We know how to factor 35. Now factoring is kind of an annoying task, the bigger
the numbers get, especially if there's no obvious small
factors that go into it. Because if I asked you, hey let's factor 143,
I mean how do you go about it? I think the way a lot of us think about it is we
initially think, okay, we know that two doesn't go into it
because it's not even. Three, there's a nice divisibility check
where you do one plus four plus three, and that sum in this case is five plus
three or eight is not divisible by three, so
that's out. Five we can see doesn't go into it.
Seven, okay you have to think about that for a moment, but you might see that seven
goes into 140 evenly because that's 20 times seven,
okay, so that's right out. And at this point you might be annoyed
with whoever was asking you the question, but if you go one step further you might
see, okay, 11. Actually 11 does go into it, and it ends
up being 11 times 13. I just love the fact that
right now people probably have no idea what any
of this has to do with the quadratic formula, but I assure you,
highly related. Because what if I asked you
3,599? And this particular example isn't
randomly chosen by the way. I was reading this article about a Russian
programmer in an interview that he had, I think it
was at Goldman Sachs, and he was describing kind of the intensity of that
interview environment. And in one of them he just walks in the
door, hadn't even met the person, and the person just shouts at him,
factor 3,599. You know the programmer's like, uh, all right. And he
actually was able to spit out the factors
particularly quickly, which is impressive given the fact that if we imagine going
through all of the different primes, you know, does two go into it? No. Does three
go into it? No. Five? No. You're going to be sitting there for quite a while.
So clearly something different was happening in his head, and the question
is, what? Well one thing you might notice
about the numbers that I've chosen here is that 35 is awfully close to a square.
It's actually just one less than six squared. And maybe it kind of makes
sense that its factors are each kind of close
to six. You know, five times seven, it's probably not going to equal six
times six, but the fact that they're of similar sizes should be intuitive,
and as it happens it's precisely one less. And something similar happens with
the other example I chose. 143 is rather close to a square number,
144. In fact it's one less. And it's no coincidence that its two
factors are hovering right around the square root of that value.
One of them is 12 minus 1, and the other one is 12 plus 1.
So it kind of makes sense that the product will be something around 12 times
12. And so from this you might make a guess
that hey, maybe any time that you have some number that's one
less than a perfect square, and this, you know, it's suspiciously close to a
very round seeming number, 3600. Well what is 3600?
We recognize the 36 as being six squared and 100 is 10 squared,
so that's 60 times 60. And maybe you think, okay, the guess,
if it's going to follow the same pattern as what we've seen above,
is that this would be one less than 60 times one more than 60.
But of course you don't just want a pattern match, let's see if there's a
nice reason that it's a true. You can work it out algebraically, which
we will, but as you guys know I love animation, so let's just see if there's a
nice visual way to understand this particular property.
And if we're going to think about this, the natural place to turn is to think
about squares. So let me just pull up an image of a
square, and if we want to say can I factor
a number which is one less than a square, what I might have us imagine doing
is taking the corner off of that square, okay?
So let's say it's x by x, whatever x is, in this case it happens to be six, but
you want to think a little bit more abstractly than that.
And I'm going to take that bottom right corner, get it out of here, we don't want
it. The question of factoring is to say can
I rearrange the quantity that remains into some kind of rectangle? And in this
case if I take that bottom row, sloop it on up to the right, what you can
see is it forms a rectangle, one with a side length x plus one and
another with a side length x minus one. So this general property holds quite
well, and I think that's really cool, right? You see this visually, you see that
it's this neat mental arithmetic trick where any time you have some sort of
square number minus one, you can factor that as x plus one
times x minus one. But of course we can go one step further
than that if we really want to. It doesn't have to be one sitting there.
If we go back to our diagram, what you might instead do is say, hey,
what if I chopped off a bigger corner of that square? What if I wasn't taking x
squared minus one, I was taking x squared minus y squared?
Well, I can rearrange what remains into a rectangle where it's x plus y
on one side and then x minus y on the other side.
Now that's the geometric way that you can view it, which I think gives a
certain satisfaction, and when we view it in terms of
numbers it gives us a reminder of how powerful it is.
And yet somehow when we do this algebraically, the magic
is a little bit lost. It's definitely easier to see, and that demonstrates the
power of algebra, but if I just said x plus y times x minus
y... Actually, you know what, let me change the variable names there. I don't like x
and y because those don't necessarily have the same meaning.
What I might do is try to picture, you know, let's picture the original two
numbers that we had, something that's like 59 and 61
on a number line, and I want to think in terms of the midpoint
m and then the distance between m and each of the other numbers,
so plus and minus d. In this case d is just one, but in principle it might be
something more. So if I ask you multiply m minus d
times m plus d, you know, at this point it's pretty straightforward algebra.
The first term's m times m, we get m squared.
Next we have negative d times m, so that's minus d
m. Next we have m times plus d, m times plus d, and then negative d times
d, so minus d squared. And indeed what comes out is m squared
minus d squared. And if you're anything like me, the first
time you see this in an algebra class, it's just one of a whole bunch of
exercises that you're doing. You're like, yeah, okay, I can expand this one way, I
guess some terms cancel out nicely. But the more you think about this, the
more intriguing it is, because any two numbers we can express,
you know, if I just take any numbers r and s, I could write that down as some
midpoint plus or minus a distance, and what this
is telling us is to think about products is always the same as thinking about a
difference of squares, which is weird, because products can be
very chaotic. If I just walk through the number line,
and I don't know, I say look at 101, 102, 103, and I just say take a look at all
the numbers on the number line, and I want you to systematically tell me
can each one of them be broken down as a product of two smaller whole
numbers? Well, we know that what that's asking is
what are the primes, because only the primes can't be broken down like that,
and yet evidently that's a very similar question to saying when can I walk
through those numbers and say, hey, am I able to express you as a
difference of squares? Could I add a square number to you to get another
square? That still feels hard, but that feels
like a very different question to me. So I think if you were doing some
arithmetic and you had this in the back of your mind,
that's a good pattern, and that's a pattern that's going to come up later in
life. For example, let's say later in life you
find yourself wanting to understand quadratic functions.
And so here we're going to talk about the the simpler version of the quadratic
formula, which is really just refactoring the
original thing, but I hope you see it's much easier to actually solve
a random quadratic that's thrown at you if you're going by
um if you're going by the method that I want to show you right here.
So what's the task? Anytime you have some function that looks
like ax squared plus bx plus c, okay, for any numbers a, b, and c.
So maybe that's something like 3x squared minus 4x plus 5.
And you want to know when that equals zero,
what are the two roots? Now this is actually equivalent to
rescaling everything, and I think it's a good common pattern to rescaling, where
I'm going to divide everything by a. So I just want that first
coefficient to be a one, because that's way easier to work with.
So I'm going to call that x squared plus b prime x
plus c prime, where b prime and c prime are just the rescaled versions there.
And this is a different function, it is a different quadratic function,
but the roots are going to be the same. And one way that you might see this is
if you just graph them. So let's go over and pull up our best
friend of Desmos, right. So let's say I have some kind of
parabola, in this case I've written it so that one of the roots is going to be 2
and the other is 4, and then g of x here is just the scaled version of
the expanded version of that. It's exactly the same graph,
but let's say I wanted to scale that up and down, right. So I might take this
and then I will multiply it by some kind of constant.
What do you guys want to call that constant? See this is the thing, if I had
the question framework working right now, I could just ask you what do you want the
constant to be, and we would see the statistics come up
with what people had. But instead maybe I'll throw in a slider.
And as I change that, the function changes, it is a different function,
but the roots are still 2 and 4, okay. So solving for this rescaled version of
the quadratic is the same, and that should kind of make sense,
because s times 0 is always going to be 0, so it doesn't matter how much we
scale it. So going back to what we're working
with here, the reason that I think it's much nicer to make sure that that
leading coefficient is a 1, is because if we're thinking of
our quadratic in terms of its roots, and I say okay, you know it's going to
intersect the x-axis at r and s, or maybe it does, maybe it doesn't, but
let's just write one that does like this. Another way that I could express that
particular quadratic is as x minus r
times x minus s, because if I plug in r it's clear that we're going to get 0,
and if I plug in s, again this term will also cancel out to 0.
So if I expand this, whatever r and s are, they're the unknowns,
I should get the same thing as what we have up here. And this is generally
useful, this is not just for the quadratic formula, but a very good
relationship to have with polynomials is to know how the roots
correspond to the coefficients, especially in a circumstance where that
leading coefficient is 1, and the whole polynomial has been kind of
normalized in that way. And in this case if you just expand it
out, what we'll get is x squared minus r plus s
times x, because we have this minus r times x,
and then x times minus s, and then the constant term will be negative r times
negative s, so that becomes a positive r times s.
Okay, so what does this tell us? This tells us the first two
of the three key facts that are needed to be able to solve
any quadratic without really needing to memorize all that much.
So the first key fact is that this b value, I'll call it b prime just to
remind ourselves that it's after you've scaled things down,
is the same as the negative sum of the two roots.
Okay, and then similarly c prime is going to be the product of those two
roots, which is kind of cool because what we
have right here is, you know, it's a system
that feels like it should have a solution. We have two
equations and two unknowns, but it's not obvious how we would go about solving it.
And every now and then I think classes will have a unit in factoring
quadratics where they basically tell you to just
guess and check, so in some very fortunate circumstances if you have
something like, you know, x squared, let's see, minus 7x
plus 12. They basically say see if you can guess
and find two different numbers that add up to be
7 and that multiply to be 12. And if you
just kind of sit back there and think you're like, okay, can I find any two
numbers that add to 7 and multiply to 12? Well, factoring 12 we get 3 and 4,
and 3 and 4 do add to 7, so yeah, in that case you just
totally luck out and you could write this as
x minus 3 and x minus 4 because those are the two roots.
And then you typically move on from that chapter and it's like, well in most cases
you won't be able to just guess and check.
And in any case what you're going to look for is a general formula anyway, so
hope you had fun with that. But it turns out there's actually a
systematic way to take this puzzle of finding two numbers
that have a known sum and a known product
and figure out what they are. And the key comes down to thinking in terms of
not the two numbers themselves but the mean of those two numbers
and then the distance between that mean and each one of them.
And you can see where this is going, this is why we talked about difference of
squares. Because the third key fact to come away
with, or to come into it with I should maybe say,
is that we could re-express that product as m
minus d times m plus d.
And you see where I'm going, right? That means that the product that we know
looks like m squared minus d squared.
So just to give an example here, it's often much more helpful to have
numbers. Let's say that you were given a
quadratic like x squared, I don't know,
let's do six even numbers will make this easier for us,
and then seven. Okay? And you were tasked with knowing when does this equal zero?
So I haven't told you how to solve it yet but these three key facts are going
to be enough to just basically walk yourself into the answer.
Well, what is what is m, right? Because we're
going to ultimately express our roots r and s as m plus or minus d
for some kind of midpoint. Well that midpoint
is the sum of the two numbers over two, that's how we define averages. And because
we know the sum of the two numbers is negative b prime, that's the same as
negative b prime over two, which you can basically read off of the
equation as just negative one half times whatever sitting right
there, which in this case will be negative three.
Awesome, we know what m is. But look at the equation we have up here.
We have an expression for c, the last coefficient, in terms of m,
which we now know, and d, which is the only thing we don't know left.
So we could rearrange this, and so that was saying c prime is that,
we could say that d squared, the square of this kind of standard deviation
between our roots, is m squared minus c prime,
the product of the two roots. But we know both of those values, we could just write
that down over here. Maybe I'll change colors again, be a little
flamboyant. d squared is equal to m squared, which in our
example turns out to be nine, minus c prime, which is that last
coefficient, or seven.
Seven. Handwriting is terrible, but I think you guys can work with me. You see
why I usually animate stuff. So that means that's two. So look, when we
said r and s is some midpoint plus or minus a distance,
that midpoint is negative three plus or minus,
well if d squared is two, that means d is the square root of two.
There you go. You could do that for any quadratic that I give you. You could
just walk through that particular process.
And let me just show you what it looks like in general, so that you can maybe
remember it as a formula if you wanted to. In general, for any
quadratic, that midpoint is just
the rescaled version of b, if the leading coefficient wasn't already one,
divided by two. And then that distance, well what did we just do? We took the
square root of the midpoint squared
minus the product of the two. And when I'm sort of singing it in my head, I've
been saying like m squared minus p, just because p has a readable meaning. I
think of it as the midpoint squared minus the product.
But of course p in this context is just whatever the last coefficient of our
quadratic was. So over in this example, the product of
the two coefficients was seven. So for me, what I think the simpler
quadratic formula is, if you're going to memorize anything,
is to come away and say it's m plus or minus
the square root of m squared minus p. All you have to do is first find m, which
is, you know, just a factor times one of the
coefficients you're looking at, and then find p, which is also, if not
already a factor, a coefficient that you're looking at, a
rescaling of one of them. So this to me is way simpler than the
traditional quadratic formula, and if you were to try to sing a song to yourself
for it, the song is almost too short. It's no fun. You're just sitting there like
m plus or minus square root of m squared minus p.
That's it. No song. No song to be had. So let's do a couple practice problems
because I do think practice will make it easier.
And for future streams, again, it'll ultimately be the case that I'm giving
you these questions, and then you'll be able to go to
3b1b.co.live and answer them. But because there's too many of you, we
can't have any fun today. This is the equivalent of trying to run
a class where you have, you know, I don't know, 20 seats sitting out and you're
going to do a normal lecture, and then there's just people banging at
the doors and trying to cram themselves in and the fire marshal comes in,
and they're like, ah, you got to cut out the class. You can't have this the way
that you hoped for. But it's cool that there's so many of
you here enthusiastic to learn about math.
So let's just do some examples, okay? That'll kind of highlight
what this process looks like. Let's say we had x squared plus 10x
plus 3. So in this case it's nicely already rescaled for us. That's always
lovely. So I often, I just like to draw the
picture for myself. Whether or not the two roots turn out to be real
or even positive, it's just nice to remind myself what we're looking for.
We're looking for where the two roots are, and I know
that a different way to think about products is to think about a difference
of squares. So I just kind of think in my head, okay,
I'll be thinking of that in terms of their mean
and a kind of standard deviation. So I just write down for myself what does
that mean. Well, it's negative b prime over 2.
And if I forget that fact, if I forget that that's what the
the sum of the two roots is, I could always just go through this little
rigmarole again and say, okay, if I systematically wanted it to be
a quadratic with roots r and s, this is what it would look like, this is how it
would expand. So you can re-derive it on the fly, there's not too much
memorization needed. In this context that works out to be
negative 5. And by the way, if I do ever make any
mistakes, which I'm quite positive I will,
go ahead and throw them in the chat and those will be forwarded to me and
I'll be able to correct myself there. So we know the midpoint,
and then we just ask ourselves what's the square of the distance,
and based on difference of squares, that'll be that midpoint squared
minus the product, which in this context is negative 5 squared
or 25 minus the product, which is that last coefficient,
minus 3. So what are the roots r and s? Well, it's negative 5 plus or minus
the square root of 25 minus 3, or 22. There you go, another quadratic solved.
Ain't no thing. Let's try another.
Just because I do think it's kind of nice to get a little bit of practice
here. And as I'm going, if you have a piece of paper and pencil,
please follow along. If you can just kind of race ahead and do the same process
before I do it, that's awesome. That is the best kind of
learning experience. If you're watching this in the future, by the way,
as with any video, I highly encourage you to pause and ponder.
I really think that's the best way to learn math if you're looking at some
kind of lecture. In those crucial moments where there's a
question asked, pause, see if you can do it yourself, and then see what the answer
turns out to be. I guarantee you'll learn more effectively that way.
I don't know what should we do. Let's do
maybe 3x squared. I think I wrote one down earlier, didn't I?
Just as kind of a off-handed thing. What did I write?
No, it wasn't there. Oh yeah, it was at the top.
Let's do that one. 3x squared minus 4x plus 5. Why not?
3x squared minus 4x plus 5. All right, so in this case, step one,
we've got to rescale things. That's what gives the coefficients a
nice readable meaning. Minus four-thirds x
plus five-thirds. Great. And now, same process. I'm sort of
thinking in my head of this particular image where I want to know the midpoint
and the distance. So I say that midpoint is negative
of this second coefficient divided by two, so that will become positive four-thirds,
but then that four divided by two gives us a two.
So that midpoint will be two-thirds, and then the distance squared
is m squared minus the product, which in this case is five-thirds.
Okay, and m squared in this case is, let's see,
two-thirds squared minus five-thirds. All right, so this one, you know, it gets
a little messier. We've got to work out our fractions, but that's not too
bad. Two-thirds squared is going to be four-ninths.
Oh, I'm off screen a little.
And then what is five-thirds in terms of ninths? That's going to be fifteen
ninths, if I'm not wrong. So we end up getting a negative number,
which is always fun. So here we have negative eleven-ninths.
Okay, so what that means is that our final answer, the roots of this
polynomial, r and s, the values that will make the
polynomial zero, are going to be two-thirds plus or minus
the square root of negative eleven over d.
Negative eleven over d. What am I saying? Negative eleven over nine.
Okay, so that's fun. In this case the square root is a negative, so that means
we have complex roots. And there's actually a
very fun way to think about the way that complex roots
play into this difference of squares perspective on the quadratic formula.
Let me actually try it with a simpler example, but it ends up relating to the
Pythagorean theorem, which I think is cool because the whole
purpose of this is to try to connect various patterns in math that come up a
lot, things that might be useful outside of this particular class
that you're doing. So I actually have written down for
myself an example that will work out with nice numbers here.
I mean nice-ish. x squared minus 6x plus 10. Okay,
so we go through the same rigmarole, we say m, the midpoint,
is going to be negative b prime over 2, so in that case it works out to just be
3, because we take the negative of this term and divide by 2.
d squared is going to be m squared, so 3 squared is 9, minus the
product, which in this case is 10. So nicely that's exactly negative 1,
which means that our two roots, and down to the wire on the page that
I've been writing with here, our two roots are 3 plus or minus
i. Okay, so what that means for us is that the actual
parabola here, it doesn't look like something that crosses the x-axis.
Instead it would be something that maybe sits above it, but it does have
imaginary roots. So if we were to look at the input space,
not just in terms of the real number line, but let me draw it out,
let me go back to black. Black will be our complex plane color for this moment.
We'll call this our imaginary axis, where numbers like i and negative i, the
square root of 1, or maybe I should say square roots of
1, it's got two of them, you interchange them, it's fine.
And then we've got just the real numbers, 1, 2,
3, 4. So in this case our two roots live at 3 plus i,
and 3 minus i. So this, I should be very clear, this is not
an x-axis and a y-axis. This entire plane now is where the
input lives, where x lives. If you were going to graph it, you'd get some kind of
graph that's outside of the paper. And any of you who've
watched the channel Welsh Labs, which if you haven't you absolutely should,
might be bringing to mind right now an absolutely awesome like artificial
reality effect he does where he sort of pulls out that graph.
Highly worth watching, super great moment. But what's interesting about this
is if we look at the magnitude of the roots,
okay, because I could ask you what is the magnitude of that root? And
it's a right triangle that we're looking at, we've switched from algebra to
geometry now, and based on the Pythagorean theorem it'll
be the square root of one of the lengths squared, which is in
this case 3 squared, plus the other length squared, which is 1
squared. So square root of 3 squared plus 1
squared, and that ends up being root 10. It is not a coincidence at all
that the magnitude of our roots, I guess sort of, no pun intended, the
magnitude of the roots of our quadratic equation here
are the square root of that constant coefficient. Because remember that
constant coefficient is telling us what is the product of the two roots.
And if you know something about complex numbers, you might know that if I have
two complex numbers and I multiply them together, the
magnitude of the product is the same as the product of the
magnitudes. So in this case, given that I'm going to have two
separate roots who are symmetric, you know, it's going to
be 3 plus or minus some imaginary number, each of them is
going to have the same magnitude. The product of their magnitudes needs to
be 10, we know that off hand, so you kind of know ahead of time that
it should be a magnitude of square root of 10.
And the reason that this is happening is basically because when you do
difference of squares, something like m plus d
times m minus d, but that distance is an imaginary value, i,
what you get is m squared minus i times d squared, but because i squared is by
definition negative one, you get a sum of squares.
So even sums of squares which come up in geometry, Pythagorean theorem stuff, all
of that, can be expressed as a kind of
difference of squares, which itself gives a kind of factoring.
And this shows up in a lot of very very beautiful math later down the road.
One of my favorite videos that I've made actually is,
oh what did I title it, I think pi hiding in prime regularities,
where you're counting lattice points inside a circle and the key insight
associated with doing that is to realize that asking when you can
express something as the sum of two squares
is a sort of factoring problem, but it's factoring not where you're dealing with
prime numbers on the real number line, but primes in
complex numbers, these things called Gaussian primes.
So even simple, I shouldn't say simple stuff, but
even stuff that comes up in high school like the quadratic formula,
I think if you're learning it the right way it ends up connecting to all sorts
of other delightful things. And remembering these patterns comes up
like I said. So just to re-emphasize, how did we get
here? What three key facts do you need to be aware of
with quadratics to be able to kind of rediscover a kind of quadratic formula on
the fly? The first one is how to read the
coefficient sitting in front of x. And if we have a quadratic that looks
like x squared plus b prime x plus c prime, you can read that first
coefficient as the negative sum of the roots.
You don't know that already, you can rediscover it on the fly, but that is
actually worth coming away with. Similar with how you can read the other
coefficient, it's the product of the roots.
Then the only other thing you need to know is that we could express that
product of roots as a difference of squares with respect
to the mean and the kind of standard deviation of those roots.
And you can just solve any quadratic that comes to you on the fly.
The only thing that looks remotely like memorization is if you want to jump
start to the end and just say m plus or minus m squared minus p.
Now to finish things off, I think it would be very satisfying to remind
ourselves that this is actually equivalent to the
traditional quadratic formula, something that looks much bigger.
So let's go ahead and actually do that exercise.
And again, if you can, pause and just work it out for yourself right now.
So let's remind ourselves of how that goes.
So we've got, what are we solving? Any kind of quadratic.
ax squared plus bx plus c. We want to say no matter what a, b, and c are, give me a
systematic way to find these roots. Again, maybe you're doing something
beautiful like ray tracing. Let me pull up that image again, that was a really
nice image. I just can't believe that this is
something that a computer generated. I guess I should believe it because
Pixar movies are amazing. But evidently, if you know the kind of
math that can lead you to create an image like this one,
that's the kind of thing that can get you a job as an engineer at Pixar.
And of course, what is that math? That math is exactly what we're doing right
now. So let's work it out again. ax squared plus bx plus c equals zero.
This time we're just going to write everything in terms of a, b, and c. No new
variables coming up. So when we do the first step of
rescaling, we say x squared is equal to b divided by a
times x plus c divided by a. We don't give it any new names. Now
remember how our trick works. We sort of picture in our head, hey,
imagine this quadratic has some roots. Let's call them r and s.
And we're trying to find the midpoint and the standard deviation. And we can
read off that that midpoint is the negative of the second term
divided by two. So in this case, that's going to be
negative b over 2a. Great. And then that standard deviation
is going to be m squared minus the product of the roots, which in this case
looks like negative b over 2a
squared minus, and the product here is what that last term is, c divided by a,
c over a. And remember, if you don't remember this idea that, oh, that's
what the distance is, just re-derive it for yourself on the
fly. Just go and say, okay, I remember that the product
p is just the product of my two roots, which can be expressed as m minus d,
m plus d. Oh, okay, that's something I can write as m squared minus d squared.
Oh, okay, that's what gives me an expression for d squared
in terms of m squared and p. Don't feel like you have to just come in and
know it off the top of your head, but after you do it a couple times it
sticks in your memory. So that's m, that's d, and the quadratic
formula is just telling us that the roots are m
plus and minus that standard deviation, which in this case looks like,
maybe I'll write it out on two lines because this will be a lot, negative b,
actually no, I'll write it on one line for this one, negative b plus or minus,
I'm jumping to the original quadratic formula, a little bit
too hard ingrained, we'll go back to two lines, negative b
divided by 2a, divided by 2a plus or minus the square root.
Oh, I wrote this incorrectly, oh someone should have corrected me.
This is what d squared is equal to, d squared is this whole thing, so d itself
is the root of those. I'm sure lots of people were shouting that in
the live chat, I don't have it pulled up now, but
to those of you who did, much appreciated.
So what do we have here? Well it's going to be the square
of negative b over 2a
minus c over a, minus c over a. Okay, now we just got to expand this
thing, which is frankly not super fun,
but it'll connect it to the original quadratic formula to
for us. So I can pull out this 2a squared and I'm just going to write that
as 1 over 4a times
times negative b squared, negative b, yeah negative b squared, and then I want
to also pull out 1 over 4a, I want to be able to say that the last
term also looks like 1 over 4a times something, and that something to
make it equal to c over a would have to cancel out the 4, it would
have to cancel out an extra a, and then c, sorry because this is really
1 over 4a squared. Let's see, have I done this right? Yeah,
because I pulled out the 2a, so that should be 4 times a squared, so
over here I have 4 times a squared. I want that to cancel to become c over a,
which it looks like it does, so that's awesome.
So you can go over here, negative b over 2a,
plus or minus, and if this feels tedious that's kind of the point, the whole
quadratic formula is more complicated than it needs to be,
because we were just solving any quadratic that was thrown at us without
having to do this, but this is what happens if you don't
introduce any new variable names on your way.
It's like code that hasn't been refactored properly. Okay, so what can we
do here? We can factor out the 1 over 4a squared,
and because that's in a radical, its square root will also be 1 over 2a,
and then what sits inside is what remains, the well familiar negative b
squared minus 4a. Okay, and this this is starting to
look like the traditional form, because if we pull onto the numerator,
negative b plus or minus square root of, why am I writing negative b squared?
Yeah, so this is a negative b squared, same as positive b squared.
What should sit on the inside here is b squared minus
4ac, 4ac. You can see how scatterbrained I am when
I'm just doing some arithmetic at times. It's okay. We all forget a variable or
two here and there, but maybe that's why I actually care so
much about formulas having nice readable meanings,
because I think this is a very error-prone process for someone like me.
If I'm just trying to work through with a bunch of symbols that,
I don't necessarily know how to read them, I get to the end result, and it's
hard for me to say like, oh yeah, of course that's what the answer is.
Whereas if I look at something like the simpler variant of the quadratic formula,
if I basically refactor it and I'm saying, okay, does the midpoint equal
negative b over two? I can kind of fact check, yeah, that
that makes sense, especially if you know a little calculus. Those of you will be
able to look at that quadratic formula and understand how to find the maximal
or minimal point. So that's a thing that gets reinforced
with a better pattern later on in your mathematical life,
always a good sign that you're learning things well. I can ask myself if it makes
sense that the distance looks like this. Again, that that has a readable meaning.
So when I'm looking at the simpler version of the quadratic formula,
we have m plus or minus a kind of square root of the variance, a kind of standard
deviation. So it's a refactoring. Now I titled this
thing, this is the simpler version of the quadratic formula,
and I think someone could rightfully complain. Like, is this actually simpler?
Because, you know, you've got a lot of steps, you've introduced new variables
into it. Now, in addition to thinking of the three
coefficients a, b, and c, you're telling me I also have to think
about like a new term m and a distance between them.
But for me, math is very much about trying to draw connections to other
patterns, and I think things are much better
remembered if you have that web of connections in your head
rather than just isolated cases. And the whole lesson here, if we think about
what's going on, it's about representing the same
information in different ways, right? Because what the quadratic formula
is doing for us, it's saying, can I go from my coefficients
a, b, and c, and can I get to the roots r and s? And we know that
there's a very easy way to go the other way around,
because we can expand something like x minus r
and x minus s. And really, because that a can get scaled out, it doesn't add any
information to the system, there's really as much information as two different
constants in there. So one of these directions is easy, and
one of these directions is hard. And this idea of information that can
be expressed in separate ways, and translation one direction being easy,
one direction hard, that comes up all the time in math. That's a very
useful thing to think about. And another useful thing to think about
is how sometimes going in that harder direction
will be better if you go through some intermediate step. In this case, rather
than thinking of your pair of numbers on the number line, just as they are,
doing your m plus or minus d trick, because we know that that changes how
you think about products. If you go through the intermediate step
of expressing that same information with a mean and a standard deviation,
that can get you to the roots. And that's all this is, it's just talking
about different information flow paths that can help go between various ways to
just express two numbers, whether those two numbers are the coefficients of your
quadratic, or the roots of the quadratic, or the mean and standard deviation.
So if the lesson you come away with is one of thinking, oh wow, sometimes
there's a lot of different ways that I can represent my data,
and some of them lend themselves to certain kind of problem solving better
than others, well then that is the proper lesson to
have with the quadratic equation. Okay, so I think with that I'm going to
call it an end to lesson number one. Really want to thank everyone who showed
up for this, definitely a ton of fun. Next time we're going to have the live
quizzing dynamic where we're going to get stats up on the screen.
So it's going to be pretty cool. I think this is a very cool
thing that two former co-workers of mine put together from Khan Academy,
but obviously this is the first time that we're trying it, it's a little rough
around the edges. So in the end what it's going to look
like is these bars that you're seeing live. Oh interesting, these are bigger
numbers than they were before. Okay, clearly they're updating, they're
updating! Oh this is exciting, do I have actual
access here? Oh it would be so fun to do this properly before we end.
Oh my god, oh this is so great, I think we're, I think we can do it.
Okay, are you ready for this guys? Okay I'm grading the answers.
Oh, oh wonderful, oh we can see what people answered.
This is great, this is how I wanted to end the stream. While I was talking just
in the background some magic was being done, this is wonderful.
So it looks like the most common answer, what's our question here?
What best describes your relationship with the quadratic formula?
And the most common answer is C. I'm a big fan, you might say I'm rooting for
it. So it looks like 1724 of you,
five short of Ramanujan's constant, are addicted to puns.
Let's do a couple more, this is going to be pretty fun.
These were just like the joke warm-up questions before we got into the real
lesson, but I actually think this is the perfect way to end
the whole lesson, is to just kind of wind down with some of
what were meant to be introductory jokes. Oh it's working, I love this so much.
Oh and there's so many of you answering, this makes me so happy. All right so
what's our question here? If the quadratic formula had a
patronus, what would it be? Okay well,
it looks like around 800 of you, I think it will be something.
By the way, I'm being told right now that if there's too many of you
who access it, we're for sure going to break the system,
and I'm purposefully ignoring that because I'm having fun with this, and if
it breaks that kind of tickles me. So I'm being told not to say this, but
please go to 3b1b.co slash live and enter questions to this,
and then you know whenever things break that would be a perfect time to end the
stream, because I just think that's hilarious.
Okay so oh again 1791, oh I guess we blew past Ramanujan's
constant. Maybe I can try to see if I can grade
this at a point right where we're going to lock in answers where the majority
is 1729, I think that would be fun. Okay so it looks like a majority of
people went with C, if the quadratic formula had a
patronus, it would be an old man hunched over a chess board,
which is the correct answer actually. You know this this question was
structured as a poll where there's no correct or incorrect rating, but I don't
think that's right. I think it should have been structured
where C is the objectively correct JK Rowling would agree
style answer. All right let's do the the warm-up, question number three here.
Oh this is a fun one, okay what does it say?
What integer will most people enter into this box?
Okay oh lots of answers coming in. Again I really want my friends to like
struggle, bars all over my face. You know this
actually seems apropos given that the whole title of this is lockdown math
that it starts to look like I'm slowly being imprisoned by everyone's answers
and just getting locked down further and further into the quarantine situation.
So this one actually now there is a, where do I talk? Help!
Bars are attacking me, okay there's an objectively correct answer
because there is going to be some number that most people enter.
And it looks like 919 of you think that it'll be one particular thing, but we've
got a widespread, this is actually pretty fun. So again if you want to
partake in this head on over to 3b1.co.live.
I actually think the best way that you could do this,
what is the, seven! Wow I would not have guessed that, most people entered seven.
And in a weird way like the plurality of you are definitionally correct
that seven was the most commonly entered expression.
69 being the second most common. I can make a guess for why that might be the
case. Did you know that 69 is the first number where if you square it and then
you cube it, those two values between them encounter
the numbers or the digits zero through nine once and
only once. Yeah it's the first number with that
property, which I assume is why that was the second most popular answer.
But the very end, which is actually apropos at this point,
we can pull up another question which is going to be
what I was going to open the whole lesson with so you can kind of see how
the plan went here. How many times do you expect to use the
quadratic formula in your real life outside of school?
And in this case luckily I'm getting a little bit less you know locked down by
the bars trapping me in here because it seems
like there's a little bit more consensus around how many times people think they
will need to use the quadratic formula in the real life.
What I could do is a plot twist on this and say you know interpret this question
in light of the lesson rather than when will you literally use
negative b plus or minus square root of I always forget it square root of b
squared minus 4ac over 2a 2a that whole thing to when are you going
to use the principles of recognizing that a product of numbers
expressed as a difference of squares can help you solve problems or we're
going when are you going to use the principles
of expressing your data in terms of a mean and a standard deviation can help
you solve problems. That I think would give you wildly
different answers but at the moment we've got a lot of you
on the system and it's not breaking. I'm so happy right now.
I just can't tell you how much this tickles me. So it looks like we've got a
wide forming consensus. You know for for my sake can we can we
just like keep going on this? I would love to see if we can get that top
bar up to 1729 whatever it might be. We can all guess what it might be but
let's see if you can go to 3b1b.co live wherever you're watching this. I think
honestly the best dynamic that I could imagine is if you just pull up your
phone and you're watching this on a screen with the one hand and then you're
using your phone to answer questions. A lot of you are already watching it on
your phone so that wouldn't necessarily work
but that is the dynamic I would most expect.
Okay so I'm just gonna wait until we get that top bar
up to be Ramanujan's constant of 1729. For those of you who don't know the
famous story behind that number is that I think it was the mathematician
Hardy was visiting Ramanujan when he was in the hospital and he said
I found this taxi cab that I was following on my way here and
the number on it was 1729 and I thought to myself what a
wholly unremarkable integer. There's nothing special about it.
You know it's not a square or prime or cube or anything like that
but we're getting close so let me not let me not mess this up.
I over blew it okay. You know and so he tells this to Ramanujan he says
1729 has no remarkable properties and Ramanujan says oh but can't you see
1729 is the first number that can be expressed as the sum of two cubes in two
separate ways. He says I don't understand how you can't
see it Hardy because 1729 is on the one hand 12
cubed plus one cubed but on the other hand
it's 10 cubed plus 9 cubed and it is the first natural number that
has this property that you can express it as the sum of two cubes
in two separate ways and that's just such a delightfully random fact that I
think it became immortalized in the history of math.
So it looks like 1769 of you which is appropriate given the second
second most common entry here said that you thought you would use the
quadratic formula zero times and honestly I agree with you.
I don't think you're ever going to use the quadratic formula unless you're a
Pixar engineer in its actual form but I think you will
use some of the other lessons that I tried to get across here.
So with that I think that is the perfect time to call things an end here.
Really appreciate you guys joining on this first stream. The next lesson
is probably but don't hold me to it going to be about how to not memorize
trig formulas some of the things like cosine of 2 theta sine of 3 theta
all of those things and it'll be on Tuesday at the same time
unless something changes and you can check the banner of the channel about
that and then for those of you watching in
the future hopefully this is just a long playlist of
high school lectures that you can join and appreciate.
So thank you so much for joining I hope to see you next time
and keep loving math.