...
you
it ends up looking like this, you know, classic exponential curve that curves upward
and I can sometimes make it hard to see where it's going or what the overall pattern is
so a common trick is to say instead of looking at this y axis that increases linearly
as in here I'm going from 5k to 10k, 10k to 15k, 15k to 20k
each step is additive, we're adding 5000
instead use a y axis where each step is multiplicative
so you're going from 10 to 100, 100 to 1000, 1000 to 10, 10,000
all of these are increases by multiplying by 10
and what you can say is the y axis is now plotting not the total number of cases but the logarithm of the total number of cases
and this actually makes it kind of easier to see on a plot if you wanted to project out what that trend would do
and, you know, it's a little bit of a naive model to say oh it's going to grow exactly exponentially
but in the early phases of something like this that is what it is
so I kind of fast forward in the animation I made for that video
and what's interesting is if back then I think I posted it on March 6th
if you just found a line of best fit and you stretched it out
and you said when is that line going to cross a million
which because the y axis is growing with multiplicative steps
each time that you step up you're multiplying by 10
so even if it might seem like the 20,000 cases or so that it was back then is very far from a million
you know when you understand logarithmic scales it actually didn't seem that far
it was only 30 days away if you naively just drew out that line
and in fact fast forward to around April 5th which is when that would have predicted
we hit a million cases outside China
that's pretty much the day that it happened
I think plus or minus a day but I don't remember exactly
but it was right in that neighborhood because I remember thinking wow
it was kind of a naive model for the video to even use
and it's shocking that it matched so exactly
thankfully since then the growth has stopped being exponential
so if you look at it on a logarithmic plot instead of going up in a straight line it starts to taper off
but point being any time that you're coming across something in nature
or even in a man-made construct
where what's natural to think about are multiplicative increases
logarithms come in to help you
so let's go ahead and think about what these actually are
how are they defined
and actually there was a question asked on Twitter right before we started
that I think hits this very perfectly
so Max 182 asks us
additions inverse is subtraction
multiplications inverse is division
but I never truly understood if exponentiations inverse was nth rooting or logarithms
if either one could be
you know
if either one could really be called that way
can they
that is such a fantastic question Max
and I think it comes down to the fact that with addition and multiplication
you're not
I'll just draw it out for you actually
this is going to be easiest
if we have some kind of exponential relationship
let's say
10 to the power 3 is equal to 1000
there's three different numbers at play here
we're showing a relationship between the 10, the 3 and the 1000
and aside from writing it with an exponent
there's two other ways we could write that same relationship
we could also say
that the cube root of 1000
is equal to 10
this is asking
what number raised to the third is equal to 1000
that's sort of what the cube root is asking
and another way that you could phrase the exact same thing
is to say the log base 10
of 1000
is equal to 3
okay
three different notations the same exact relationship
a while ago I made this video about an alternate possible notation
that would center in the idea that
you think of this relationship between the three numbers with a triangle
where you'd have our 10 sitting down here
the power sitting at the top 10 to the third
and the thing they equal sitting to the lower right
and whenever you want to talk about a function
or an operation between two of these numbers
you indicate which one of them you're leaving out
so to write 10 cubed
we would include the 10 on the lower left
the 3 on the upper right
and then we leave out that bottom one
so this is indicating that we're taking a power 10 cubed
for that radical
what you would say is
we know what's on the bottom right
something to some power equals 1000
we even know what the power is
something cubed equals that 1000
but the thing we don't know is on the bottom left
that is the sense in which radicals are an opposite of exponentiation
where if the thing you don't know
instead of being on that bottom right
is on the bottom left
but what logarithms are
it's an inverse in another sense
because what it's saying is
in this triangle relationship
we know the base, it's 10
we know the power that it should be
but the thing we don't know is what's in that exponent
so to answer your question maybe even more briefly
we could say that 10 to the x
the inverse of that
the inverse is the log base 10
you know, of y
of some other variable
whereas if you're taking x to the 10th
some unknown raised to a power
the inverse of that
is going to be the 10th root
of some other value
and on the triangle it's basically asking
which of the things do we consider to be a variable
so are you considering that lower right to be a variable quantity
are you considering that top to be a variable quantity
and what is the unknown
but I really liked this idea of
making explicit how we have three totally different notations
for the same exact fact
one of them you're using relative positions of the numbers
one of them we introduce a new symbol
this radical
and one of them we introduce a new word, log
so these three syntactically different ways to communicate the same idea seemed wrong
and so I made this video about an alternate possible notation
and while I don't necessarily think that
oh we should teach logarithms with this triangle
because convention is what it is
so it's better to start getting people used to the usual expression
what I do like about it and starting off with it
is when you see and think about this triangle
it's really emphasizing that what the log wants to be
is that exponent
every time that you see log of some value
you should think in your mind
okay whatever this number is it really wants to be an exponent
it wants to be an exponent
and we'll see more of what that means as we go on
okay so every time you see a log
it wants to be an exponent this value three
and more specifically it should be an exponent sitting on top of whatever that base is
now in terms of convention
for the first part of this video
I'm just going to be using log without a base written on it
to be the shorthand for log base 10
because log base 10 will be the most intuitive thing out there
you should know that often in math
the convention instead is that log without anything might mean log base e
there's also another notation for that ln for natural log
we're going to talk all about the natural log next time
so don't worry too much about that right now
and there's also yet another convention
often if you're in a computer science setting
log without any added sugar to indicate what it is
defaults to meaning log base 2
so this can sometimes be a source of confusion
but it basically depends on what discipline you're in
in math, not moth, math
people really like a base of e
we'll see why next lecture
in, I don't know, I'll say engineering
but really it's anything where you want
good intuition with our normal base 10 number system
log means log base 10
and if you're curious often in computer science settings
log base 2 comes up all the time
so
like I said, in the back of your mind
if you're trying to think of some of these properties
just resting on the idea that log counts the number of zeros at the end of a number
that can get you a really far way
so we're going to start going through a couple of these properties
and I want to do this just with a set of practiced examples
so we'll transition away from the poll
and this time to the first proper question
and the question
asks you which of the following is true
a. the log of 1000 times x is equal to 3 times the log of x
and remember we're using the convention that it's base 10 log
b. log of 1000 times x equals log of x cubed
c. log of 1000 times x equals 3 plus the log of x
d. log of 1000 times x equals 3 to the power of log of x
and e. none of the above
and remember like I said earlier
we should fully expect that all of those people at the beginning who said they understand logs well
they're going to be answering immediately, they're going to be answering correctly
but if you're someone who doesn't, don't let that intimidate you
when you're looking at a problem like this one
what I would encourage you to do is
just plug in various powers of 10
and think in terms of the idea
that the log function counts the number of zeros
so I'll give you a little moment to think about that
great
ok so I'll go ahead and grade it
and as always if that's faster than what you're comfortable with
know that it's only because I want to proceed forward with the lesson
so in this case the correct answer comes out to be
log of 1000 times x is the same as taking 3 plus the log of x
and now let's think about that for a moment
and like I said when you're just getting started with them
I think the best thing to do is just be comfortable plugging in various numbers
and the best numbers to plug in are the ones that are already powers of 10
so if you're asking something like log of 1000 times x
well I don't know, let's just plug in something for x
log of 1000 times 100
ok, well we know how many zeros are going to be in the final answer here
well 1000 times 100 is 100,000
we already intuitively have this idea that when we multiply 2 powers of 10
we're just taking the zeros, the 3 zeros from that 1000
the 2 zeros from that 100 and we're putting them next to each other
so it should be 5 total zeros
but if you really reflect not just on how did the number turn out
but why did it turn out that way
it was the 3 zeros from that 1000 plus the 2 zeros from that 100
which we could also write by saying
the number of zeros in 1000 plus the number of zeros in 100
so this idea that a logarithm of the product of two things
is the sum of the logarithms of those two things
in the context of powers of 10
that's just communicating what's already a super intuitive idea for a lot of us
if you take 2 powers of 10 and you multiply them
you just take all of their zeros and kind of cram them onto each other
so the way I've written things out here is actually indicative of a slightly more general fact
which is going to be our very first property of logarithms
which is that if we take the log of A times B
it equals the log of A plus the log of B
now anytime you see one of these logarithm rules
if you find yourself squinting your eyes or you're a little bit confused by how to remember it
just plug in examples
I'm being redundant, I'm saying this a lot
but it's because I think it's very easy to forget
once you're swamped in the algebra itself
and you're sitting on some kind of test and it's just got a lot of symbols
to remind yourself you are okay to just plug in some numbers
that's a fine thing to do
and often it's a great way to yield intuition
so in this case, saying log of A times B and breaking it apart
we could just think, oh, that log of 100 times 1000
which is 5, there's 5 zeros in it
and it breaks up in terms of the number of zeros in each given part
great, wonderful
so carrying that intuition further, let's try another practice problem
and again, if you know it, great, you'll be able to answer it fine
but maybe think, not just what is the answer
but how would I explain this answer to someone
or how would I try to get a student to come to this answer on their own
without me having to tell them what the answer is
so there's two potential audience members
there's those who are interested in the lesson itself
and then those who are interested in the meta lesson
so our question asks, again, which of the following is true
A, log of x to the n is equal to n times log of x
B, log of x to the n is equal to log of x to the power n
C, log of x to the n is equal to n plus log of x
or D, log of x to the n is equal to log of n times log of x
or none of the above
so again, take a moment to answer
as people do answer, we'll start to see them roll in
and if you are struggling to think of where to even start
just plug in some powers of 10
and see what intuition you might get from it
you
alright, so it looks like just about everybody is landing on one particular answer
hopefully it's the right answer, like I said, all to be expected
so let's go ahead and see if our majority ended up correct
and they did
so the correct answer here is A, which it looks like 4000 of you got
congratulations, telling us that log of x to the power n is equal to n times log of x
so again, let's say that you're trying to teach this to someone
or if you're trying to come to grips with what it means yourself
I think a fine place to start is plugging something in
and in this case, for log of x to the power n
let's just try it with 100 to the power 3
and you could try it with other ones to see if the patterns you're doing actually work
but if you're thinking it through not in terms of simply seeing what the answer is
but trying to think of why the answer turned out that way
sometimes one example will do
because 100 cubed, we can think of that as taking
well, that's 3 copies of 100
I'm taking 3 copies of 100
and when I multiply all that out
and I think of log as counting the number of zeros
we say, oh, it's going to be some number that just has 6 zeros on it
that's what it means to take 100 times 100 times 100
I can just think of grouping all of those zeros together
to get a million
so this number is going to be 6
but if we think actually why was it 6
not just that's the number of zeros inside the million
where that 6 came from
is that we had 3 copies of that 100
and each of those 100 had 2 different zeros
so that way it's a more general way you can think about it
where if instead of taking 100 cubed we were looking at 1000 cubed
or 1000 to the n or x to the power n
you can think that it's whatever that value of n was
the number of copies we were multiplying in
times the number of, well let's see, it's not x
times the number of zeros that were in whatever we substituted for x
which in this case was 100
so if instead I had taken something like log of 10,000 to the power n
this would be the same as taking n copies of that 10,000
counting the number of zeros in each one of them which is 4
so it would be n times 4
and of course the general property that most of you correctly answered
is that you have this lovely little effect where when you see the log of something raised to a power
that little power hops down in front of it
and you just have log of what was on the inside
now one of the maybe most important implications of that
I don't know if you'd call it an implication or if you'd call it a restatement of the definition
if I'm taking log, and I'll just re-emphasize it's base 10
of 10 to the power n
we can kind of think of that little n as hopping down in front
and it becomes n times the log base 10 of 10
which is of course 1
this expression you can think of as either counting the number of zeros at the end
or more generally it's asking 10 to the what equals 10
and the answer is simply 1
which is very reassuring because another way that you could go back and just read this original expression
is saying 10 to the what equals 10 to the n
oh well the answer is n
now with every given logarithm property that we have
so in this case we just found one, log of x to the power n involves that n hopping in front
there's always going to be a mirror image exponential property
and that's another way that we can help to get ourselves a little bit of intuition for these
so let me just cover up some of the future properties we're going to get to here
try to hide where we're going
what we just found, raising something to the n that hops in front
this corresponds to the exponential property that if I take 10 to the x
and raise that whole thing to the power n
that's the same as taking 10 to the n times x
and this gets us to another intuition that you might have for logarithms
which is they kind of, they're like exponentiation turned inside out
and here's what I mean by that
the thing sitting on the inside of the log, if I'm taking log of a
you should be thinking of that as the whole outer expression for something that's exponential
in this case the a, the thing on the inside, corresponds to 10 to the x
the output of the function
whereas the entire thing itself, the log of a
corresponds to what's on the inside over here
just what's the exponent of the 10
so wherever you see a log expression here, you should be thinking
that plays the role of an exponent on the right side
and every time you see an exponential
the entire 10 to the x expression, the whole outer component on the right side
that corresponds to something that's sitting on the inside of one of the logs
and we saw this above, right
the idea that when we're multiplying on the inside, that's adding on the outside
well if logs kind of turn exponentials inside out
that's telling us that multiplying on the outside, multiplying the outputs of the function
is the same as adding on the inside
because each of these logs, like log a and log b
is playing the role of the x and the y in the expression on the right
okay, so with that, let's keep playing
let's just do a couple more of these and see how many of these properties that we can build up an intuition for
so this last one, very nice, thinking of exponents hopping down
the next one is something that might look a little bit weird
to those who are not necessarily familiar with logarithms
but again, plug in some numbers to gain some intuition for it
and we'll give it a little bit more, a moment to pull up
which of the following is true?
log base a of b is negative log base b of a
log base a of b is 1 divided by log base b of a
log base a of b is 1 minus log base b of a
log base b of a is log base a of 1 divided by b
or none of the above
so it's asking what happens when we swap the base with what's sitting inside of the logarithm
and I'll just give you a minute or two to answer that
so let's do a couple more
okay, so it seems like answers have kind of stabilized out there
so let's go ahead and grade things
and in this case, the correct answer of the choices we have comes out to be b
that the log base a of b involves taking 1 divided by the log base b of a
again, let's think this through both in terms of an example and then in terms of a more
proofy, systematic reason why it should be true
so if we're swapping our bases
let's just start off with
our good old friend log base 10
and let's plug in a nice power of 10 like 1000
counting the number of zeros, we get 3
so let's try swapping the bases and see what this should mean
log base 1000 of 10
okay, well what is this asking?
maybe you think of drawing the little triangle saying something like
we know 1000 to something is equal to 10
1000 to the what equals 10?
well, if 10 cubed is 1000
that is the same thing as saying 10 is equal to 1000
raised to the 1 third
doing the inverse here involves the multiplicative inverse of the exponent
and the way that pans out is that it looks like 1 divided by 3
and that 3 corresponds to the log base 10 of 1000
it's 1 divided by the log base 10 of 1000
so more generally, you might guess
based on this single example that when we swap the base with what's on the inside
it corresponds to taking 1 divided by what's on the outside there
and again, you can think this through in terms of
looking at the corresponding exponential rule
now what happened to my lovely little log and exponentials?
wonderful
so, again let's hide where some of the things
some of the other properties that we'll get to here
and I'll keep it in the same order I had it before
here I was thinking that having it pre-written could keep me a little bit cleaner than usual
but maybe it just involves playing this weird game of paper cutting shuffling around
so what we just found, log base b of a
if you swap those, it's the same as dividing by 1
what this corresponds to, off an exponential land
is if you take b to some power
and say that that equals a
that's the same statement as saying that a to the inverse of that power equals b
again, it's kind of helpful to take a moment and think of the logarithms as turning things inside out
the expression log base b of a is playing the role of that x
and the expression log base a of b is playing the role of whatever sits on top of the a
and then symmetrically, the whole expression b to the power x
is playing the role of the inside on the left, it plays the role of the a
and the whole expression, a to the power of something
plays the role of what's sitting inside the log base a there
so you can see just by plugging in some examples and by corresponding it to the exponential rules
we can already think through three different logarithm rules
which if they were just handed down as pieces of algebra to be memorized
you know, you could memorize them
but it's very easy for them to kind of slip out of your head
and it's also very easy to get frustrated by the task at hand
but you might want to remind yourself that the reason we care about these sorts of things
is understanding the rules of logarithms helps us do math in contexts where it's like a virus growing
where from one day to the next, from one step to the next, things tend to grow multiplicatively
understanding the rules of logarithms helps you to get a better feel for that kind of stuff
so before we do a nice real world example of what that can look like
let me just do one more quiz question in this vein to ask about properties of logarithms
one last one before we transition to a little bit of a real world example
get rid of what we had here
and now, which of the following is true?
log of a plus b is the same as log of a plus log of b
log of a plus b is equal to log of a times log of b
log of a plus b is equal to one divided by log of a plus log of b
or log of a plus b is equal to one divided by log of a times log of b
or none of the above
ah, and now we don't have as much consensus, do we?
very interesting, we've got a horse race between two
so I will give you a moment to think this through
Ally Freed
So, you know, I was just talking about how we might think in terms of
multiplicative growth and that doesn't just have to be powers of 10
We could also do something like powers of 3 or if you're going from 1 to 3 to 9
to 27 to 81 all of these
We could say that the log base 3 of these numbers
Just grows in nice little steps
So log base 3 of 1, 3 to the what equals 1, the answer is 0. In general the log of 1 no matter the base
will be 0. Log base 3 of 3, 3 to the what equals 3 is 1
Similarly log base 3 of 9 is 2
You might wonder what my question is, but it'll help to draw all of these out and
For my own pleasure here. Let me just write out one more log base 3 of 81 is 4. Now
I've heard that ostensibly if you ask a child's let's say around like 5 or 6 years old
What number is halfway between 1 and 9?
Okay, you say what number is halfway?
Their instincts for how to answer are
Logarithmic whereas our instincts tend to be more linear
So we often think 1 and 9 you've got a bunch of evenly spaced numbers between them 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8
And if you go right halfway in between you'll land on 5
But if you're thinking in terms of multiplicative growth where to get from 1 to 9
It's not a matter of adding a bunch of things
But you're growing by a certain amount you grow by a factor of 3 then you grow by another factor of 3
supposedly a kid's natural instinct lines up with saying 3 and supposedly this also lines up with
If you have anthropologists studying societies that haven't developed
Counting systems and writing in the same way that modern societies have they'll answer 3 for this
So my question for the audience if any of you watching right now have access to a small child
Let's say in the range of 5 years old
See if you can go ask them
What number is halfway between 1 and 9 and if you can let us know on Twitter what the
What the child says what their actual answer is?
Because I I don't know why I'm just a little bit skeptical of whether that
Actually pans out in practice. I understand
this is not a super scientific way to do it asking people watching a YouTube live stream to
Survey their own children and then tweet the answer but for my own sake it would be interesting to see some kind of validation there
Back to our question. This is the first one that doesn't seem to have a huge
Consensus in one direction, but let's go ahead and grade it to see what the answer turns out to be
Great okay, so
2400 of you correctly answered that it's none of the above okay that log of a plus B doesn't satisfy any of these nice properties
And in general unless we're going to be working with
Certain kinds of approximations especially when the natural log comes into play we might talk about this next time
Adding the inputs of a logarithm is actually a very weird sensation
It's a very weird thing to do and to get a sense of that weirdness plug in some powers of 10
If I ask you log of a plus B
What you might start thinking is okay? Let me just plug in some examples like
10,000 and
100 and
I asked myself if I do this zero counting function of what's in that input how many zeros are in it?
But it's weird because when we add 10,100 well, we're no longer at a clean power of 10 and okay
That's fine. You know often you're taking logarithms of things that aren't clean powers of 10
but it becomes very strange to ask how you express this in terms of
log of 100 which was 2 and
log of
10,000
Which was 4?
Because if you look at log of 10,100 it's asking 10 to the what is equal to 10,100
You might say it's gonna be a little above 4 because it's kind of close to 10,000 so the best you might
Guess here is oh, this is gonna be something. That's kind of like
The log of 10,000, but that just feels like a coincidence based on the two numbers that we happen to put in
There's not a nice systematic reason coming there, so maybe you guess oh if the numbers A and B are very different
It's kind of close to
Whatever the maximum of them is
But it's very bizarre and most importantly for the sake of the quiz
If you just look at the options that it's giving you if you try this out with any particular numbers
You'll find that none of those actually work
So all is good sometimes you get something that looks like it's going to be a nice property
But it doesn't end up being a nice property, and I also think that's important rather than just finding yourself
Only working with the various
You know log of A times B or log of X to the power N these things that have a nice rule
Sometimes you're out in the mathematical wild you're working on some problem
You have a logarithm expression
And it's adding things in the input and you want to be able to
Have familiarity with the fact that that's kind of weird that you're not going to be able to simplify
But if you you know if you hadn't thought about that before you might wonder
Oh is there just some formula that I haven't seen before
So with all of that let me go ahead and take a couple questions from the audience
Before we transition to a different sort of example
So it looks like Uma Sherma asks
Can can the base be zero? That's an interesting question okay? Can the base of a logarithm be zero?
Well in terms of our triangle we might think of that as saying
You know zero to some kind of power X is equal to some other value Y
Right this is something that we could write either by saying zero to the X equals Y
Or we could write the same thing by saying log base zero of Y
Is equal to X zero to the what equals X?
Now the issue here is that zero to anything ends up being zero right so?
If we're just going to be thinking of log
base zero of
Y for any other input Y. You know you want to input something like one or two or pi
Anything you might want you're asking the question zero to the what is equal to one or two or pi?
Or whatever number you might have there, and there's just not going to be an answer so at best
You could try to say oh yes log of zero. It's a perfectly valid function
It's only defined on the input zero, but even then you'd have trouble
Trying to finagle what you want there because saying zero to the what equals zero. It's like anything anything applies to it
So your arm is going to be twisted behind your back
However you want to make that work and it corresponds to the fact that the exponential function with base zero
Is entirely zero it doesn't it doesn't map numbers in a nice one-to-one fashion on to each other?
So that's a great question can you have a log base zero now back to the idea of where these things come up in the
real world
One one example I kind of like is the Richter scale for earthquakes
so the Richter scale
Gives us a quantification for how strong an earthquake is okay?
And it can be anything from very small numbers up to very large numbers like I think the largest earthquake ever measured
And this is just a chart that comes from Wikipedia was a nine point five okay?
And to appreciate just how insane that is it's worth
looking at the relationship between
What these numbers mean and then something like the equivalent amount of TNT some sort of measure of how much energy there is in it
And then what we can try to do here is see if we can get an expression for
the Richter scale number in terms of the amount of energy and
Why logarithms would be a natural way to describe this?
So the key to focus on is as we're taking steps forward how much do things increase?
So for example if we go from two
Well in this case it doesn't show us where three is so maybe we think of
Taking a step from two up to four which is kind of like taking two steps
What does that do in terms of the amount of energy?
Well it looks like it takes us from one metric ton of TNT
Which is I guess a large bomb from World War two and it takes us up to a kiloton a thousand times as much
Okay
Which is a small a small atom bomb so just two steps on the Richter scale
Going from an earthquake of magnitude two to an earthquake of magnitude four takes us from large bomb from World War two
Up to the nuclear age, right?
so that is
noteworthy and
The first clean step that we get is going from four to five at least in terms of what this chart is nicely showing us
And evidently a single step up from four to five
Corresponds to going from one kiloton to 32 kilotons
And that was evidently the size of the city destroying bomb that land on Nagasaki
So this is maybe one thing that can be counterintuitive about logarithmic scales if you're just hearing in the news the difference between oh there
Was an earthquake that was a 4.0 versus an earthquake that was a 5.0. It's easy to think yeah four and five
Those are pretty similar numbers
But evidently in terms of TNT amounts that corresponds to multiplying by 32 to get from one to the next
And going from two to four was evidently multiplying by about a thousand
okay, and the only reason that's bigger is because here our chart wasn't showing what three was so we were taking two steps and
You can verify for yourself that if you take a step of 32, and then you multiply by another 32
That's actually pretty close to a thousand
So the idea that additive steps on the Richter number correspond to multiplicative steps in the TNT
Seems to suggest that something logarithmic is at play here, and it's a little interesting to just keep going here and say
How how much does this grow partly?
Because of the the world phenomena. It's describing. Yes, not a huge surprise that as we take another step
It's multiplying by about 32 again
But raining that in to our intuitions. That's the difference between 32 kilotons a small atom bomb
And then one megaton which we might think of as not small atom bomb Nagasaki atom bomb
Which I guess is 32 of the Nagasaki atom bombs
For one megaton that is evidently the magnitude of the double string flat earthquake in Nevada, USA 1994
I didn't know what that was. Thanks Wikipedia in terms of frequencies by the way I
Also looked these up evidently ones that are less than two those happen all the time
There's like 8,000 of those per day, but as soon as we're in the realm of atom bombs things like 3.5 and 4
Those evidently also happen quite frequently somewhere on the earth. There's around 134 of those happening somewhere every day who knew
But as we get even more intense into this 5 and 6 range which you know we're well above the atom bomb scale
now we're only merely at around 2 per day and
You know I'm sure that a geologist could come in and explain why we all shouldn't be super worried about the fact that there's
two atom bomb equivalent
Disruptions to the Earth's crust happening every day, but presumably it's particularly rare for those to be concentrated on some
Some spot like a city where what lots of people live
Now just verifying that I thought that each step involves a growth of 32
Let's look at what the step from 6 up to 7 looks like and here
It's giving us lots more examples in between maybe giving the illusion that that's a bigger step than it actually is and indeed
That's the difference between 1 megaton and 32 megatons, so that's multiplying by 32
One of the things I found most interesting on this chart by the way was
Look at how far we have to go before we get to the largest nuclear weapon that's ever actually been
Tested
This was height of the Cold War the Tsar bomb
That was 50 megatons, and I believe they actually had original plans to have a 100 megaton bomb but talked themselves down from that
50 megatons we're talking start off at that 32 kilotons of the Nagasaki bomb
Multiply by 32 to get a megaton multiply by another 32
Right so we're talking about a thousand times the strength of the World War two ending explosion
And you're still not at the 50 megatons of what humanity is capable of
And that is evidently you know the Java earthquake of Indonesia
so 7.0 is not just a little bit bigger than 6.0. It's a lot bigger and
The point here of course is just that when you have a scale giving you multiplicative increases
It's worth appreciating that what look like small steps
Can actually be huge steps in terms of the energy implied or the absolute values implied here
So it I mean when we're thinking about the fact that there was ever a 9.5
That actually seems absurd given that it's only in the 7.0 range that we're talking about the largest thermonuclear weapon ever put out
And this is indicative of one area where logarithms tend to come about it's
When humans want to create a scale for something that accounts for a hugely wide variance in how big things can be
So in the case of size of earthquakes you can have things from what happens
Just all the time around the earth the size of a large hand grenade
And you want that to be on your scale and something to think about ranging all the way up to you know the largest disruption
that we've
Seen in human history right and in order to have that in a way that you're not just
Writing a whole bunch of different digits in your numbers for one case and a whole bunch of different a smaller number of digits
For your number in another case
It's nice to take logarithms
And then just put that on a single scale that basically puts squishes those numbers between 0 and 10
You see something very similar going on with the decibel scale for music that one actually
Works a little bit differently where every time you take a step up of 10 decibels that corresponds to multi multiplying by 10
So rather than a step of 1 multiplying by 10
It's a step of 10 that multiplies by 10 so that kind of makes the math of it a little bit screwy
But the idea is the same that if you're listening to a sound that's 50 decibels for 60 decibels
It's a lot quieter in terms of the energy being transmitted and going from you know
What would it be 60 to 70 or 70 to 80?
Those steps you know from 60 up to 80 that involves multiplying the amount of energy per square area
By a factor of 100 so every time you see a logarithmic scale
Know in your mind that that means whatever it's referring to under the hood grows by a huge amount
This is again why we saw a lot of logarithmic scales used to describe the coronavirus outbreak so
How might you describe a relationship like this where every time you grow the Richter scale number by 1 you're multiplying by 32
Well, we could think in terms of a log with base 32. I
Could say if I take the log of
I'm just gonna call our the number for the Richter scale. I might think of this as log base 32 and
That's going to correspond to
No, no, no, I'm doing this wrong
That's not the thing that's logged
We take the log base 32 of the big number of the the TNT number something that was like
You know one
Gigaton or one megaton
It's one million
Tons
The log base 32 that should correspond to the Richter scale number
But there might be some kind of offset. So we might say that there's some kind of
Constant s that we're adding to this Richter scale number and this expression is exactly the same
Excuse me for going off the bottom there. This expression is exactly the same as saying
32 to the power of some offset times our Richter scale number, which is the same as taking you know
32 to that offset which itself is just some big constant times
32 to the Richter scale number so you might think of this as just being some constant
Times 32 to the power of the number you see
So this way of writing it really emphasizes the exponential growth of it
that if this is what corresponds to the TNT amount that you see as
You increase that R step by step you're multiplying by 32
But another way of communicating the exact same fact is to take the log base 32 of whatever that amount is
Alright now the next thing I want to talk about is how we don't always have to
Worry about how to compute logs of different bases and it's a little weird here that we were talking about log base 32
I referenced earlier how mathematicians really like to have a log with base e
computer scientists really like to have a log with base 2 and it turns out for
Computational purposes or for also thinking about how these things grow if you have one
Log if you're able to compute one type of log whether that's base 10 base 2 base e you can compute pretty much anything else
That you want
Okay
now to get our intuitions in that direction, let's turn back to our quiz and
go to the next question and
I believe that this question is the most I don't know. This is this is a halfway reasonable question. This should be nice
This is just going to get us prepared to translate from base 2
contexts to base 10 contexts and it's also a good intuition for
understanding powers of 2 to have in general
The relationship that it has with powers of 10 because it's this lovely kind of coincidence of nature that
these two sort of
Well, you'll see what I mean. They play nicely with each other
So a question asks given the fact that 2 to the 10th is 10 24 a thousand and 24 which is approximately
1000 okay, so you can if you're being a little bit loose with your numbers and you're just making approximations 2 to the 10th
Basically a thousand which of the following is closest to being true
Log base 2 of 10 is approximately 0.3
Log base 2 of 10 is approximately sorry log base 10 of 2 is approximately 0.3
Log base 2 of 10 is approximately 1 third or log base 10 of 2 is approximately 1 third
Hey, which of these is closest to being true based on the fact that 2 to the 10th is essentially a thousand
I'll give you a little moment for that
You
Interesting that we've got kind of a split on this one so
I'm wondering if they're gonna be numerically pretty similar or if they're gonna be conceptually similar
Or if there's even a difference between those two
So since answers keep rolling in I'm gonna give this give this a little bit more time so anyone at home watching
Hopefully you already have a pencil and paper out to be noodling through these yourself
That is the spirit of the lectures that we're doing
If you don't now is the time to take out a pencil and paper and
See if you can think this one through and write it out some of the problems that we're gonna build to here
Definitely will require pencil and paper so now is as good a time as any and if you're watching this in the future even if
You can't participate in the live poll. I really do think it's a lot of fun to
Kind of throw your own hat into the mix even if it's not going to contribute to one of the numbers
That you see growing on the screen
I'll give you a little bit more time here as the answers seem to continue rolling in
You
Okay, so I'll go ahead and grade it now and
Let's see how people did on this one
So the correct answer is B
Which is that the log base 10 of 2 is approximately 0.3 and it looks like 1850 of you correctly got that
so congratulations, but the close contender
not at all a
Unanimous decision here looks like it was D. Which is that the log base 10 of 2 is around 1 third so that's good
They're very numerically similar right that
It's either 0.3 or around 1 third which is 0.3 3 3 3 repeating
But the question was asking which one is closest to being true, and let's see how we can think about this so
It points out that you have a power of 2 which is
1024 awfully close to a power of 10 about 10 cubed and the question is how we can leverage this to understand something like
Log base 2 of 10 or log base 10 of 2 as we saw earlier those are just the reciprocals of each other
So what does this mean if log base 2 of 10 is equal to X?
That's the same thing as saying 2 to the X is equal to 10 right. It's asking us 2 to the what equals 10
So what we have here is an expression
10 cubed is approximately equal to 2 to the 10th so what I might write out is we know that 2 to the 10th
Instead of writing it as a 10. I'm going to write that 10 as 2 to the X
Where X is the number such that 2 to the X is approximate is equal to 10?
So if that cubed is the same as 2 to the 10th
This is I'll just write out the full details the same as saying 2 to the 3 X is equal to 2 to the 10th
and
Exponentiation is a nice one-to-one function, so it's okay to just
Say whatever is going on in the input if the outputs are the same the inputs must also be the same
You can't do that with every function people seem to think you can do that with any function
But you just can't and what that means is that?
X is about
X is about 10 thirds, okay
which
Ah
Great so log base 2 of 10 is about 10 thirds, so if we looked at our answers though
That's not actually any of the options. We've got various things asking log base 2 of 10
being around 0.3 or 1 third so it looks like instead we should try to re-express this as log base 10 of 2 and
Well enough what we saw earlier is that log base 2 of 10 we could also say
log base 10 of 2 is
Just 1 over that amount 1 over X and you can see this pretty easily by writing 2 is equal to 10 to the 1 over
X if we're asking 10 to the what equals 2 the answer is 1 over what we just got there, so
Log base 10 of 2 is 1 divided by this amount
Which is 3 tenths?
Which is 0.3
great
So this is kind of a nice constant to think about because there's this wonderful pattern that happens when we're looking at
powers of 2 so if I ask
What is the log base 2 of?
1,000
Like we just saw it's approximately the case that 2 to the power 10
Is equal to a thousand and because we're doing things at logs
I'm just going to be writing it in that way a log 2 of a thousand is approximately 10
Similarly log base 2 of a million
Well, let's see if we have to multiply
2 by itself about 10 times to get to a thousand we should have to multiply it by itself around 20 times
to get up to a million and
Indeed log base 2 of a million is approximately 20
It's a little bit smaller, but this is kind of a nice approximation to have in your mind
And then similarly you'll see why I'm writing out this as a pattern in just a moment if we wanted to go up to a billion
Saying how many times do I have to multiply 2 by itself to get to a billion
This is about 30
And any computer scientist out there who's thought about you know just how much as a kilobyte or a megabyte or a gigabyte?
They'll be familiar with the idea that
Powers of 2 are nice and close to these powers of 10 or more specifically powers of a thousand now
What I want to do is just write all of the same things with log base 10
Not not approximately equal to this is actually equal to 3 log base 10 of a thousand. It's equal to 3
Log base 10 well you tell me what's log base 10 of a million
It's counting the number of zeros it ends up being about 6 and log base 10 of a billion
Counting the number of zeros it ends up being 9
Now the reason I wanted to write all of this out is to just emphasize an interesting pattern here
Which is we're just growing by these increments right as we go from a thousand to a million to a billion with log base 2
We're stepping up by steps of 10
But when we're playing the same game with 10 we're stepping up by these increments of 3
So there's this nice relationship and in fact for all of them to go from log base 2 to log base 10
It seems like we're just multiplying by 0.3. So 10 times 0.3 is 3
20 we scale down by that same amount 30 we scale down by that same amount
Okay
now this is an intuition worth remembering if you have
Your numbers described with one base. It's basically the same as describing them with another base, but there's some rescaling constant
Okay, and then the next question is going to start getting us at that direction
But it's going to be framed in a way that just looks like a whole pile of algebra
And again, I will encourage you to plug in numbers if you want to to gain a little intuition for it
So as our third to last question, this will be a long lecture
We have which of the following is true and then just a whole pile of
Various possible ways to combine log base C of B times log base C of A
Does that equal log base B log base B of A and rather than me reading them out to you?
I'll just let you look through them plug in some numbers
I'll give you I'll give you a meaningful time on this one because it's not it's not obvious unless you're already familiar with logarithms and
It's worth thinking through a little bit
You
We have an outstanding question from the audience
Which is does the bar length of the pole use some kind of log function and healthily?
It looks like Ben Eater has gone ahead and directly answered in the form of the code involved where the chart max is
mapped up is the
raising 2 to the power of a
Ceiling of a log base 2 of the maximum attempt count which I think is to say unraveling
If you're looking at the maximum number
I'm not I'm not great at Vanna whiting this thing if you look at the maximum number in our poll
It's asking what's the log base 2 of that?
so as it crosses different powers of 2 then that rescales it and
Yes, yes is the answer what a fantastically apropos question Thank You Karen
All right, so answers are still rolling in and I think like I said
I just want to give you some more time to think this through because it's looks like a big pile of algebra
plug in some numbers to see what seems to work well and
See which answer fits
You
Okay, so even if you are still thinking about it
I'm gonna go ahead and grade it here and then start talking about
Why it's true and then also why we should care why this is an operation that actually tells us something
so the correct answer which it looks like around 1700 of you got congratulations is
Log base C of B times log base B of A is equal to log base C of A
great
Now that's just a big ol pile of things. Why would that be true? How do we think about it?
Now phase one, like I said, we might plug in an example, but let's try to actually think about why the example holds. So let me
Pull out we've got this as one more of the log rules
This is just repeating the end what the correct answer turned out to be where we've got an expression for
Log base C of B log base B of A and this ends up being log base C of A
It's gotten rid of the B's which is kind of interesting
so
Some examples you might plug in here would be things like let's use a different color. Let's use green
Instead of C. I'm gonna go ahead and plug in 10
Log base 10 of 100 which is kind of asking how many times does 10 go into a
100 in a multiplicative sense how many times do I multiply 10 by itself to get to 100 where the answer is 2 and
then log of
100 of
Let's plug in another power of 10
It'll be nice if it's also a power of 100
So I'll do a million
So
This one is asking 10 to 100 to the what equals a million
How many times do I multiply a hundred by itself to get to a million? How many times does a hundred go into a million?
Phrasing the same thing 10 different ways now the claim is that this is the same thing as taking log base 10 of a million
That if I ask how many times does 10 go into 100 and how many times does 100 go into a million?
Multiplying those should give me the answer to how many times 10 goes into a million now just checking the numbers this certainly works
10 goes into a hundred two times
100 goes into a million
three times in a multiplicative sense in that a hundred cubed is equal to a million and
Indeed how many times does 10 go into a million?
well six
Now we could think of this property in terms of the corresponding exponent rule which is going to look a little bit stranger
But it's actually just saying the entirely the same thing
So here we're if we have a base of C and a base of B
And we're trying to relate those to each other the whole statement is
equal to saying that um suppose that B to the X is equal to a
Got some number B. You raise it to some number X and equals a suppose
It's also the case that C to the Y equals B. Those two together are the same as saying C to the XY equals a
Now that's kind of a mouthful to say out loud
But if you plug in some numbers to translate what all of that is really saying in the context of the example we just did
Saying if you can write a hundred is ten squared and if you can write a million as a hundred cubed
Well that lets you write a million in terms of a power of ten
Okay, so sort of asking this question
How many times does one number go into another?
But letting you layer it on top of each other
Now if we rearrange that expression we get what is probably the second most important of all of our log rules
The most important is this top one that when you multiply the inputs you add the outputs
But the second most important which is known as the change of base formula
Lets us rate that if you want the log base B of some value a
Then for whatever C you want it doesn't actually matter what log you have in your pocket if you use that other log
And you take the log C of a divided by the log C of B that gives you log base B of a
Okay, so just as an example here what this would look like is let's say I wanted to be able to compute log base
100 of things I just really want to it's not a button on my calculator, but I would love to be able to do it
and I want to do it in
With an input like a million well even if I don't have the log base 100 button on my calculator
what I can do is say I'll use the log base 10 button and
Evaluate what's on the inside here which at least positionally it's kind of above the 100 it has a higher altitude as we write it so
This can line up with the notation a little bit that it sits on the numerator and on the bottom
I use the log base 10 button that's in my calculator on the base on the 100 and
Then I can evaluate both of those and it'll give me the answer in this case it gets you 6 divided by 2
which will be 3 and
If we really just think through what this is saying I know I've said it many different times
But it's a it's a convoluted enough way to write things
but an intuitive enough fact that I think just coming at it from a bunch of different angles can be important because like I said
This is probably the second most important log rule
We're asking how many times does 100 go into a million in a multiplicative sense how many times we multiply by itself?
But division is asking that same question in an additive sense if I say how many times does the log of 100 go into the?
Log of a million that's what division means it's saying how many times do I add this bottom number to itself to get to the top?
But anything additive in the logarithm realm is the same as anything multiplicative in terms of what's inside the parentheses
So both of the left-handed side and the right-hand side are just saying how many times does 100 go into a million?
But going about that in different ways
So this is extremely nice because it actually lets us compute things
next time we're going to talk all about the natural logarithm, which is log base e often written ln and
Turns out this is much easier to compute
There's nice math behind it such that if you want to come up with an algorithm that your calculator can use
It's actually a lot easier to think of log base e of numbers
So anytime that you need to go to some kind of calculator. I don't know let's say we popped over to something like Desmos
Always happy to have as a friend, and you wanted to compute log base 10 of
Some number you know let's say we're doing log base 10 of
57 and it looks like that's you know it should make sense. It's between 1 and 2 because 57 was between 10 and 100
What's going on under the hood? How is it actually figuring this out?
It's going to use somewhere in there a change of base formula
Which is going to be that the natural log of 57 divided by the natural log of 10 is the same thing
These are two different ways of writing it so if you know one logarithm. You know all of the logarithms okay, and
Well, let's just use that fact to answer one more of our quiz questions
And this will be the second to last quiz question, so thank you all for sticking it through
I think we will be I
Think you'll be pleased by the last question because the last question will actually be like a fun
Problem-solving puzzle II thing and it'll involve a lot of what we've used up to this point kind of a culminating thing
So before that though just to make sure that we've got the instincts of
Change of base down. What do we have?
Use the approximation that log base 2 of 10 is around 10 thirds so using that approximation
Which of the following is approximately true?
Log base 2 of X is about 10 thirds of log base 10 of X
Log base 2 of X is log base 10 of 10 thirds of X log base 2 of X is
log base 10 of X to the power 10 thirds or
Log base 2 of X is 10 thirds times the log base 10 of X and finally none of the above
So I'll give you a moment to think about that you might want to think to the chart that we were drawing earlier and thinking
about log base 2 and log base 10 as we're looking at powers of 1000 and how each of those grows that can leverage some of
The intuition but I'll let you think about it. Stop talking
You
While answers are rolling in it looks like a number of people have been asking on Twitter about
Basically how complex numbers play into this so you know we've got Jamil asking
What if the base is imaginary?
We've got
Kelcon asking what about complex bases since e to the X is walking around the spiral wouldn't it hit every complex number
Well it won't hit every complex number, but your instinct that it's hitting multiple things is pretty spot-on
Doesn't make sense to talk about logs with imaginary numbers by Nitya so to all of these questions. It's actually a very
Nuanced question the short answer is yes complex logarithms absolutely exist
But each one of them has multiple different outputs so a good a good analogy here is how?
If we have the square root function if I ask something like the square root of 5
You know we have the convention that you always do the positive amount, but that doesn't quite feel honest
It feels like the right answer is to specify that there's two different outputs for the square root function two solutions to x squared
equals 25
And this is actually true in complex numbers as well one of the things we talked about in a complex number lecture
Was that you can take the square root of I and you actually get root 2 over 2 plus root 2 over 2 I?
But that there's two solutions you can do plus or minus this value and so you could say that the square root function
Isn't a function, but it's a multi-valued function
It always has two different outputs now something funky happens when we have exponents at play
So if you're just like someone who hasn't seen this stuff don't worry. We talked about it in previous lectures
I'm obviously jumping around on the complexity level a lot here where if in lecture 5 I'm talking about
Like Euler's formula with complex numbers and compound interest and like how that plays into physics and then lecture 6
We're back to the basics of logarithms. I acknowledge that might be a little bit
jarring to potential audience members, but just continuing on with the answer if you note that e to the
2 pi times you know some number times I
This basically walks you around a circle so that the output will
Walk around a circle and just keep repeating as n goes from 0 up to 1
It'll walk around one cycle and end up back where you started as n goes from 1 to 2
You'll end up back where you started so for example e to the 0 sits here e to the I pi
Is at negative 1 but e to the 2 pi I is?
also at 1 same with
Excuse me same with e to the 4 pi
I
that also
Equals 1 so in general if you wanted to ask something like what is the log base e of 1?
You know on the one hand we want to say the log of
Log base anything of 1 should be 0 because anything to the power 0 equals that 1
But if we're letting complex numbers into the mix you would have to honestly say well
2 pi I is another pretty good answer to this question because e to the 2 pi I also equals 1 and
Same with 4 pi I and you could even go in the negative direction and in general n times pi
Times 2 times I kind of wrote that in a weird order
for any integer in
Feels like a valid answer to this question
So there's a couple ways that you can deal with that in math and before we get back to our usual lesson
Just on logarithm rules. This is interesting enough. I kind of want to pull it up
Let's see what if we have complex logarithm
uh
Great
Wikipedia always to our aid probably it'll have a nice like visual of some kind for us look such fancy color diagrams
What I want okay. This is what I want wonderful. Let's zoom out a little bit
Great, so there's this notion of what's called a Riemann surface
That's basically trying to capture the idea that you have a function with multiple outputs and intuitively
Maybe you can understand what it's getting at where the input would be something on the XY plane and the output
There's just many different outputs sitting there so when you have a complex logarithm you have to account for that, but it's used
It's actually a very useful idea
To do but it takes a lot more nuance than than you might expect
So with all of that hopefully that helped
At least partially answer some of people's questions same same by the way with
Logarithms with based negative numbers because if you're asking like negative 1 to the X and really noodling on what that means it's
It gets you into the realm of
Complex numbers, so you have to deal with the same multiple output idea now
answers are rolling in more slowly so this seems like a fine time to grade things and
the answer turns out to be
You rescale it if you want to go from log base 2 of something to log base 10 of something
It involves rescaling and one way you could think about this is with the change of base formula, so let's say we have
Let's get rid of our e stuff
Let's say you have
Log base 2 of X, but we want to write it in terms of log base 10
We can write that as log base 10 of X
Divided by log base 10 of 2 saying how many times does 2 go into X in a multiplicative sense is
The same as saying how many times does the log of 2 go into the log of X in an additive sense, okay?
And
Well, what is 1 divided by the log base 10 of 2?
so we're going to keep our log base 10 of X out here and
From what we found earlier
We found that log base 10 of 2 was approximately
3 tenths was approximately 0.3. So when we divide by it that should get us 10 thirds
Okay, and this lines up with what we were looking at a little bit earlier with powers of 1000. Let's see. Where was it?
Great
So when we're converting from log base 10 of something up to log base 2
You know here we were thinking of multiplying the top by 0.3 to get to the bottom
But you could also think of multiplying by 10 thirds to get to the top
Anytime you have log base 10 of some number you just rescale it and you have log base 2 of that number and the rescaling
Constant comes from the log base 2 of 10 or vice versa log base 10 of 2
So that's change of base like I said, it's very important
It lets you put everything into a nice universal language and that should be all of the hint that you need for the last question
Which is a challenge question on this one. So if anyone's been watching and they've been like I know logarithms. I've got this
completely down
Let me pull up the last question which came up on let's see
It's not the AMC, but it's whatever the predecessor to the AMC was I believe
So it's you know, it's gonna involve a little cleverness and manipulation
We've got this long
Sequence of fractions. Okay, you take 1 divided by the log base 2 of a hundred factorial
And remember 100 factorial is a hundred times 99 times 98 on the way all the way down to 1
so 1 divided by the log base 2 of that plus 1 divided by the log base 3 of
100 factorial
Plus 1 divided by log base 4 of 100 factorial on and on and on up until 1 divided by the log base 100 of 100
factorial
So this looks rather intimidating, right?
Certainly adding fractions is never fun adding 100 fractions seems even worse
Dealing with a bunch of logs of different bases seems like a pain and the factorial is playing into this
So I'm just gonna give you you know, given that this is the wind down time. I'm gonna give you
Two or three minutes to start thinking about this and if you don't get it, it's totally fine
We're gonna walk through what the answer is, but I'm just gonna let people think about this final challenge question before we call it a day
You
So I'm gonna give you a little bit more time on this one because it's definitely
It's definitely fun to work out and I think if you know how to start then great
But if you don't know how to start just letting yourself kind of work with a couple of the different
rules that we've worked out before
Change of base it comes into play if you'd like to use that
And just kind of keep manipulating and if it feels like you're getting something that's a little too messy
see if you come at it from a different angle and
Because answers are rolling in a little bit more slowly now
What I'm going to do is just start to describe the explanation here and then come back to grade it in just a moment here. So
the expression that we have
Looks like I just started writing it out while you guys were working on it one divided by log base two of a hundred factorial
Plus one divided by log base three of a hundred factorial and before you even start the fact that the thing on the inside of
The log involves a big product of stuff should actually feel good because logs like to take in things that look like products
because of the most important property that we have which
Is the idea that it turns products into addition?
Okay, so right away, you know that you're probably going to use that second thing
You notice is that it's uncomfortable to have all of these different bases log base
2 of something log base 3 of something log base 100 of something so
Translating it all into the common language should be helpful. How does change of base work?
Well asking how many times does to go into a hundred factorial is the same as asking?
How many times does the log of to divide into the log of a hundred factorial?
It doesn't even matter what logarithm you use this log could be base 10 base e base 2 doesn't matter this change of base formula
Still holds now what that means for our expression is instead of taking one divided by log base
2 of 100 factorial I could write that as
log of 2
Divided by so let me draw a little dividing line between what I'm doing here log of 2 divided by log of
100 factorial
Okay, and then similarly?
log of 3
divided by log of
100 factorial so all I'm doing here is taking
The reciprocal so instead of taking log of 100 factorial over log of 2
I have inverted it log of 2 over 100 factorial because that's what this reciprocal is doing
so with that as the beginning I'm gonna go ahead and just grade this lock in the answers and
See how see how everyone's doing
So it looks like
awesome
around
1796 we always we always draw a little bit north of Ramanujan's number around 1800 of you
Answered that it's one which is correct congratulations
70 of you answered 100 which we can maybe see where where that our error would have come from
Those of you that answered zero that's interesting it would imply that somehow you have cancellation at play
Because these are all positive numbers so thinking one of them was negative
So you could probably gut check against the idea that it would be zero
41 of you want me to come up with a number fun numerical fact about 69, but I won't
28 of you said 2 and I think yeah, I think that's I
Think the the difference between 1 and 100 maybe would be interesting to try to analyze, but if we go back to our answer I
Realize it may be a little bit confusing how I've heard this this isn't this is not a big fraction
this was just a dividing line between
Not true ironically trying not to confuse my fractions with each other so
rewriting our expression up on the top here as we add all of these things and we can continue up until
log of 100 all divided by log of 100 factorial
The key is that now all of the denominators are the same so we can add the numerators
No more plus sign is just going to equal something that top is going to look like log of 2
Plus log of 3 plus on and on
up to log of
100 all divided by the log of
100 factorial and it seems like the only little contention among those answering the question is
whether this should simplify to be 1 or should it simplify to be a hundred and
Really the way we can think about this is to just break down that bottom part in terms of what a factorial means
I'll go ahead and do this on the bottom part since I didn't manage my paper real estate very effectively here
the log of 100 times
99 times
98 on and on times 2 times 1 is the same as adding all of them and
You can probably see this mostly cancels out with the top the only question you might have though
Is that in the factorial can we keep multiplying down until we get that one?
Which doesn't really make a difference, but before you think about it too much you might wonder
Hang on you know on the bottom. I'm multiplying everything, and I'm adding this log of 1 but on the top
From what we found before I never saw that log of 1 does that make any difference and the answer is no
Because log of 1 is saying 10 to the power of what equals 1 and the answer is 0
So in fact
Taking the log of 100 factorial is the same as adding the logs of all the numbers from 2 up to 100 and it simplifies
Down to 1 so to those of you who got it congratulations to those of you who feel like you maybe have better intuitions for
Change of base formulas for the fact that logarithms turn multiplication into addition
That's my hope in the next time with this as a foundation of logarithms that can be pointed back to
What I would love to talk about is what's known as the natural logarithm
Log base e and try to give an instinct for why that's something that we care about okay
Why is it that mathematicians just seem to really love the number e sitting in the base of their logarithms?
What does that buy for them? Why does it show up in nature?
So that will happen on Friday at the same time as this lecture, and I look forward to seeing everyone there
You