Hey everyone! So I'm pretty excited about the next sequence of videos that I'm doing.
They'll be about linear algebra, which, as a lot of you know, is one of those subjects
that's required knowledge for just about any technical discipline, but it's also,
I've noticed, generally poorly understood by students taking it for the first time.
A student might go through a class and learn how to compute lots of things, like matrix
multiplication, or the determinant, or cross products, which use the determinant, or eigenvalues,
but they might come out without really understanding why matrix multiplication is defined the way
that it is, why the cross product has anything to do with the determinant, or what an eigenvalue
really represents. Oftentimes, students end up well-practiced in the numerical operations
of matrices, but are only vaguely aware of the geometric intuitions underlying it all.
But there's a fundamental difference between understanding linear algebra on a numeric
level and understanding it on a geometric level. Each has its place, but roughly speaking,
the geometric understanding is what lets you judge what tools to use to solve specific
problems, feel why they work, and know how to interpret the results, and the numeric
understanding is what lets you actually carry through the application of those tools.
Now, if you learn linear algebra without getting a solid foundation in that geometric understanding,
the problems can go unnoticed for a while until you've gone deeper into whatever field
you happen to pursue, whether that's computer science, engineering, statistics, economics,
or even math itself. Once you're in a class, or a job for that matter, that assumes fluency
with linear algebra, the way that your professors or your coworkers apply that field could seem
like utter magic. They'll very quickly know what the right tool to use is and what the
answer roughly looks like in a way that would seem like computational wizardry if you assume
that they're actually crunching all the numbers in their head.
Here, as an analogy, imagine that when you first learned about the sine function in trigonometry,
you were shown this infinite polynomial. This, by the way, is how your calculator evaluates
the sine function. For homework, you might be asked to practice computing approximations
of the sine function by plugging in various numbers to the formula and cutting it off
at a reasonable point. And in fairness, let's say you had a vague idea that this was supposed
to be related to triangles, but exactly how had never really been clear and was just not
the focus of the course. Later on, if you took a physics course, where sines and cosines
are thrown around left and right, and people are able to tell pretty immediately how to
apply them and roughly what the sine of a certain value will be, it would be pretty
intimidating, wouldn't it? It would make it seem like the only people who are cut out
for physics are those with computers for brains, and you would feel unduly slow or dumb for
taking so long on each problem. It's not that different with linear algebra,
and luckily, just as with trigonometry, there are a handful of intuitions, visual intuitions,
underlying much of the subject. And unlike the trig example, the connection between the
computation and these visual intuitions is typically pretty straightforward. And when
you digest these and really understand the relationship between the geometry and the
numbers, the details of the subject, as well as how it's used in practice, start to feel
a lot more reasonable. In fairness, most professors do make an effort
to convey that geometric understanding. The sine example is a little extreme. But I do
think that a lot of courses have students spending a disproportionate amount of time
on the numerical side of things, especially given that in this day and age, we almost
always get computers to handle that half, while in practice, humans worry about the
conceptual half. So this brings me to the upcoming videos.
The goal is to create a short, binge-watchable series animating those intuitions from the
basics of vectors up through the core topics that make up the essence of linear algebra.
I'll put out one video per day for the next five days, then after that put out a new chapter
every one to two weeks. I think it should go without saying that you cannot learn a
full subject with a short series of videos, and that's just not the goal here. But what
you can do, especially with this subject, is lay down all the right intuitions so the
learning that you do moving forward is as productive and fruitful as it can be.
I also hope this can be a resource for educators who are teaching courses that assume fluency
with linear algebra, giving them a place to direct students that need a quick brush-up.
I'll do what I can to keep things well-paced throughout, but it's hard to simultaneously
account for different people's different backgrounds and levels of comfort, so I do encourage you
to readily pause and ponder if you feel that it's necessary.
Actually, I'd give that same advice for watching any math video, even if it doesn't feel too
quick, since the thinking that you do on your own time is where all the learning really
happens, don't you think?
So with that as an introduction, I'll see you next video.