The safest way to reopen the economy soon without causing a second wave in the virus
will involve some notion of contact tracing. But there's a common misconception that this
requires tracking people's locations. A friend of mine, Nikki Case, recently wrote up a post
explaining why contact tracing is needed, and importantly, how the privacy-protecting variants
of it work. This was done in collaboration with the epidemiologist Marcel Salathe and
the security researcher Carmela Trancoso. What follows is a video adaptation of that post.
As far as COVID-19 cares, there are only three kinds of people. Not infected yet,
infected and contagious but with no symptoms, and infected, contagious and showing symptoms.
If you have widespread testing, you can get people to self-isolate as soon as they show symptoms.
The problem is that the virus still spreads because of all the contacts that happened
while people are contagious but asymptomatic. However, if when someone shows symptoms and tests
positive, you isolate not only them, but everyone they've been in contact with, you're staying one
step ahead of the virus. The old-school way to do this is with interviews, but that's slow,
it's inefficient, and frankly it's quite the intrusion on people's privacy. Another approach
in the modern world would be to ask people who've tested positive to forfeit all the geolocation
from their phones, and then track down the people who've been in those same spots.
But now we're well into big brother territory, so do we have to sacrifice privacy for health?
Well, I'll just let Nicky's illustration speak for itself here.
There are several clever algorithms that let you alert everybody who's recently been in contact
with someone who tests positive for COVID-19, but without compromising the privacy of anybody
involved. Side note here, I found this very surprising. I know it shouldn't have been since
many times of thinking something's impossible only to see that cryptography makes it possible,
but I would not blame anybody at all for assuming that downloading an app that can alert everybody
you've been in contact with must necessarily be tracking and revealing your location.
The code for these apps is entirely open, so you don't have to trust me or whoever wrote the app,
or Nicky, or anyone to believe it's doing what it really claims to be doing.
Anyway, back to the post.
Let's see how this works with the help of Alice and Bob. Alice gets a tracing app. Every five
minutes her phone sends out some uniquely pseudo-random gibberish to all the nearby
devices using Bluetooth. Because these messages are pseudo-random, they don't use GPS, and they
contain no information about Alice's identity, not her location, not anything. It really is gibberish,
but the key point is that this gibberish is unique. Now, while her phone sends out messages,
it also listens for messages from nearby phones. For example, Bob's. Bob also has a privacy-first
tracing app that's compatible with, or the same, as Alice's. If Alice and Bob stay close to each
other for more than five minutes, their phones will exchange respective strings of unique gibberish.
Both of these phones remember all of the messages that they said and heard over the last 14 days.
Again, because the random messages contain no information, Alice's privacy is protected from
Bob and vice versa. The next day, Alice develops a dry cough and a fever. Alice gets tested,
Alice has COVID-19. This is not a good day for Alice. But she won't suffer in vain. Alice tells
her app to upload all of the random gibberish messages that it's been sending out to a hospital
database. To do this, she uses a one-time passcode given to her by her doctor. This code
is to prevent spam. The database then stores Alice's gibberish, and again, the random messages
give no information about Alice, where she was, who she was with, what she was doing, or even how
many people Alice met. It really is meaningless to the hospital. But it's not meaningless to Bob's
phone. Bob's phone often checks this hospital list of random messages that have come in from
COVID-19 positive cases. Essentially, the hospital's database is saying to all the phones
out there, hey, we just got this new random gibberish. If you've seen that same random
gibberish sometime in the last 14 days, it means you've been in contact with someone who just
tested positive for COVID-19. Once Bob's phone recognizes some of these numbers that are the
gibberish snippets now known to be associated with positive test cases, it can warn Bob to
self-quarantine. And so Bob cuts off the chain of transmissions. We're staying one step ahead of the
virus. And that's it. That's how digital contact tracing apps can proactively prevent the spread
of COVID-19 while also protecting our rights. Thanks, Alice and Bob. Stay safe.
One important thing to realize is that you don't need everyone to have these apps.
Estimates have it that about 60% would do the trick for COVID-19. Even if you can't catch all
possible contacts, what you need is to catch enough so that the spread of coronavirus shifts
from growing exponentially to shrinking exponentially. For those of you who know what
this means, what we need is for R to drop below one. The author of the post that this video is an
adaptation of is a friend of mine, Nicky Case, who is a brilliant programmer and artist. He often makes
these interactive explanations of societally important ideas, including a new one all about
what happens next with COVID-19. So I would highly recommend taking a look at his work if you get the
chance. He kindly made this post public domain and moreover helped me in putting together this video.
Any reasonable plan for reopening the economy without causing a second wave in the virus
will include some kind of contact tracing. And given how counterintuitive the privacy protection
here can be, I wanted to do all that I could to help amplify this message. If you agree,
please do share either Nicky's original post or this video adaptation of it.
And since the time that Nicky posted that, Apple and Google have put out press releases about their
own interoperable contact tracing systems. And I'll tell you, I'm one of those people who
aggressively turns off location tracking as much as I can on my phone, no matter how annoying the
apps can be about asking. I'm looking at you, Fitbit. But I am 100% on board with these apps,
because it's not tracking your location or anything like that. And if you're a nerd like
me who wants to dig into the cryptography a bit, I would recommend looking at the white paper and
the code for the VP3T algorithm, for which I've left links in the description. And as a final
note, among the many unfortunate consequences of the lockdowns is a spike in calls to mental health
services, like the suicide prevention hotline. If somebody that you know is at risk of suicide,
give them a call, make sure they're doing okay. And if you're at risk, take a look at the resources
in the description. And if it's an option, reach out to the people in your life to talk about what
you're going through.