E raised to pi with an i.
We've been taught by a lot that you've got minus one.
Can we glean what this means?
For such words are absurd.
How to treat the repeat of a feat pi i times.
This is bound to confound till your mind redefines these amounts one can't count which surmount
our friend E.
Numbers act as abstract functions which slide the ridge to the space in its place with a
grace when they sum.
They slide, they don't slide.
Acting a second way, they rotate and dilate but keep straight this same plane.
Now what we write as E to the X won't perplex when you know it's for show that X goes up
and right.
It does not, as you thought, repeat E product E. It functions with gumption on functions
we have now seen.
It turns slide side to side into growths and shrinks both.
Up and downs come around as turns round which is key.
This is why pi times i which slides north is brought forth and returned, we have learned,
is a turn halfway round.
This one, matched by none, turns this way and we're done.