Intro 00:00:01,989 --&gt;
This is a video for anyone who already knows
00:00:06,060 3
what eigenvalues and eigenvectors are, and
who might enjoy a quick way to compute them
a trükk,
in the case of 2x2 matrices. If you’re unfamiliar
with eigenvalues, take a look at this video
de ha
which introduces them.
lehetséges, szeretném, ha
You can skip ahead if you just want to see
újra felfedeznéd
magadnak, ezért
let’s lay down a little background.
00:00:23,349 --&gt;
As a quick reminder, if the effect of a linear
transformation on a given vector is to scale
00:00:28,550 8
it by some constant, we call it an "eigenvector"
of the transformation, and we call the relevant
gyakran lambda betűvel
scaling factor the corresponding "eigenvalue,"
jelöljük. Amikor
ezt egyenletként írja fel,
a little bit, what you see is that if the
és átrendezi a 00:00:47,320
number lambda is an eigenvalue of a matrix
A, then the matrix (A minus lambda times the
--&gt; 00:00:53,190 00:00:53,190 értéket,
identity) must send some nonzero vector, namely
the corresponding eigenvector, to the zero
a módosított mátrix 12-jének
vector, which in turn means the determinant
0-nak kell lennie.
Oké, ez mind
to say, but again, I’m assuming all of this
egy kis
is review for anyone watching.
falat 00:01:09,960 --&gt;
So, the usual way to compute eigenvalues,
how I used to do it, and how I believe most
00:01:12,829 00:01:12,829
students are taught to carry it out, is to
subtract the unknown value lambda off the
--&gt; 00:01:17,939 17
diagonals and then solve for when the determinant
egyenlő 0-val.
Ennek mindig néhány
expand out and simplify to get a clean quadratic
lépést kell tennie
polynomial, what's known as the “characteristic
polynomial” of the matrix. The eigenvalues
a 00:01:32,630 --&gt;
are the roots of this polynomial. So to find
them you have to apply the quadratic formula,
00:01:38,069 további 21
which itself typically requires one or two
egyszerűsítési lépésig.
Őszintén szólva, a folyamat nem szörnyű. De
at least for 2x2 matrices, there’s a much
00:01:52,710 --&gt; 00:01:57,049
more direct way to get at this answer. And
if you want to rediscover this trick, there
25 ennek
are only three relevant facts you need to
know, each of which is worth knowing in its
a két átlós
own right and can help you with other problem-solving.
bejegyzésnek az összege
Number 1: The trace of a matrix, which is
egyenlő a
sajátértékek összegével. Vagy
way to phrase it, more useful for our purposes,
egy másik 00:02:14,700 --&gt;
is that the mean of the two eigenvalues is
the same as the mean of these two diagonal
00:02:18,959 30 31
entries.
értelme van, ha
Number 2: The determinant of a matrix, our
usual ad-bc formula, is equal to the product
megérti, hogy a sajátértékek
of the two eigenvalues. And this should kind
azt írják le,
hogy egy operátor mennyivel
in a particular direction and that the determinant
feszíti meg a
describes how much an operator scales areas
(or volumes) as a whole.
teret 00:02:37,720 --&gt;
Now before getting to the third fact, notice
how you can essentially read these first two
00:02:42,189 35 sokkal lefelé.
values out of the matrix without really writing
Vegyük példának ezt a mátrixot.
Azonnal tudhatja,
the eigenvalues is the same as the mean of
hogy a
8 and 6, which is 7. Likewise, most linear
algebra students are pretty well-practiced
00:02:55,970 --&gt;
at finding the determinant, which in this
case works out to be 48 - 8 So right away
00:03:02,420 39
you know that the product of our two eigenvalues
átlaga 40.
Most szánjon egy pillanatot, és
what will be our third relevant fact, which
nézze meg, hogyan származtathatja
is how to recover two numbers when you know
their mean and you know their product.
a 00:03:17,079 --&gt; 00:03:21,860
Here, let's focus on this example. You know
the two values are evenly spaced around 7,
43 43 szót, nevezzük
so they look like 7 plus or minus something;
ezt a távolságot &quot;d&quot;-nek.
Azt is tudja, hogy
numbers is 40. Now to find d, notice that
ennek a két
this product expands really nicely, it works
out as a difference of squares. So from there,
00:03:40,239 --&gt; 00:03:45,480 47
you can directly find d: d^2 is 7^2 - 40,
or 9, which means d itself is 3.
konkrét példa szorzata
In other words, the two values for this very
4 és 10.
De a célunk egy
want to think this through each time, so let’s
gyors trükk, és
wrap up what we just did in a general formula.
For any mean, m and product, p, the distance
nem 00:04:06,239 --&gt;
squared is always going to be m^2 - p. This
gives the third key fact, which is that when
00:04:12,610 51 ezt a
two numbers have a mean m and a product p,
két számot m
± sqrt(m^2 -
p) alakban írhatja le.
if you ever forget it, and it’s essentially
menet közben 00:04:34,490
just a rephrasing of the difference of squares
formula. But even still it’s a fact worth
--&gt; 00:04:39,360 56
memorizing so that you have it at the tip
of your fingers.
írt nekünk egy gyors
In fact, my friend Tim from the channel acapellascience
csilingelést, hogy egy
kicsit emlékezetesebb legyen.
m plusz vagy mínusz
minus p (ping!)
squaaare négyzetgyöke 00:04:53,880
Let me show you how this works, say for the
matrix [[3,1], [4,1]]. You start by bringing
--&gt; 00:04:59,069 61
to mind the formula, maybe stating it all
in your head. But when you write it down,
p ahogy megy.
you fill in the appropriate values of m and
Tehát ebben a
példában a sajátértékek átlaga
of 3 and 1, which is 2. So the thing you start
megegyezik az átlaggal 00:05:19,030
writing is 2 ± sqrt(2^2 - …). Then the
product of the eigenvalues is the determinant,
--&gt; 00:05:26,780 65 felismerheti,
which in this example is 3*1 - 1*4, or -1.
So that’s the final thing you fill in. This
hogy ez ugyanaz a
means the eigenvalues are 2±sqrt(5). You
mátrix, amelyet az
elején használtam, de figyelje
much more directly we can get at the answer.
meg, hogy 00: 05:47,370
Here, try another one. This time the mean
of the eigenvalues is the same as the mean
--&gt; 00:05:52,190 69 a
of 2 and 8, which is 5. So again, you start
writing out the formula but this time writing
2*8 - 7*1 vagy
5 in place of m [song]. And then the determinant
9. Tehát ebben a
példában a sajátértékek
simplifies even further as 9 and 1.
úgy néznek ki, mint
You see what I mean about how you can basically
just start writing down the eigenvalues while
5 ± sqrt(16), ami
staring at the matrix? It’s typically just
the tiniest bit of simplifying at the end.
00:06:19,590 --&gt; 00:06:23,800
Honestly, I’ve found myself using this trick
73 nagyon sok, ha
lineáris algebrával kapcsolatos gyors
as examples. I’ve been working on a video
jegyzeteket vázolok, és
about matrix exponents, where eigenvalues
pop up a lot, and I realized it’s just very
kis mátrixokat szeretnék használni.
handy if students can read off the eigenvalues
from small examples without losing the main
00:06:37,039 --&gt; 00:06:41,800 77
line of thought by getting bogged down in
egy másik számítás.
Egy másik szórakoztató példaként
set of three different matrices, which come
vessen egy pillantást erre
up a lot in quantum mechanics, they're known
as the Pauli spin matrices. If you know quantum
a 00:06:54,190 --&gt; 00:06:59,419
mechanics, you’ll know that the eigenvalues
of matrices are highly relevant to the physics
81 mechanikára, legyen ez
they describe, and if you don’t know quantum
csak egy kis
bepillantás arról, hogy ezek
to real applications.
a számítások mennyire relevánsak
The mean of the diagonal in all three cases
is 0, so the mean of the eigenvalues in all
00:07:12,639 --&gt; 00: 07:19,990
cases is 0, which makes our formula look especially
simple.
85 ezeknek a
What about the products of the eigenvalues,
mátrixoknak a meghatározói? Az elsőnél
0 - 1 vagy -1. A
also looks like 0 - 1, but it takes a moment
második 00:07:36,430 --&gt; 00:07:42,310
more to see because of the complex numbers.
And the final one looks like -1 - 0. So in
89 tudja, hogy
all cases, the eigenvalues simplify to be
±1. Although in this case, you really don’t
egyenletesen 0 körül
need the formula to find two values if you
helyezkednek el, és
a szorzatuk -1.
Ha kíváncsi vagy, a
mechanics, these matrices describe observations
kvantum kontextusában 00:07:59,759
you might make about a particle's spin in
the x, y or z directions. The fact that their
--&gt; 00:08:04,470 94 vagy
eigenvalues are ±1 corresponds with the idea
that the values for the spin that you would
teljesen másban, nem
observe would be either entirely in one direction
pedig valami folyamatosan a
kettő között. Talán
wonder how exactly this works, or why you
00:08:20,680 --&gt;
would use 2x2 matrices that have complex numbers
to describe spin in three dimensions. And
00:08:26,259 98 00:08:26,259
those would be fair questions, just outside
the scope of what I want to talk about here.
98 mert
You know it’s funny, I wrote this section
szerettem volna
egy olyan
or homework problems, ones where they actually
esetet, ahol 2x2
come up in practice, and quantum mechanics
is great for that. But the thing is after
mátrixok vannak,
I made it I realized that the whole example
kind of undercuts the point I’m trying to
amelyek nem
make. For these specific matrices, when you
csak játék
példák 00:08:38,970
it might actually faster. I mean, take a look
--&gt; 00:08:43,880 102
a the first one: The relevant determinant
directly gives you a characteristic polynomial
hagyományos módszer,
of lambda^2 - 1, and clearly, that has roots
of plus and minus 1. Same answer when you
amelyik jellegzetes
do the second matrix, lambda^2 - 1. And as
polinomokkal rendelkezik,
lényegében ugyanolyan gyors;
already a diagonal matrix, so those diagonal
-&gt; &gt;
entries are the eigenvalues!
00:09:28,850 111
However, the example is not totally lost to
our cause. Where you will actually feel the
egy, plusz
speed up is in the more general case where
you take a linear combination of these three
b-szer a második,
matrices and then try to compute the eigenvalues.
plusz c-szer
You might write this as a times the first
a harmadik.
A kvantummechanikában ez
describe spin observations in a general direction
00:09:47,360 --&gt; 00:09:53,240
of a vector with coordinates [a, b, c]. More
specifically, you should assume this vector
116 továbbra is
is normalized, meaning a^2 + b^2 + c^2 = 1.
When you look at this new matrix, it’s immediate
nulla, és akkor
to see that the mean of the eigenvalues is
is élvezheti, ha
egy pillanatra megáll,
of those eigenvalues is still -1, and then
hogy megbizonyosodjon arról, hogy
from there concluding what the eigenvalues
must be. And this time, the characteristic
a termék 00:10:13,560
polynomial approach would be by comparison
a lot more cumbersome, definitely harder to
--&gt; 00:10: 18
do in your head.
710 120 alapvetően
To be clear, using the mean-product formula
nem különbözik a
karakterisztikus polinom gyökeinek
mean, it can't be, they're solving the same
megtalálásától; I 00:10:33,110
problem. One way to think about this, actually,
is that the mean-product formula is a nice
--&gt; 00:10:37,160 125
way to solve quadratic in general (and some
viewers of the channel may recognize this).
egy másodfokú gyökei
This about it: When you’re trying to find
együtthatói alapján, ez egy
másik helyzet, amikor
sum of two values, and you also know their
ismeri a 00:10:50,950
product, but you’re trying to recover the
original two values.
--&gt; 00:10:54,820 129
Specifically, if the polynomial is normalized
so that this leading coefficient is 1, then
lineáris együtthatót, ami
the mean of the roots will be -½ times this
-1-szerese ezen gyökerek
összegének. A 00:11:12,820
screen that makes the mean 5. And the product
--&gt; 00:11:17,610
of the roots is even easier, it’s just the
constant term no adjustments needed. So from
133 példában a
there, you would apply the mean product formula
and that gives you the roots.
hagyományos másodfokú
On the one hand, you could think of this as
képlet könnyebb
változata. De az
is that it's fewer symbols to memorize, it's
igazi előny 00:11:34,200
that each one of them carries more meaning
with it.
--&gt; 00:11:37,370 137
The whole point of this eigenvalue trick is
that because you can read out the mean and
nem kell átmennie
product directly from looking at the matrix,
a karakterisztikus polinom
beállításának közbenső lépésén.
You can jump straight to writing down the
00:11:49,930 --&gt; 00:11:54,339
roots without ever explicitly thinking about
what the polynomial looks like. But to do
141 egy nagyon
that we need a version of the quadratic formula
where the terms carry some kind of meaning.
speciális közönség számára,
I realize that this is a very specific trick,
de bárcsak tudtam
volna az egyetemen,
to know any students who might benefit from
szóval ha megtörténik
this, consider sharing it with them.
00:12:08,240 --&gt; 00:12:10,330
The hope is that it’s not just one more
thing to memorize, but that the framing reinforces
00:12 :10,330 --&gt;
some other nice facts worth knowing, like
how the trace and determinant relate to eigenvalues.
00:12:15,140 146 szánjon
If you want to prove those facts, by the way,
egy pillanatot az
általános mátrix karakterisztikus
hard about the meaning of each of these coefficients.
polinomjának kiterjesztésére, és
Many thanks to Tim, for ensuring that this
mean-product formula will stay stuck in all
gondolja, 00:12:32,449 --&gt;
of our heads for at least a few months. If
you don’t know about acapellascience, please
00:12:36,420 150 különösen
do check it out. "The Molecular Shape of You",
az egyik legnagyobb
dolog az interneten.