Now that we've seen what a derivative means and what it has to do with rates
of change, our next step is to learn how to actually compute these guys. As in, if
I give you some kind of function with an explicit formula, you'd want to be able
to find what the formula for its derivative is. Maybe it's obvious, but I
think it's worth stating explicitly why this is an important thing to be able to
do, why much of a calculus student's time ends up going towards grappling with
derivatives of abstract functions rather than thinking about concrete rate of
change problems. It's because a lot of real-world phenomena, the sort of things
that we want to use calculus to analyze, are modeled using polynomials,
trigonometric functions, exponentials, and other pure functions like that. So if you
build up some fluency with the ideas of rates of change for those kinds of pure
abstract functions, it gives you a language to more readily talk about the
rates at which things change in concrete situations that you might be using
calculus to model. But it is way too easy for this process to feel like just
memorizing a list of rules, and if that happens, if you get that feeling, it's
also easy to lose sight of the fact that derivatives are fundamentally about just
looking at tiny changes to some quantity and how that relates to a resulting tiny
change in another quantity. So in this video and in the next one, my aim is to
show you how you can think about a few of these rules intuitively and
geometrically, and I really want to encourage you to never forget that tiny
nudges are at the heart of derivatives. Let's start with a simple function like
f of x equals x squared. What if I asked you its derivative? That is, if you were
to look at some value x, like x equals 2, and compare it to a value slightly bigger,
just dx bigger, what's the corresponding change in the value of the function, df?
And in particular, what's df divided by dx, the rate at which this function is
changing per unit change in x? As a first step for intuition, we know that you can
think of this ratio df dx as the slope of a tangent line to the graph of x
squared, and from that you can see that the slope generally increases as x
increases. At 0, the tangent line is flat and the slope is 0. At x equals 1, it's
something a bit steeper. At x equals 2, it's steeper still. But looking at graphs
isn't generally the best way to understand the precise formula for a
derivative. For that, it's best to take a more literal look at what x squared
actually means, and in this case let's go ahead and picture a square whose side
length is x. If you increase x by some tiny nudge, some little dx, what's the
resulting change in the area of that square? That slight change in area is
what df means in this context. It's the tiny increase to the value of f of x
equals x squared caused by increasing x by that tiny nudge dx. Now you can see
that there's three new bits of area in this diagram, two thin rectangles and a
minuscule square. The two thin rectangles each have side lengths of x and dx, so
they account for 2 times x times dx units of new area. For example, let's say
x was 3 and dx was 0.01, then that new area from these two thin rectangles would
be 2 times 3 times 0.01, which is 0.06, about 6 times the size of dx. That little
square there has an area of dx squared, but you should think of that as being
really tiny, negligibly tiny. For example, if dx was 0.01, that would be only 0.0001,
and keep in mind I'm drawing dx with a fair bit of width here just so we can
actually see it, but always remember in principle dx should be thought of as a
truly tiny amount, and for those truly tiny amounts a good rule of thumb is
that you can ignore anything that includes a dx raised to a power greater
than 1. That is, a tiny change squared is a negligible change. What this leaves us
with is that df is just some multiple of dx, and that multiple, 2x, which you could
also write as df divided by dx, is the derivative of x squared. For example, if
you were starting at x equals 3, then as you slightly increase x, the rate of
change in the area per unit change in length added, dx squared over dx, would
be 2 times 3, or 6, and if instead you were starting at x equals 5, then the
rate of change would be 10 units of area per unit change in x.
Let's go ahead and try a different simple function, f of x equals x cubed.
This is going to be the geometric view of the stuff that I went through
algebraically in the last video. What's nice here is that we can think of x
cubed as the volume of an actual cube whose side lengths are x, and when you
increase x by a tiny nudge, a tiny dx, the resulting increase in volume is what I
have here in yellow. That represents all the volume in a cube with side lengths x
plus dx that's not already in the original cube, the one with side length x.
It's nice to think of this new volume as broken up into multiple components, but
almost all of it comes from these three square faces, or said a little more
precisely, as dx approaches 0, those three squares comprise a portion closer and
closer to 100% of that new yellow volume.
Each of those thin squares has a volume of x squared times dx, the area of the
face times that little thickness dx. So in total this gives us 3x squared dx of
volume change. And to be sure there are other slivers of volume here along the
edges and that tiny one in the corner, but all of that volume is going to be
proportional to dx squared or dx cubed, so we can safely ignore them. Again this
is ultimately because they're going to be divided by dx, and if there's still
any dx remaining then those terms aren't going to survive the process of letting
dx approach 0. What this means is that the derivative of x cubed, the rate at
which x cubed changes per unit change of x, is 3 times x squared.
What that means in terms of graphical intuition is that the slope of the graph
of x cubed at every single point x is exactly 3x squared.
And reasoning about that slope, it should make sense that this derivative is high
on the left and then 0 at the origin and then high again as you move to the right,
but just thinking in terms of the graph would never have landed us on the
precise quantity 3x squared. For that we had to take a much more direct look at
what x cubed actually means.
Now in practice you wouldn't necessarily think of the square every
time you're taking the derivative of x squared, nor would you necessarily think
of this cube whenever you're taking the derivative of x cubed. Both of them fall
under a pretty recognizable pattern for polynomial terms. The derivative of x to
the fourth turns out to be 4x cubed, the derivative of x to the fifth is 5x to
the fourth, and so on.
Abstractly you'd write this as the derivative of x to the n for any power n
is n times x to the n minus 1.
This right here is what's known in the business as the power rule. In practice
we all quickly just get jaded and think about this symbolically as the exponent
hopping down in front leaving behind one less than itself,
rarely pausing to think about the geometric delights that underlie these
derivatives.
That's the kind of thing that happens when these tend to fall in the middle of
much longer computations.
But rather than chucking it all off to symbolic patterns let's just take a
moment and think about why this works for powers beyond just 2 and 3. When you
nudge that input x, increasing it slightly to x plus dx, working out the
exact value of that nudged output would involve multiplying together these n
separate x plus dx terms. The full expansion would be really complicated
but part of the point of derivatives is that most of that complication can be
ignored.
The first term in your expansion is x to the n. This is analogous to the area of
the original square or the volume of the original cube from our previous examples.
For the next terms in the expansion you can choose mostly x's with a single dx.
Since there are n different parentheticals from which you could have
chosen that single dx, this gives us n separate terms, all of which include n
minus 1 x's times a dx, giving a value of x to the power n minus 1 times dx. This
is analogous to how the majority of the new area in the square came from those
two bars, each with area x times dx, or how the bulk of the new volume in the
cube came from those three thin squares, each of which had a volume of x squared
times dx. There will be many other terms at this expansion but all of them are
just going to be some multiple of dx squared so we can safely ignore them, and
what that means is that all but a negligible portion of the increase in
the output comes from n copies of this x to the n minus 1 times dx. That's what
it means for the derivative of x to the n to be n times x to the n minus 1. And
even though like I said in practice you'll find yourself performing this
derivative quickly and symbolically, imagining the exponent hopping down to
the front, every now and then it's nice to just step back and remember why these
rules work. Not just because it's pretty and not just because it helps remind us
that math actually makes sense and isn't just a pile of formulas to
memorize, but because it flexes that very important muscle of thinking about
derivatives in terms of tiny nudges. As another example think of the function f
of x equals 1 divided by x. Now on the one hand you could just blindly try
applying the power rule since 1 divided by x is the same as writing x to the
negative 1. That would involve letting the negative 1 hop down in front leaving
behind 1 less than itself which is negative 2. But let's have some fun and
see if we can reason about this geometrically rather than just plugging
it through some formula. The value 1 over x is asking what number multiplied by x
equals 1. So here's how I'd like to visualize it. Imagine a little rectangular
puddle of water sitting in two dimensions whose area is 1. And let's
say that its width is x which means that the height has to be 1 over x since the
total area of it is 1. So if x was stretched out to 2 then that height is
forced down to 1 half. And if you increased x up to 3 then the other side
has to be squished down to 1 third. This is a nice way to think about the graph
of 1 over x by the way. If you think of this width x of the puddle as being in
the xy plane then that corresponding output 1 divided by x, the height of the
graph above that point, is whatever the height of your puddle has to be to
maintain an area of 1. So with this visual in mind for the derivative
imagine nudging up that value of x by some tiny amount, some tiny dx. How must
the height of this rectangle change so that the area of the puddle remains
constant at 1? That is increasing the width by dx adds some new area to the
right here. So the puddle has to decrease in height by some d 1 over x so that the
area lost off of that top cancels out the area gained. You should think of that
d 1 over x as being a negative amount by the way since it's decreasing the
height of the rectangle. And you know what? I'm gonna leave the last few steps
here for you, for you to pause and ponder and work out an ultimate expression. And
once you reason out what d of 1 over x divided by dx should be I want you to
compare it to what you would have gotten if you had just blindly applied the
power rule purely symbolically to x to the negative 1.
And while I'm encouraging you to pause and ponder here's another fun challenge
if you're feeling up to it. See if you can reason through what the derivative
of the square root of x should be.
To finish things off I want to tackle one more type of function, trigonometric
functions, and in particular let's focus on the sine function. So for this section
I'm going to assume that you're already familiar with how to think about trig
functions using the unit circle, the circle with a radius 1 centered at the
origin. For a given value of theta like say 0.8 you imagine yourself walking
around the circle starting from the rightmost point until you've traversed
that distance of 0.8 in arc length. This is the same thing as saying that the
angle right here is exactly theta radians since the circle has a radius of
1. Then what sine of theta means is the height of that point above the x-axis,
and as your theta value increases and you walk around the circle your height
bobs up and down between negative 1 and 1. So when you graph sine of theta versus
theta you get this wave pattern, the quintessential wave pattern. And just
from looking at this graph we can start to get a feel for the shape of the
derivative of the sine. The slope at 0 is something positive since sine of theta
is increasing there, and as we move to the right and sine of theta approaches
its peak that slope goes down to 0. Then the slope is negative for a little while
while the sine is decreasing before coming back up to 0 as the sine graph
levels out. And as you continue thinking this through and drawing it out if
you're familiar with the graph of trig functions you might guess that this
derivative graph should be exactly cosine of theta since all the peaks and
valleys line up perfectly with where the peaks and valleys for the cosine
function should be. And spoiler alert the derivative is in fact the cosine of
theta, but aren't you a little curious about why it's precisely cosine of theta?
I mean you could have all sorts of functions with peaks and valleys at the
same points that have roughly the same shape, but who knows maybe the derivative
of sine could have turned out to be some entirely new type of function that just
happens to have a similar shape.
Well just like the previous examples a more exact understanding of the
derivative requires looking at what the function actually represents rather than
looking at the graph of the function. So think back to that walk around the unit
circle having traversed an arc with length theta and thinking about sine of
theta as the height of that point.
Now zoom into that point on the circle and consider a slight nudge of d theta
along their circumference, a tiny step in your walk around the unit circle.
How much does that tiny step change the sine of theta?
How much does this increase d theta of arc length increase the height above the
x-axis?
Well zoomed in close enough the circle basically looks like a straight line in
this neighborhood.
So let's go ahead and think of this right triangle where the hypotenuse of
that right triangle represents the nudge d theta along the circumference, and that
left side here represents the change in height, the resulting d sine of theta.
Now this tiny triangle is actually similar to this larger triangle here
with the defining angle theta and whose hypotenuse is the radius of the circle
with length 1.
Specifically this little angle right here is precisely equal to theta radians.
Now think about what the derivative of sine is supposed to mean.
It's the ratio between that d sine of theta, the tiny change to the height,
divided by d theta, the tiny change to the input of the function. And from the
picture we can see that that's the ratio between the length of the side adjacent
to the angle theta divided by the hypotenuse.
Well let's see, adjacent divided by hypotenuse, that's exactly what the
cosine of theta means, that's the definition of the cosine.
So this gives us two different really nice ways of thinking about how the
derivative of sine is cosine. One of them is looking at the graph and getting a
loose feel for the shape of things based on thinking about the slope of the sine
graph at every single point. And the other is a more precise line of
reasoning looking at the unit circle itself.
For those of you that like to pause and ponder, see if you can try a similar line
of reasoning to find what the derivative of the cosine of theta should be.
In the next video I'll talk about how you can take derivatives of functions
who combine simple functions like these ones, either as sums or products or
function compositions, things like that. And similar to this video the goal is
going to be to understand each one geometrically in a way that makes it
intuitively reasonable and somewhat more memorable.