Intro 00:00:01,989 --&gt;
This is a video for anyone who already knows
00:00:06,060 3 il
what eigenvalues and eigenvectors are, and
who might enjoy a quick way to compute them
trucco, ma se
in the case of 2x2 matrices. If you’re unfamiliar
with eigenvalues, take a look at this video
possibile vorrei che
which introduces them.
tu lo
You can skip ahead if you just want to see
riscoprissi da solo,
quindi per quello
let’s lay down a little background.
00:00:23,349 --&gt; 00:00:28,550
As a quick reminder, if the effect of a linear
transformation on a given vector is to scale
8 spesso
it by some constant, we call it an "eigenvector"
of the transformation, and we call the relevant
indicato con la
scaling factor the corresponding "eigenvalue,"
lettera lambda. Quando
lo scrivi come
a little bit, what you see is that if the
un&#39;equazione e riorganizzi 00:00:47,320
number lambda is an eigenvalue of a matrix
A, then the matrix (A minus lambda times the
--&gt; 00:00:53,190 12
identity) must send some nonzero vector, namely
the corresponding eigenvector, to the zero
di questa matrice modificata
vector, which in turn means the determinant
deve essere 0.
Ok, è tutto
to say, but again, I’m assuming all of this
un boccone 00:01:09,960
is review for anyone watching.
--&gt; 00:01:12,829
So, the usual way to compute eigenvalues,
how I used to do it, and how I believe most
00:01:12,829 --&gt; 00:01:17,939
students are taught to carry it out, is to
subtract the unknown value lambda off the
17 è uguale
diagonals and then solve for when the determinant
a 0.
Fare questo implica
expand out and simplify to get a clean quadratic
sempre qualche passo
polynomial, what's known as the “characteristic
polynomial” of the matrix. The eigenvalues
per 00:01:32,630 --&gt;
are the roots of this polynomial. So to find
them you have to apply the quadratic formula,
00:01:38,069 altri 21
which itself typically requires one or two
passi di semplificazione.
Onestamente, il processo non è terribile. Ma
at least for 2x2 matrices, there’s a much
00:01:52,710 --&gt; 00:01:57,049
more direct way to get at this answer. And
if you want to rediscover this trick, there
25 la somma
are only three relevant facts you need to
know, each of which is worth knowing in its
di queste due
own right and can help you with other problem-solving.
voci diagonali è
Number 1: The trace of a matrix, which is
uguale alla somma
degli autovalori. Oppure
way to phrase it, more useful for our purposes,
un altro 00:02:14,700 --&gt;
is that the mean of the two eigenvalues is
the same as the mean of these two diagonal
00:02:18,959 30 31
entries.
che abbia senso
Number 2: The determinant of a matrix, our
usual ad-bc formula, is equal to the product
se capisci che gli
of the two eigenvalues. And this should kind
autovalori descrivono di
quanto un operatore allunga
in a particular direction and that the determinant
lo spazio 00:02:37,720
describes how much an operator scales areas
(or volumes) as a whole.
--&gt; 00:02:42,189 35
Now before getting to the third fact, notice
how you can essentially read these first two
molto verso il basso.
values out of the matrix without really writing
Prendi questa matrice qui come esempio.
Puoi subito sapere
the eigenvalues is the same as the mean of
che la media
8 and 6, which is 7. Likewise, most linear
algebra students are pretty well-practiced
di 00:02:55,970
at finding the determinant, which in this
case works out to be 48 - 8 So right away
--&gt; 00:03:02,420 39
you know that the product of our two eigenvalues
è 40.
Ora prenditi un momento
what will be our third relevant fact, which
per vedere come puoi
is how to recover two numbers when you know
their mean and you know their product.
derivare 00:03:17,079 --&gt; 00:03:21,860
Here, let's focus on this example. You know
the two values are evenly spaced around 7,
43 chiamiamo quel qualcosa
so they look like 7 plus or minus something;
&quot;d&quot; per la distanza.
Sai anche che il
numbers is 40. Now to find d, notice that
prodotto di questi due
this product expands really nicely, it works
out as a difference of squares. So from there,
00:03:40,239 --&gt; 00:03:45,480 47
you can directly find d: d^2 is 7^2 - 40,
or 9, which means d itself is 3.
esempio specifico risulta essere
In other words, the two values for this very
4 e 10.
Ma il nostro obiettivo è
want to think this through each time, so let’s
un trucchetto veloce, e
wrap up what we just did in a general formula.
For any mean, m and product, p, the distance
non 00:04:06,239 --&gt; 00:04:12,610
squared is always going to be m^2 - p. This
gives the third key fact, which is that when
51 puoi scrivere questi
two numbers have a mean m and a product p,
due numeri come m
± sqrt(m^2 - p)
Questo è abbastanza veloce
if you ever forget it, and it’s essentially
da ridirigere al volo
just a rephrasing of the difference of squares
formula. But even still it’s a fact worth
00:04:34,490 --&gt; 00:04:39,360 56
memorizing so that you have it at the tip
of your fingers.
ci ha scritto un
In fact, my friend Tim from the channel acapellascience
breve jingle per renderlo
un po&#39; più memorabile.
m più o meno radice
minus p (ping!)
squaaaare di me al
Let me show you how this works, say for the
matrix [[3,1], [4,1]]. You start by bringing
quadrato 00:04:53,880 --&gt; 00:04:59,069 61
to mind the formula, maybe stating it all
in your head. But when you write it down,
p man mano che
you fill in the appropriate values of m and
procedi. Quindi in questo esempio,
la media degli autovalori
of 3 and 1, which is 2. So the thing you start
è la stessa della
writing is 2 ± sqrt(2^2 - …). Then the
product of the eigenvalues is the determinant,
media 00:05:19,030 --&gt; 00:05:26,780
which in this example is 3*1 - 1*4, or -1.
So that’s the final thing you fill in. This
65 potresti riconoscere che questa
means the eigenvalues are 2±sqrt(5). You
è la stessa matrice
che stavo usando all&#39;inizio,
much more directly we can get at the answer.
ma nota come 00:
Here, try another one. This time the mean
of the eigenvalues is the same as the mean
05:47,370 --&gt; 00:05:52,190 69
of 2 and 8, which is 5. So again, you start
writing out the formula but this time writing
è 2*8 - 7*1 o
5 in place of m [song]. And then the determinant
9. Quindi in questo
esempio, gli autovalori
simplifies even further as 9 and 1.
assomigliano a 5 ±
You see what I mean about how you can basically
just start writing down the eigenvalues while
sqrt(16), che 00:06:19,590
staring at the matrix? It’s typically just
the tiniest bit of simplifying at the end.
--&gt; 00:06:23,800 73 è
Honestly, I’ve found myself using this trick
molto quando sto abbozzando
appunti rapidi relativi
as examples. I’ve been working on a video
all&#39;algebra lineare e voglio
about matrix exponents, where eigenvalues
pop up a lot, and I realized it’s just very
usare matrici piccole
handy if students can read off the eigenvalues
from small examples without losing the main
00:06:37,039 --&gt; 00:06:41,800 77
line of thought by getting bogged down in
un calcolo diverso.
Come altro esempio divertente,
set of three different matrices, which come
dai un&#39;occhiata a questa
up a lot in quantum mechanics, they're known
as the Pauli spin matrices. If you know quantum
00:06:54,190 --&gt; 00:06:59,419 81
mechanics, you’ll know that the eigenvalues
of matrices are highly relevant to the physics
meccanica, lascia che sia
they describe, and if you don’t know quantum
solo un piccolo
assaggio di come questi
to real applications.
calcoli siano effettivamente rilevanti
The mean of the diagonal in all three cases
is 0, so the mean of the eigenvalues in all
00:07:12,639 --&gt; 00: 07:19,990
cases is 0, which makes our formula look especially
simple.
85 le determinanti
What about the products of the eigenvalues,
di queste matrici? Per il
primo è 0 - 1 o -1. I secondi
also looks like 0 - 1, but it takes a moment
00:07:36,430 --&gt; 00:07:42,310
more to see because of the complex numbers.
And the final one looks like -1 - 0. So in
89 sanno che sono
all cases, the eigenvalues simplify to be
±1. Although in this case, you really don’t
equidistanti attorno allo
need the formula to find two values if you
0 e il loro
prodotto è -1.
Se sei curioso, nel contesto
mechanics, these matrices describe observations
quantistico 00:07:59,759 --&gt; 00:08:04,470
you might make about a particle's spin in
the x, y or z directions. The fact that their
94 o interamente in
eigenvalues are ±1 corresponds with the idea
that the values for the spin that you would
un altro, in contrapposizione
observe would be either entirely in one direction
a qualcosa che sta
continuamente nel mezzo. Forse
wonder how exactly this works, or why you
dovresti 00:08:20,680 --&gt; 00:08:26,259
would use 2x2 matrices that have complex numbers
to describe spin in three dimensions. And
98 perché volevo
those would be fair questions, just outside
the scope of what I want to talk about here.
un caso in cui
You know it’s funny, I wrote this section
hai matrici 2x2
che non sono solo
or homework problems, ones where they actually
esempi giocattolo 00:08:38,970
come up in practice, and quantum mechanics
is great for that. But the thing is after
--&gt; 00:08:43,880 102 usare
I made it I realized that the whole example
kind of undercuts the point I’m trying to
il metodo il
make. For these specific matrices, when you
metodo tradizionale, quello con
i polinomi caratteristici,
it might actually faster. I mean, take a look
è sostanzialmente altrettanto veloce;
a the first one: The relevant determinant
directly gives you a characteristic polynomial
00:08:58,700 --&gt; 00:09:03,390
of lambda^2 - 1, and clearly, that has roots
of plus and minus 1. Same answer when you
106 per l&#39;ultima matrice,
do the second matrix, lambda^2 - 1. And as
dimentica di fare
qualsiasi calcolo, tradizionale o
already a diagonal matrix, so those diagonal
meno, è 00:09:20,940
entries are the eigenvalues!
--&gt; 00:09:23,510 00:09:23,510 --
However, the example is not totally lost to
our cause. Where you will actually feel the
&gt; 00:09:28.850 111
speed up is in the more general case where
you take a linear combination of these three
uno, più b per
matrices and then try to compute the eigenvalues.
il secondo, più
You might write this as a times the first
c per il terzo.
Nella meccanica quantistica, questo
describe spin observations in a general direction
sarebbe 00:09:47,360 --&gt;
of a vector with coordinates [a, b, c]. More
specifically, you should assume this vector
00:09:53,240 116 ancora pari
is normalized, meaning a^2 + b^2 + c^2 = 1.
When you look at this new matrix, it’s immediate
a zero, e potresti
to see that the mean of the eigenvalues is
anche divertirti a fermarti
per un breve momento
of those eigenvalues is still -1, and then
per confermare che il
from there concluding what the eigenvalues
must be. And this time, the characteristic
prodotto 00:10:13,560 --&gt; 00:10:
polynomial approach would be by comparison
a lot more cumbersome, definitely harder to
18.710 120 non è
do in your head.
fondamentalmente diverso dal trovare
To be clear, using the mean-product formula
le radici del polinomio
caratteristico; I 00:10:33,110 --&gt;
mean, it can't be, they're solving the same
00:10:37,160 125 le
problem. One way to think about this, actually,
is that the mean-product formula is a nice
radici di una quadratica
way to solve quadratic in general (and some
viewers of the channel may recognize this).
dati i suoi coefficienti,
This about it: When you’re trying to find
questa è un&#39;altra situazione
in cui conosci il
sum of two values, and you also know their
coefficiente lineare 00:10:50,950 --&gt;
product, but you’re trying to recover the
original two values.
00:10:54,820 129 coefficiente lineare,
Specifically, if the polynomial is normalized
so that this leading coefficient is 1, then
che è -1 volte
the mean of the roots will be -½ times this
la somma di quelle
radici. Per l&#39;esempio
screen that makes the mean 5. And the product
su 00:11:12,820 --&gt;
of the roots is even easier, it’s just the
constant term no adjustments needed. So from
00:11:17,610 133 una
there, you would apply the mean product formula
and that gives you the roots.
versione più leggera
On the one hand, you could think of this as
della tradizionale formula
quadratica. Ma il vero
is that it's fewer symbols to memorize, it's
vantaggio 00:11:34,200 --&gt;
that each one of them carries more meaning
with it.
00:11:37,370 137 non è
The whole point of this eigenvalue trick is
that because you can read out the mean and
necessario passare attraverso il
product directly from looking at the matrix,
passaggio intermedio per impostare
il polinomio caratteristico.
You can jump straight to writing down the
00:11:49,930 --&gt; 00:11:54,339 141
roots without ever explicitly thinking about
what the polynomial looks like. But to do
per un pubblico molto
that we need a version of the quadratic formula
where the terms carry some kind of meaning.
specifico, ma è
I realize that this is a very specific trick,
qualcosa che vorrei sapere
al college, quindi
to know any students who might benefit from
se ti capita 00:12:08,240
this, consider sharing it with them.
--&gt; 00:12:10,330 00:12
The hope is that it’s not just one more
thing to memorize, but that the framing reinforces
:10,330 --&gt; 00:12:15,140 146
some other nice facts worth knowing, like
how the trace and determinant relate to eigenvalues.
prenditi un momento per
If you want to prove those facts, by the way,
espandere il polinomio
caratteristico per una matrice
hard about the meaning of each of these coefficients.
generale e pensa
Many thanks to Tim, for ensuring that this
mean-product formula will stay stuck in all
00:12:32,449 --&gt; 00:12:36,420 150
of our heads for at least a few months. If
you don’t know about acapellascience, please
in particolare, è
do check it out. "The Molecular Shape of You",
una delle cose più
grandiose su internet.