Today we are going to talk about one of my absolute all-time favorite pieces of math.
It's incredibly fundamental to engineering, to mathematics itself, to quantum mechanics,
but it's something that has a terrible, terrible name. We call them complex numbers.
And worse than that, the things that bring about complex numbers we call imaginary numbers.
And before we get into any of it, what I want to do is start with kind of a poll,
just to poll the audience on seeing what you guys can consider to be, well, real. What do you
consider to exist when it comes to numbers? So we've already been doing a couple polls in the
warm-up animations, but as a serious poll of sorts, one that's actually going to help me see
where you're coming from before we begin the lesson here, I just want to ask you a very simple
question, okay? So let's go ahead and poll it up here. Pull it on up. And, oh, for whatever reason,
it seems like we're having trouble polling this one up. Hmm. Okay, there we go. Took a little
delay there. Among the values 2, square root of 2, square root of negative 1, and infinity,
which would you personally consider to really exist, whatever really existing means to you?
So in theory, if you guys go to 3b1b.co slash live, you should be able to answer this,
and then the statistics based on your answers are going to start populating the screen.
We won't know what those answers refer to. At the moment, all we know is that there's someone
who has a lead, another one that's pretty close behind it, and as your answers come in and as the
servers kind of digest them, we'll start to see some of the stats here. If you go to that page,
by the way, 3b1b.co slash live, which redirects to itempool.com, what you're going to find is at
the very top you can ask a question on Twitter, and all that's going to do is basically open up
a tweet that's going to have the hashtag in it, lockdown math, and that's the way that we're going
to be doing questions to this. Instead of a live chat, anytime you have a question or a comment
that you want to, you know, insert into the lesson and let that be part of the discussion,
it's going to be pulled up here, and it looks like we already have one. This is from Yash
Dave, who asks if you could rename the complex numbers and the so-called imaginary numbers to
something more intuitive, to a name that conveyed the fact that they have numerous applications in
the real world, what would you name them? I couldn't be happier that you asked, Yash. So I
have one friend who seems very passionate about the fact that we should call them sneaky numbers.
Personally, I'm very fond of trying to connote spinning and rotation, and this is one of the
things we'll talk about in today's lesson, is the fact that what we call complex numbers, what we
call imaginary numbers, some of the main uses that they have come from very elegant descriptions of
how to rotate stuff, and I hope you'll kind of see what I mean as we proceed with that.
So on our poll, asking you guys which numbers you consider to really exist, which is of course a
subjective question, there's no right or wrong answer here. I am genuinely curious, actually,
how this breaks down, because it's not at all a strong consensus in one direction. It seems like
we've got three top contenders, and then three that are falling pretty evenly behind that, so
let's go ahead and take a look. What do you consider to really exist when it comes to numbers?
Now, I can imagine which ones might be the top two, but I'm very curious about the fact that
there's three all kind of coinciding with each other there, and it looks like I'm getting a
little bit of a delay before the reveal, so there's kind of this nice dramatic pause.
I'll tell you, for me personally, I feel like it's very silly to answer anything that's either,
that's not all of them or none of them. I can maybe understand if someone wants to treat
infinity as something different, because it's ill-defined. There's lots of different things
that that might mean, but insofar as numbers exist at all, if you consider what a number is to be a
real thing, then it would... oh man, I can't believe that we're stalling out on this one. We had fixed
it by live stream too, but I guess there's going to be an oscillation between when it works and
when it doesn't. But for me personally, basically, any time that you have a numerical construct
that's helpful in the real world, you know, I consider that real. I would say that if it's
something that's actually useful in an application, then it is as real as words are, right? You're
never going to run into an abstract word like happiness out there, but it has a kind of reality
in our minds, and things like the square root of two, which you can't express as a fraction,
or things like the square root of negative one that don't show up among real normal numbers,
you know, even if they might seem a little bit different. Oh, this is such a shame. I'm genuinely
curious to see what your answers are, but it's not showing up for me, which I suppose means we'll
have to move on with the lesson, but this will presumably begin working by the end and we can
maybe pull things up again. So let me go ahead and take that away. What I'd like to do for you today,
basically, is show you the sense in which imaginary numbers are useful, the complex numbers
are useful, and from there maybe try to imbue them with a little more reality. I won't assume that
you know what they are yet, it's meant to be a basic primer, but let's just dive right in, okay?
The end, by the way, the very end here, I want to talk about two different trigonometric functions,
and this is kind of the thing that we're going to build to, two identities from trigonometry, and
I understand that maybe, oh, these complicated identities from trigonometry is not going to be
the best way to lure some people into understanding, oh yeah, complex numbers,
they're really useful, you're really going to love them. But I do think it's interesting that
you can have a fact that has nothing to do with complex numbers or the square root of negative 1,
it's just trigonometry, it's everything we were talking about last time, and you can have facts
that are pretty hard to remember. I remember when I was in school and we learned these addition
formulas, that if you want to know the cosine of the sum of two different angles, you know,
it's this kind of long thing in terms of cosines and sines of the original two angles,
there's this minus sign that would always trip people up, if you do the same for the sign,
it looks similar but there's a plus sign, and instead of having cos-cos you have cos-sin,
it's something that's very error-prone if you're just trying to memorize it as it is.
However, if you come at it with complex numbers, this is not only much less error-prone,
it has a very beautiful meaning and it just falls right out. So even if you don't necessarily believe
in the reality of the square root of negative 1, you at the very least have to admit that it's
interesting that it can make other pieces of math useful, that other pieces of math a little bit
more understandable too. And trigonometry is just the tip of the iceberg. If you talk to anybody
who's in engineering, anybody who's going into serious math, they'll tell you that complex
numbers are as real a part of their work and their life as real numbers are. But the starting point
looks very strange, okay? When you start introducing this, the very first thing you do is to say,
assume that there's some number i so that i squared is equal to negative 1. And I think to
a lot of students there's maybe one of two possible reactions that you can have here. One is, no there
isn't, right? Any time I square a number, even if it's negative, if I take negative 5 for example,
and I square it, well a negative times a negative is a positive, so I get 25. Any number that you
square, if it's positive, well that just stays positive. So it seems like no matter what, when
I'm squaring numbers, I always get a positive number. I'm never going to get anything negative.
So this does not exist, no such number. However, if a mathematician comes and says, oh no no it
exists, we've defined it so that that's the case. I think the other reaction someone can have is,
hang on a second, you can do that? When you have a problem that you can't solve, you can just say,
oh I've defined things so that we now magically have a solution. Okay, next time I'm having
trouble with my homework and I don't know what the answer to x is, I will be like, let x be the
value defined to be the answer to this question. So if you're uncomfortable with this, you're
definitely not alone. In fact, Rene Descartes coined the term imaginary for these numbers
as a derogatory. It was meant to make fun of the fact that obviously there is no such answer and
it shouldn't be taken as serious math. And then we stuck with that as a convention and we still
call them imaginary numbers, which is genuinely absurd. But that's not the only weird assumption
that we make. The second weird thing that you do when you start talking about complex numbers
is to say, there's not just such a number i, but we're going to give it a home. Instead of the real
number line, which you know all of these numbers we know when we square them, you can't get a
negative, what we do is say i lives in a different dimension. i lives perpendicularly, there's one
above and then there's one below, negative i, and you can have negative 2i, you scale it however you
want. Essentially it's proposing that numbers be two-dimensional and that i has a very specific home,
one unit perpendicular, uh, perpendicularly above the real number line. And, okay, if we want to extend
our number system, I get it, maybe it's useful to put some kind of number up there, but why i, right?
Why not say infinity is the number that sits one unit above zero, or one divided by zero, or any
other problem that you couldn't solve before and you make up an answer to, why should that live
there? What on earth does the idea of a point one unit above the real number line in a separate
dimension have to do with squaring to negative one? So I hope to answer this for you. At the very
beginning, let's just talk about how if you're adding numbers that are two-dimensional like this,
the rules are pretty straightforward and it operates essentially the same as vectors, for
any of you who might be familiar with vectors. So let's say, hypothetically, I have a number,
oh I don't know, let me draw one here that's going to be 4 plus i, okay? And then I'm going to take a
second number and it's helpful to draw them as vectors, kind of an arrow from the number zero,
and this one is going to end up at negative 2 plus 2i. So what I'm saying is, uh, you take the real
number negative 2 and then you move in that perpendicular direction into the extension of
our number system, which again, you're kind of asking the students to take a lot on faith here
that you're okay to do that, that you're allowed to just pretend that the numbers extend in this
direction. If you take that on faith and you follow, hopefully the fact that it becomes useful
helps to justify why we're doing any of this. So my question for you is simply, what happens
when we add these two numbers? Now, assuming that our question system has not broken down,
I should be able to do this as a proper poll. And let me go ahead, I guess we can first check the
previous poll, okay things seem to be working, so we can take a little step back in the lesson,
so I'm just genuinely curious, I want to know how you guys answered on this one.
Um, it looks like there's a, there's a back and forth between answers f and d, so f is all of them,
saying that all of these should be considered real. And interesting, d is the one that says
you should consider 2 square root of 2 and negative 1, but not infinity, so there's a good contingent
of you out there who would just reject infinity as being considered real, but are very comfortable
with the square root of negative 1, that's awesome. And then after that, it looks like c,
people who reject the square root of negative 1, fascinating, I actually would have thought that
none of them would have come higher than that. None of them is much lower at a. Okay, so it looks
like we've got a cohort of people who are comfortable with negative 1, a large cohort are
uncomfortable with infinity, that's a topic for another day, don't worry about it, and then a
number of people who are kind of in that middle ground of maybe not being super comfortable with
the idea that negative 1 might be real. Let's see if we can convince you of the difference of that.
So for our first much more mathematical question, as kind of a warm-up, I just want to ask you to
add these two. Before I've taught you how to add them, make a guess at how it might work, and
I hope that it feels pretty straightforward, addition is actually the least interesting part
of this, but it is, it's a good thing to know when you're learning about complex numbers.
It's definitely one of those operations that you are going to need to know.
Unfortunately, and you can tell by the fact that I'm stalling and what I'm saying here,
it looks like the question is still not loading completely correctly, so I'm going to have a
stern word with Cam and Ider behind the scenes who have otherwise built such a beautiful,
beautiful interface that's helpful for this kind of back and forth between you guys and me. I'm
going to have a stern word with them behind the scenes, but in the meantime let's go ahead and
move forward with the lesson here. So I guess I can pull it up on the, just on the piece of paper,
and you can follow along at home, see what the addition might be. It turns out to be relatively
straightforward. If you're moving four units to the right and then one unit up, and you want to
add the idea of moving two units to the left and then two units up, well you just do each of those
one at a time. I'll go ahead and pull out black here. The real part is going to be those four to
the right, then minus two to the left. Okay, straightforward enough. And then the imaginary part
is going to be this one unit up and then these two units up, one plus two, times i. So is that one i
plus two i. And then when you work that out, four minus two is two, one plus two is three.
A nice simple introduction here. Addition doesn't really have anything complicated going on, which
is great. That means that it's one fewer thing for us to worry about. What is so complex about
complex numbers after all? Well where everything becomes interesting is when you try to multiply
these numbers together. So with vectors, there's not really any notion of multiplying them to get
two vectors back, at least when we're in the 2D plane. You have some notions like cross products
and dot products that in three dimensions can get you something like it. But the rules end up being
very different from that in the number system. You can't really do algebra. You can't do things like
assume that if two numbers multiply to make zero, then one of them has to be zero. But complex
numbers are going to end up behaving much like the real numbers, so rules from algebra can carry
over. But to understand what that multiplication rule is, I just want to ask you a simple question.
Which is basically, suppose I have the point three, two. We're not even going to think of it as a
complex number per se. If I just have some sort of coordinate grid and I go to the point with
x coordinate three and y coordinate two, what is the 90 degree rotation of this? If I rotate it 90
degrees and let's say counterclockwise. I think see counter, counter, geez, writing is difficult.
Counterclockwise.
Okay. Now what's lovely about this is we can basically just turn our paper to figure it out.
You say okay if it started at three, two and then I rotate 90 degrees counterclockwise, I can just
read that off now as being negative two in the x direction and then three in the y direction, if I
had rotated the whole plane like that. So what we've done here is we've taken three, two and then we
convert it to negative two, three. Something which maybe in our original system
you know looks like this negative two and then three. That's going to be the 90 degree rotation.
And what's nice here is that that rule is very simple and it applies to any pair that we might
have. If I took a pair of numbers a comma b okay and then I said where is that going to rotate to
if I rotate it 90 degrees it's going to end up by swapping the coordinates b a and then making
that first one negative. That's a 90 degree rotation and a nice gut check here is to say
what happens when we do that twice what if we do that same very mechanistic operation again twice
and I'm going to go and take this I swap the two coordinates we get a negative b but then that
first one becomes negative. So that was another 90 degree rotation. Well what's happened here is
we've just made both of the coordinates negative and that's reassuring because if I take some point
sitting at a b and then I rotate it 90 degrees so this will be my initial 90 degree rotation
and then another 90 degrees that's the same as 180 degree rot- oh no I've done that wrong.
That will be the same as a 180 degree rotation which should look like this ignore the other
vector that I drew which is just taking both of the coordinates and making them negative
negative a negative b okay so that's reassuring this operation that does a 90 degree rotation
actually behaves like you would expect it to. Now why am I asking you this? Well I'm being told that
supposedly I'm allowed to ask you questions again so I'm going to have you do your very first
complex product. Oh look a lot of people did submit answers very good. Great let's let's
grade the complex addition actually let's let's see if it is as straightforward a process as I
was hoping it was and see how much explanation is demanded. Okay so it looks like a majority of you
did get the correct answer which is 2 plus 3i. Very good very good. 52 of you answered simply 2
which would have been the real part of the answer so maybe just the fact that there's some vertical
component and you need to still add those vertical components or maybe those of you who answer 2
reject the reality of imaginary numbers so you just don't even acknowledge that vertical
component. Some of you answered negative 2 3 which I guess is just making that's just swapping
up whether you're taking 4 minus 2 or 2 minus 4 so that's completely understandable. We've got 2
plus 3 which is maybe just dropping off the i so I think maybe a lot of like simple errors and entry
and you know that happens to all of us especially on tests is sometimes you know what the right
answer is but then you you forget a symbol or you swap two so that's all very good. Let's go ahead
and try our very first product though like I said so here because I already talked through one of
the questions we're going to go ahead and skip ahead of it we know how to rotate something like
3 comma 2 so I'm not even going to give you time to do that and properly grade it. Stal stal words
words you know they tell me that it's working and yet it's very slow for me to progress forward so
you know if I'm not going to have a stern word with them you guys can go at them on twitter too
under the same place that we ask questions and just say hey kamineter can't you make the live
questions work a little bit better for us? Okay I think we're finally there. Everybody ready? Aha!
Wonderful! Very simple question I want you to take the number i and I want you to multiply it by 3
plus 2i and even though I haven't really talked about the rules for multiplication what I can say
is pretend like it operates just like it does for normal numbers you've got things like the
distributive property where you can distribute this throughout and then the defining feature of
i is this idea that i squared is negative one that's the only special thing you need to know
about that other than that just treat it like it's a normal number okay and then proceed forward with
the product. Wonderful! Okay so it looks like we've got quite a few of you coming in to answer which
is always lovely super exciting for me by the way just how many people are enthusiastic about coming
and like getting back to the fundamentals of math in this lockdown and just you know we're going to
sit back for an hour and we're going to learn about complex numbers and we're actually going
to participate we're actually going to answer questions as you do it rather than sitting in
passively watching this is genuinely delightful to me. Okay this is this isn't necessarily a
question I was expecting to divide the audience necessarily so unsurprisingly it looks like we
have a very strong majority in one direction hopefully in the correct direction but if not
that would that would heavily inform where the lesson should go so that would be quite useful
and I think that's probably enough time so I'm going to go ahead and lock the answers into this
one okay and it looks like the majority of you answered negative two plus three i which is
absolutely correct absolutely correct so there's two ways to think about this okay one of them is
to walk forward with the algebra and just do it a little bit mechanistically okay so if we pull
ourselves up our sheet if we take i times three plus two i three plus two i it just distributes
i times three is going to be three i i times two i is going to be two times i squared by definition
i squared is negative one which means that our final answer is going to look like negative two
plus three i okay and like I said it looks like a majority of you correctly did that product now
it's one thing to just walk through it mechanistically it's another to step back and say
what just happened geometrically right because what we just talked through was the fact that
if you want to rotate numbers 90 degrees the rule is to swap the two coordinates and then multiply
that first one by negative two well look at what's happened here we've got three and two those
coordinates have been swapped two is now the real part three is the imaginary part but that two got
multiplied by a negative one because i has this defining feature of squaring to become negative
one so that should give you some indication that okay multiplying by i has this action of rotating
things by 90 degrees maybe that means that it's not a crazy thing to do to geometrically position
i at a 90 degree angle with the real number line okay now to really see why that ends up being
useful it turns out that if you have that if you have a number that behaves this way it gives you
a computational mechanism for all of the other types of rotations that you might want to do
that might not necessarily be 90 degrees and to show you why this works i'm going to go ahead and
pull up an animation so let's say we have any number z and in this case z is going to be let's
see where do i have it z is going to be at two uh plus i great and let's say i want to understand
what is multiplying by z due to every other possible complex number well we can go one by one
the very first one that's relatively simple is if i ask what is z times one where does it take the
number one well z times one is going to be z so we're going to take the number one which i might
draw with a little yellow arrow and we're going to rotate and stretch that arrow up to the point
where z is great a kind of trivial fact even though it's trivial i'm actually going to take
a moment to write that down just so that we can oh no no no that's for that's for later that is
randy don't you guys worry about him he'll be coming in in just a moment so i just want to write
down three crucial facts that are getting an influence rotation three facts i'll call it three
facts about multiplication the first two are going to look simple the third one is going to
look innocuous but it ends up being extremely constraining so the first one is that if i have
any number z and i multiply it by one will i get the number z back okay geometrically that means
with that we stretch and rotate that vector one to get what we want the second one is that if i
take z times i from what we just talked about that is the 90 degree rotation what i might write
is like rotate by 90 degrees the number z okay so often our animation what does that look like
let's see we've already multiplied by one we take i and then it's going to move to whatever the 90
degree rotation point for z itself is okay so two down infinitely many to go okay we know what it
does to one we know what it does to i let's see if we can understand what z does to any other
possible number well it turns out those two is really all we need to work with if we have the
distributive property so the third fact that's going to look kind of innocuous is let's say i
take this z and i multiply it by c plus d times i where c and d are just any two numbers okay well
this is going to distribute so z times c i'm actually going to write that a little differently
i'm going to write it as c times z plus z times di which again i'm going to write in kind of a
funny order and write that as d times z i now the idea here is well we know where z is we also know
where z times i is so if we're just scaling them up by some other constants that completely
constrains where we need to go so let me go ahead and write this down with an example okay
let's say that we go back here and i want to know what multiplying by z does to anything i want to
tell i want to convince you that it rotates all of the grid in a way that keeps these lines
parallel it keeps them evenly spaced keeps them perpendicular to each other it applies this very
constrained rule to the whole plane and really just think through any one particular point for
this let's say that we have two times negative i okay so you move two units in the positive right
direction and then negative one unit in the vertical direction well after the product
where that's going to land has to be two times wherever z lands plus negative one times wherever
i lands okay and we see that right it's two times this yellow vector and it'll be negative one times
the green vector so here even before you actually work out the product we could just read off the
fact that z here which looks like it's two plus i multiplied by two minus i must land on the number
five okay so i actually want you guys to work this out algebraically because i do think that it's
it's edifying to see this work in practice right the fact that we have this geometric rule where
we're just kind of stretching and rotating and this corresponds to an otherwise very mechanistic
process of expanding out a sum so let's pull back our quiz and i'm going to
it's a little bit silly because i've revealed the answer but what i actually want you guys to do
here is take a look at the question which says what is two plus i times two minus i and if you
have notes right now if you have a pencil and paper which i encourage you to always come to
class with i want you to try working it out do the first inside outside last distribution
property just to see mechanistically what number ends up popping out from this and then we'll try
to see how that squares with the geometric intuition so while you're doing that while
you're working that out hopefully on pencil and paper it looks like we've got a question from the
audience which is is i the same as i and j the vectors in physics great question actually that's
that's a much more interesting question than you might think it is the short answer is no so in
physics you often describe the right word direction as i and then the up and down direction as oh we
got another one here let me finish answering the question first so in physics you often have this
situation where instead of describing the xy plane you describe the right vector as i sometimes i hat
and the vertical one as j hat so that's a separate thing that's uh how physicists will describe the
right direction up direction for vectors they're not necessarily describing complex numbers
totally separate thing what's more interesting actually is that the reason that convention came
about uh i believe has to do with a number system that extends even beyond complex numbers it's
called the quaternions so with the complex numbers we introduce something called i with the quaternions
we introduce j and k these two other numbers both of which also have squares to negative one
as it happens and the guy who invented them hamilton he was trying to describe three
dimensional space very elegantly and using the purely imaginary directions i j and k became a
nice way to do that and i think it's because of that and his attempts to push that forward
that the conventions slipped into uh normal physics to just describe those as i and j of
course that leads to serious confusion now because if we look at how physicists think of things you
know i is in the right direction j is in the vertical direction but with complex numbers i is
of course in the vertical direction so it just makes for a whole potential mess um now what was
our oh no it looks like they took away the comment oh man there was a comment giving them some sass
and then they got embarrassed so they pulled it away well it's on screen it's in there for everyone
in the future to see now i think that's probably been enough time to work through a little bit of
algebra here so let's go ahead and grade it for everyone to see and it looks like the vast
majority of you well i told you the answer so i'm going to assume the vast majority of you
are giving the correct answer oh interesting okay so it looks like uh five five is correct and
that's the most common answer but then the ones uh where missed were three and four and maybe we
can try to understand why three and four would have been common um misconceptions on this one
69 is close 0 i plus 5 is correct but i guess just uh formatted in a weird way um so let's
let's go ahead and work this one out by hand okay it's actually you know kind of a pleasant process
to multiply complex numbers because it's so deterministic you know what you have to do you
know where you start you know where you're going to end and it's really just kind of practicing
through it um so two times two that's the first thing that we get and then you take the inside
parts i times two so that's going to be 2i and then the outside parts which is negative i times
two so that's negative 2i and then the last part which is i times negative i so that'll be negative
i squared the defining feature remember is that i squared is the same as negative one which means
that the real component of our answer is going to be two times two or four now minus negative one
which is plus one so that'll be five and then the imaginary parts cancel each other out that
2i cancels out with a negative 2i so to everyone on the quiz who answered uh five plus zero i uh
you know extra credit to you because that actually is 100 correct you're even emphasizing that we're
doing this in a complex context so there's no reason that you should have been graded
incorrectly on that one um however what's uh what's interesting here those of you who
watch the very first lecture might notice the similarity with difference of squares
and this is effectively a difference of squares type question and i'm going to guess that those
of you who answered three or four it probably came down to if you answered three it would have
been because you took this four and you subtracted one rather than subtracting negative one very
common mistake no harm in that and then if you answered four it comes from forgetting the fact
that i squared can be simplified into a real number so that you know that very much counts
for the the real component of your final answer now what's interesting i think is that that
process of just walking through the algebra feels very different from this geometric idea that we
had before of saying multiplying by z has the action of rotating and stretching things and how
it rotates and stretches things is in the way that's necessary to get the number one to sit on
the number z and in fact i have a i have a good friend uh ben sparks who is a frequent number file
uh contributor that some of you might recognize and i asked him uh to whip up a little geogra
thing because he's just a geogra whiz and he actually created basically the complex number
equivalent of a slide rule that we can play with here so the way that this is going to work is that
i can take the number one and sort of drag it around the plane and as i do the rest of the grid
moves in the way that it has to so that the origin stays fixed in place and then everything else kind
of stays rigid with the exception of being able to stretch so the way that you might use this is to
say let's say we want to know what z times w is well i'm going to stretch and rotate the number
one so that it lands on z and then i'm going to follow what happens to w which is now drawn as a
orange vector follow what happens to w and as it lands there we can just read off that it ends up
at five now even though in practice computationally you would be working it out with the algebra like
we just showed having in the back of your mind that this is how they operate helps draw the
connection between complex numbers and geometry and also trigonometry which we'll get to in a
moment and that turns out to be a much more helpful connection than you might expect so
let me go ahead and ask you guys a second question here which is bring back our helpful little friendly quiz
given what i just told you about how complex numbers act i want you to guess for me it's
okay if you don't know it's okay if you just want to hazard a guess here what is the complex number
z so that multiplying by z has the effect of rotating 30 degrees or pi sixth radians
counterclockwise okay so you want to number z so that when it's being applied as an action and
you're saying what do you do to all the other possible complex numbers the corresponding
action is to rotate by pi six radians or 30 uh 30 degrees okay great we've got a lot of answers
coming in strong consensus around one of them which is always a good sign let me show you uh
how i might draw this out um if i were doing things so i would take a look at um a unit circle of some
kind and luckily i have my infinite supply of unit circles sitting right here and i would say okay i
know that the action that i want is going to be whatever takes the number one to something that's
the 30 degree rotation of the number one that sits up here whatever complex number z this is
is going to have the appropriate action and then from there it's all of the trigonometry that you
and i were working through last time so let's look at our answers and let's go ahead and lock them
into place now before we talk through the explanation and the correct answer in this context
is d which is cosine of pi six plus i sine of pi six congratulations to the uh majority of you
who correctly answered that very interesting to me actually is that the second most common answer
was a which is one plus pi six um and i think that's that's an utterly reasonable guess actually
and let's take a look at why so if we go back to our our friendly unit circle the number we were
going for is uh like i said sitting pi six radians around and from everything we talked
about last time the x component of that is the cosine of pi six this is sort of how cosine is
defined and then the y component of that is going to be sine of pi six which means that that number
z that we're dealing with okay is going to have an x component of cosine of pi six
and then an imaginary component what's in the y direction of sine of pi six
great now that second most common answer like i said that's very interesting um if we pull it up
it was a which was one plus pi six over i let's take a look at where that sits with a i'll bring
in a second cleaner unit circle here like i said i've got an infinite supply they were guessing
that it's one and that instead of walking pi six around that you walk to straight up pi six okay
which is actually quite close right especially for small angles if you're just walking straight
up that's not too different from walking around the circle so if you were to try to use that
number um to have the action of rotating by 30 degrees it would have an action of rotating by
something that's slightly less than 30 degrees and they would stretch things out by something
that's slightly more than a factor of one but it's actually close um which is cool because usually
the misconceptions might be like very wrong computationally but the idea that the uh the
misconception here was like computationally quite close indicates that maybe the geometric reasoning
was lining up with truth which i think is awesome so to give you an illustration of how this might
actually be used okay we have a number that has this action of a 30 degree rotation um i want to
bring in uh of course a friendly pi creature for us to all think about
brandy so let's say that i have a pi creature and i'm i don't know animating a video and at some
point for whatever reason i want that pi creature to rotate 30 degrees okay i just want them to
rotate there's lots of ways you could do this one of the most common ones in computer graphics is to
use matrices which might be a whole topic for another day but a tactic you could use is to use
complex numbers and the way this would work is to think of our pi creature as living in the complex
plane and then at any kind of computer graphics it's always defined with various points often
these control points around it and each one of those control points i would give complex
coordinates to so for example let's say the the lower right foot here or i guess stage left our
right looks like it has coordinates about one negative three so that would be given the number
one minus three i and then from what you guys just told me in answering the question if we want
to take that point and then figure out where it gets when we rotate 30 degrees about the origin
what i should be multiplying it by is cosine of 30 degrees by sine of 30 degrees and if ever you
wanted to be convinced that complex numbers are just as real as real numbers i think one factor
to consider is that many programming languages have built into them complex numbers they are
considered as real as real numbers so what i might do i could pull up a little python terminal for
us to play with and complex numbers if i write something like three negative one are considered
a valid type in this case they use j um i think basically because in programming parlance i is
often used as an indexing variable so they just go with j instead that actually matches with
electrical engineering convention too where they instead of using i for the imaginary number they
use j because again i was kind of already used so three minus one j you can just read that as being
the same as three minus one i and i can take this number and i can multiply it by other complex
values i don't know like five four two if i multiply that it's going to apply the rules of
complex multiplication which basically is just foiling it out you can think of this as being the
real part is three times four or 12 minus negative one times two because remember that i squared
gives us that negative so that's where the 14 comes from and then the imaginary part is going
to be that negative one times four which is negative four plus three times two which indeed
works out to two so that's kind of cool python seems to be working all of this out for us and
what that means remember is let's say that we wanted to rotate our pi creature and let's say
i'm just going to focus on one point like his foot sitting here which is at one negative three
so let's say i define the foot to be uh sitting at real part one imaginary part negative three
uh the rotating number that i want z is what you guys figured out for me we're going to need a
little math for this so let's import math always a sign that you're about to have some fun so we're
going to call z a complex number whose real part is the cosine well i can't write 30 degrees because
this will all be in radians so i'll write it as pi six that's the same thing as 30 degrees
and then the y is going to be the sine of that sine of math dot pi over six great so if we look
at its components uh the real part is around 0.866 and the imaginary part should be exactly
one half but you know often you get a little numerical error because computers they can't get
all the real numbers perfectly there's just not enough information in the universe so they have
to have a little bit of an error there some of you might recognize that uh that first part is
the square root of three divided by two this is everything we were working out last lecture for
computing things like the cosine of pi six now what this means for us is if we take z times foot
right or remember foot was that one negative three z times foot should tell us where it goes when you
just go through the mechanistic operation of complex multiplication this point should tell us
where it lands evidently it's supposed to land at around 2.3 as a real part and then negative 2.09
as the imaginary part and indeed when we play that out and we follow our little foot point here
where does it land all right it looks like the real part is a little above two and the imaginary
part is a little less than negative two and any deviation there is probably because the foot
wasn't exactly at that point one negative three like i said but you can see what i mean in
principle you tell the computer to do this for every single point in a given image that you want
and it will tell you where the outputs should be it'll tell you where the rotated versions should
be so complex numbers are certainly as real as real numbers in that respect um it looks like
we've got a question from the audience so let's go ahead and pull that up seal programmer asks what
is the biggest reason that people use vectors and matrices to represent rotation instead of complex
numbers that is actually a very interesting question i don't know if there's a great reason
actually because if all you're going to do is rotate and then potentially scale things you
could have everything defined in terms of complex numbers in 2d graphics in 3d graphics that actually
wouldn't work complex numbers only describe rotations in two dimensions however if you
want to use a number system to describe rotations in three dimensions instead of using matrices you
could use these things called quaternions which are they're basically the complex numbers on
steroids and in fact they they expose you to fewer errors like there's errors that come about
when you try to use matrices for 3d rotation this thing called gimbal lock talk to any roboticist or
any computer graphics programmers they'll tell you that gimbal lock is a real pain and the quaternions
this sort of complex numbers on steroids helps to solve that problem there's a whole other contingent
of people who feel passionate about something called geometric algebra that is a whole other
topic potentially for another day but that's that's a really valid question you've got these
two perspectives on one one possible operation but if we're just coming at it from the idea that
complex numbers play a role in other parts of math and in other parts of engineering
i think thinking of the rotation implications really helps us see that and this is particularly
visceral for me when i think in terms of trig identities so if you remember at the very beginning
i opened up by talking about one particular trig identity and without pulling it up again i don't
want to go back and just read off of it i'm going to ask you one more question which this is going
to be a tricky question this one will actually take some time to work through which is i want
you to calculate for me the cosine of 75 degrees okay and let's go ahead and pull this up as a quiz
question so let's pull up our quiz let's move on to the next question let's cross our fingers and
hope that cam and eater have not broken anything again and that's all it's asking what is the cosine
of 75 degrees okay now let me get you started here on how you might think about it 75 degrees
it's not going to be based on any triangles that we might have seen maybe you've seen a 75 degree
triangle and you happen to remember what its side lengths were but most people won't have
however what you can do is note that 75 is the same as taking 45 degrees and then walking another
30 degrees around okay 45 plus 30 degrees and if our question is asking us for the cosine of 75
one way to think of it is if you first walk 45 degrees around and then you walk another 30
degrees around what is the x coordinate of that corresponding point okay so this is going to have
some coordinates x y the cosine of 75 degrees is asking for the x coordinate of that now like i
said i think this is um this is not easy okay so it's going to take some time to work out and while
you guys are working this out i want you to actually pull out some pencil and paper and
think it through i'm just going to pull up a little pause and ponder music and give us i don't
know i might give us a full 60 seconds or so to like noodle this one out and think it through
and in the meantime if you want to ask any questions you know how to do so through twitter
it's with the hashtag lockdown math and i might go ahead and take a couple questions while people
try working this out by hand which again i heavily encourage you to do even if you're not watching
this live even if you're watching this at a later date this is the time to say okay i'm going to pull
out my paper i'm going to try to think this through and and now i'll stop talking i'll let you just
think
certainly don't feel rushed by the way even if there are some answers rolling in right now
that is by no means any indication that you should have finished or anything like that
so
so interestingly we do have a strong lead but it's not at all a strong second place so it seems like
the way that the assuming that the lead is correct the way that the errors have happened
is not in a consistent way which is interesting and that'll be
that'll be fun to dissect once we reveal what the answers are
so let's um let me check if there's any new questions that have rolled in
no huh which suggests to me that the two folks that i have behind the scenes who are supposed
to feed me questions are probably desperately wrangling with uh something item pool related
those of you who have already submitted an answer or who think you already know the answer by the
way i want you to take a moment to seriously guess what you think the second most common
answer is going to be and where exactly the misconception could have taken place
or to double check your work you very well might be one of those sitting in the um the
misconception territory which you know it's uh it's a lot to work out there's
a lot of different failure points along the way
all right so with that i'm going to go ahead and lock in the answers and if you wanted to still
work it through even if the answer isn't going to be recorded that's totally fine we're going to
walk through it in a moment but i'm going to lock them in just so that we can see um what the
correct answer turns out to be and the correct answer is d which it looks like a majority of
you got so that's awesome um the second most common was c which really only differs by a minus
sign and i can i can actually guess why that's true already so that's that's interesting um
after that is b where there's a square root of three instead of a square root of two okay so we
have we actually have a pretty good distribution on this i think that this shows that this is not
at all an obvious question and can take um take a little bit of noodling to figure out so if i saw
this on a test okay let's say that someone threw like a high school math test at me right now and
it said cosine of 75 you know i would know that in principle i'm supposed to be thinking of this
as uh in terms of friendlier angles i know that 45 degrees is a friendly angle for trigonometry
and i know that 30 degrees is what i don't have memorized though are the addition formulas uh i
learned them once slipped out of my head definitely don't have them memorized but i do know how to
re-derive them on the fly basically the idea is that we take the complex number associated with
the 45 degree rotation which is going to be cosine of 45 degrees plus i times the sine of 45 degrees
i take that complex number and i'm going to rotate the complex number corresponding to a 30 degree
rotation so i might even just pull up yet another unit circle here and say the one that sits 30
degrees away i want to multiply it by this number well what is that number its x component is the
cosine of that so the real component is the cosine of 30 degrees and then the imaginary component
okay the vertical component here is the sine of 30 degrees which looks like it's you know
the smaller leg of a 30 60 90 triangle which is going to be one half but we'll work out the numbers
in just a moment sine of 30 degrees times i and by the magic of complex multiplication which i
hope isn't magical based on what we walked through a little bit earlier the effect that this will have
is to rotate by one and then rotate by the other so what are these values cosine of 45 degrees
is the square root of 2 divided by 2 sine of 45 degrees is the square root of 2 divided by 2 and
if you want to if you don't remember that and you want to work it out the way to think about it is
that a 45 degree angle is going to create an isosceles right triangle so if we don't know what
this side length is we at least know that it's the same as the other side length so if the
hypotenuse is one we know that x squared plus x squared is supposed to equal one that's the
pythagorean theorem that tells us that 2x squared equals one so x squared is the square root of one
half and then that's actually the same as writing the square root of 2 divided by 2
you could also write it as 1 divided by the square root of 2 if you want but these are these
are equivalent forms so if you forget you just draw the triangle it's no big deal cosine of 30
degrees well if we have our 30 60 90 triangle the long side of that from everything we talked through
in the last lecture is square root of 3 over 2 square root of 3 over 2 and then the sine of 30
degrees is one half and now we just carry out the complex product it's not exactly a fun prospect
maybe but it's really just four operations so it's not going to be too bad the real part is going to
be our cosine times our cosine okay so that's going to end up being our square root of 2 over 2
multiplied by square root of 3 over 2 okay i'm also going to package in when we multiply both
imaginary parts okay i guess i was a little inconsistent i wrote i times sine and then sine
times i but it's the same thing so i'm going to include that square root of 2 over 2 multiplied
by the one half but because each of them has an i we also multiply it by i squared which by
definition is negative 1 so we get this negative sign in here and that's going to be the real part
okay which is actually all we need we just need the real part and that gives us the uh that gives
us the x coordinate of the where did i drop before here we go if we rotate 45 degrees then we rotate
another 30 the x component of that the real part is going to be the final answer so we'll do the
sine part in a moment too when we make it more general but just for the sake of answering the
question this ends up being root 2 times root 3 which is root 6 divided by 2 times 2 so root 6
over 4 minus and that minus sign came about because of the i squared minus square root of 2
over 4 okay so all in all that ends up being root 6 minus root 2 divided by 4 and if we pull up the
question um i think it's very interesting that the second most common uh answer the the most common
mistake you might say is only different because of that plus sign and if we look at the math where
that came from as it happens is the idea that this was a minus sign which came about from the
idea that there was an i sitting in front of each sign so the most common misconception came from
maybe forgetting to apply the fact that i squared is equal to negative 1 at least if you were going
about it using complex numbers which from the whole context of the lecture of course we want to
so this actually corresponds to a much more general formula and i think it's edifying to
write out that general formula for ourselves because anytime that i've forgotten what the
sum of two angles in trigonometry should be it's totally okay because you can re-derive it
relatively quickly if you're comfortable with complex multiplication and the more math that
you do because it shows up all over the place you actually get very comfortable with complex
multiplication even if you like me become very rusty on things like trigonometric identities
but with that comfort you can very quickly re-derive what the angles should be or what the
some identities should be sine of beta writing and talking at the same time so remember the way
to think about this is that this first number is what we get by finding a complex number that's
basically just rotating alpha around the unit circle if you rotate an angle of alpha around
that's what this first number is this second number tells us what you would get if you rotate
an angle beta around so let's say there's some other angle which i might write down here the
whole angle from the x-axis would be how should i write it i'll write it as beta that doesn't
really connote that it's the full angle just bring i'll just i'll just do it as a separate
a separate friend over here
beta so i think like when i when i see these terms cosine alpha plus i sine alpha i think in
my head very visually of a point on the unit circle in the complex plane similarly i think
of a point on the unit circle in the complex plane and i know that multiplying them together
means that the action of one of them is rotating the other so the final result we know is going to
be the point that sits alpha plus beta around alpha plus beta plus i times the sine of alpha
plus beta wonderful but on the other hand if you go through the mechanistic foil operation
you will get an alternate expression for the answer and by having an alternate expression
you have an identity which i think is pretty cool it's a sign that when you have a non-obvious
relationship like the algebra of complex multiplication and the geometry of complex
multiplication you can leverage that non-obvious relationship to get yourself real identities okay
so how does this work the real part is going to consist of multiplying those cosines so we have
cosine alpha times cosine of beta and then it also consists of the two imaginary parts multiplied
together because that i squared becomes real i times sine i'd say i won't write anything here
it'll be that sine of alpha and then the sine of beta
and because we have an i squared we can consider that a negative one okay so it's cosine alpha
cosine beta minus i sort of accidentally started writing a plus so we're just going to live with
that minus sine of alpha plus sine of beta sine of alpha times sine of beta okay obviously it's
a lot of algebra but it is satisfying the idea that you don't need to memorize this and again
do this regularly when you do complex multiplication regularly you can kind of see this pop out where
you're like oh yeah it's the the real the two real parts minus the two imaginary parts that as a
pattern is something you start to recognize and that when you want the imaginary part of the
product that you take the other two like in this case it's going to be i times sine times cosine
so the sine of alpha times the cosine of beta plus the cosine of alpha times the sine of
beta the cosine of alpha times the sine of beta long complicated formula all of that times i
this long complicated formula is giving you the angle and some identities and sometimes you can
write this out in a much more compact form this this is not a commonly used notation and i'll
explain why in a moment but sometimes uh cosine plus i sine of something comes about commonly
enough it has this meaning on the unit circle that it's written as c i s okay in this case
c is of alpha so everything that we just wrote down could be written more compactly as c is of
alpha times c is of beta is equal to c is of alpha plus beta okay this is communicating the very
non-trivial fact that complex multiplication lets us you know lets us work out rotations in the way
that we want to again that's not standard notation and i'll explain why there's a much more standard
way to write these but it's weird so i don't want to just kind of throw it down there but before we
do that i want to illustrate how you can do a little bit of magic when you have this proper
intuition for complex numbers and and how they multiply so let me pull up our quiz again and
let's move on to another question and this question asks which of the following values of z
satisfies z squared equals i okay so there's two ways that you can think about this i'll
talk about them both and i'm just going to give you a moment to kind of think this one through
so
and and while you work that out let me go ahead and take a question from the audience
achmed osama asks what is an application that is impossible to achieve without complex numbers
convince me that they are needed they're fun to work with maybe but they made things easier
but can we do without them um i would say i believe yeah you can absolutely work without them
because you can basically use rotation matrices in place of complex numbers so what's nice about
complex numbers is that when you're adding things and when you're multiplying things you're dealing
with the same type they're both complex numbers but if you wanted to describe this all with
matrices and vectors and such when you're adding stuff you'd be adding vectors but then when you
want to do rotation type actions and stretching type actions you'd be transferring to instead
dealing with matrices so that's fine you just have to keep that jumbled and use them differently
i'd be willing to bet pretty much anything you can do with complex numbers you could do there
it'll become much less elegant and i guess one of the one of the main things that would be
just really awkward is the fundamental theorem of algebra which we'll talk about in a moment but it
basically says anytime you have a polynomial of degree n so the highest term you see is something
like x to the n among the complex numbers it has n different solutions so that's very elegant it's
very nice to work with it definitely makes the lives easier of anyone who's working with
things where polynomials come about to include matrices and things like i don't want to like
throw around terminology but when you're computing eigenvalues and such you find yourself with
polynomials often of high degree and it's nice to have solutions to them i can conceive of
constructing some kind of way to work with the numbers where you have like solutions to all of
these where the solutions are expressed in terms of vectors and matrices and so maybe the strict
answer to your question is you could do without them you definitely would not want to life for
mathematicians and quantum physicists and really anyone who works with like linear algebra and
polynomials would just become incredibly awkward so in some very real sense they are a natural
construct so much so that even if you could do without them conceivably you never would want to
it would really make things quite the pain so coming back to our quiz here it looks like again
we've got a lot of strong consensus which is good and let me go ahead and create this
all right so the correct answer is a okay it's root two over two plus root two over two i it
looks like the majority of you got that and okay so very interesting is that the second most common
answer was d that no solution exists without extending beyond the complex numbers because
the question we're asking in this context is basically to take a square root of i so if you
think of oh i is defined to be the square root of negative one i think a common question is to say
you know how deep does this rabbit hole go okay if we had to make up an answer to the question
square root of negative one do we have to make up another one for the square root of i and the
square root of that and just kind of keep extending and extending and it's interesting and surprising
that once you have i you have pretty much everything else that you want at least when it
comes to solving anything that looks like a polynomial okay so the answer here there's two
ways to think about it one of them is the brute force way and then one of them is the more elegant
way so the brute force way looks like this you're reading through the multiple choices and you just
kind of try them out and in this case when you try out square root of two over two plus square root of
two over two times i and you square it so we're going to multiply it by itself i'm going to
actually do this just to illustrate that it's possible and that it's not super fun taking root
two times root two for that first real part is going to give us two divided by two times two so
two over four the real part will also include the products of the imaginary parts because of that i
squared so we're going to have root two over two times root two over two which like we just saw
oh excuse me that was supposed to be two over four you can tell them a little all over the place
today which you know just because sometimes complex numbers get me excited root over two
times root two over two is going to be another two over four but this time it's times i times i
so we're going to have a negative in there okay that's going to be the full real part
and then the imaginary part is going to come from the cross terms something where there was only one
i included so two over two i times root two over two it's the same product we're doing over and
over it's always two over four and then we're going to add root two over two times root two
over two i so we're going to add the same thing and i'm not writing the i's here because i'm going
to factor it out okay so the real part involves subtracting these the imaginary part involves
adding them and indeed when we subtract them that real part is zero and when we add them that
imaginary part is one so we just get zero plus i or i and okay it works but imagine that you
looked at this question and it wasn't multiple choice right someone asks you to find a square
root of i if if the only option you have is this terrible brute forcing it seems like a very
painful process right to try every number try squaring it if this is what you have to do but in
an insane trial and error it would seem like magic if someone just pulled that answer out of a hat
but if you're thinking about it geometrically it's actually a pretty straightforward question
to ask because what you're saying is we want a number such that z squared is sitting where i
is right it's sitting one unit above well if we know that rotation corresponds to complex
multiplication right that means what we want is a number that rotates by 45 degrees
because if you have a number that rotates by 45 degrees then when you multiply by it twice that's
the same as rotating 90 degrees so it gets you up to i all right well what number is that we
could think of it in terms of sines and cosines if we want you know this is going to be cosine
of 45 degrees this vertical part is going to be the sine of 45 degrees and it's root 2 over 2 for
each of them this is something we were working out just by looking at the uh the isosceles right
triangle each one of these is equal to root 2 over 2 so that's very fun simply by thinking of
the geometry you could pull out of your hat the fact that the square root of i or i should say
a square root of i is root 2 over 2 plus root 2 over 2 i another answer would have been what
happens when you rotate not 45 degrees but if you were to rotate 40 45 plus another 180 degrees
okay so 45 plus 180 actually gets us 225 degrees all the way around that's another number where if
you multiply by it twice it'll have the effect of rotating you a grand total of 360 plus 90 degrees
it'll kind of rotate you all the way around and then an extra 90 so in the same way that most
positive numbers have two square roots you know square root of 25 is 5 but it's also negative 5
and in the same way that even negative numbers like negative 1 has two square roots not only is
it i but negative i also satisfies this property that when you square it you get negative 1 even i
itself has two square roots and in general everything except for 0 has two square roots
0 you might consider to have like a double root but again that's sort of a story for another time
so that's pretty magical and now let me show you another bit of magic okay something where again
you can come at a question that seems like it's going to involve just insane trial and error but
if you're thinking about the geometry of it you're able to come to a pretty uh a pretty meaningful
answer relatively quickly all right what's our question here the equation x cubed equals 1 has
one real number solution x equals 1 makes sense you cube 1 you get 1 among the complex numbers
there are two more solutions which of the following is one of them okay so this time
it's actually asking us to cube uh some kind of complex number or to verify that when you cube it
you're going to get one i'll give you some some time to sort of think about that
and in the meantime let me take a sip of water and then take the question from the audience
so what do we have you showed that in order to find the cosine of a sum of two angles you can
multiply two complex numbers does that mean that if i need the cosine of a subtraction of two
angles i need to divide two complex numbers wonderful question yes yes it does mean that
and dividing by a complex number is actually the same as multiplying by one in the same way that
dividing by two is the same as multiplying by one half you basically say two has the action
of stretching the number line by two um one half as a multiplier has the action of squishing
everything down by a factor of two that's kind of the inverse action when it comes to complex
numbers to divide by it you ask what's the inverse action so an example here might be let's say
let's pull up something here let's say i wanted to rotate uh you know negative alpha that's what
i want to do so i'm going to do like cosine of beta minus alpha or something like that that number
could be considered the inverse the multiplicative inverse of what you get by rotating alpha the
other way so up here we have i'm just going to write it as c is for cosine plus i times the sign
of alpha the inverse number over here is c is of negative alpha right that number is one divided
by this i could even write it out over here to say c is the number that's alpha the way along
a unit circle is equal to one divided by c is of negative alpha and vice versa if i took one
divided by c is of alpha this is equal to c is of negative alpha now everyone who knows euler's
formula is kind of screaming at me that there's an easy way to see this in terms of exponentials
which is of course where we're getting with this but because it's weird this connection between
complex numbers and exponentials i don't want to just throw that down right away i do want to
emphasize that this is this should all make sense before anything like euler's formula enters the
picture if you think of c is as being what basically a function to ask where do you end up if you walk
alpha units around the unit circle in the complex plane it's the upper it's the number that you can
use for for rotating things by alpha degrees so dividing by it will also get you rotating the
other way but the the overall answer there is that division is the same as multiplication so that's
absolutely the right instinct you can derive for yourself the angle what would you call them the
trigonometric difference formulas if you wanted to great so i think that's probably enough time
if we punch back to our quiz and let's tone down the pause and ponder music here it seems like
answers have sort of stopped rolling in so this is as good a time as any to grade things so the
correct answer here of the four options that we were given ends up being drum roll please negative
one half plus the root three over two times i now i just want you to imagine for a moment that
if you didn't know any of the geometry of complex numbers someone asks you this question and if you
were able to spit it back decently quickly it makes you look like a machine right because you
would imagine that the only way to answer this is to look at each number and then cube it that you
have to go through and do the whole first inside outside last but twice because you're cubing it
for each one of those and then deduce that answer b turns out to have this property that we want
geometrically there's a very nice way to see it so let's go ahead and pull it up
what we want is an action so that when you do it three times you end up back at the uh back at one
basically i want if i were to multiply by this number three times i end up back at one
let me clear for myself a nice new piece of paper here
so just remind ourselves what we're looking for which is x cubed is equal to one okay so one such
action is the do nothing action right if you multiply by one which does nothing yeah do that
three times you end up back at one that is our real solution the other ones would be to rotate
a third of the way around the circle okay to rotate 120 degrees or you could rotate 120 degrees
the other way which is equivalent to thinking of rotating 240 degrees around those are other
actions where if you do them three times it's the same as doing nothing if i rotate 120 degrees
then do that three times i cube it that's the same as doing nothing that's how you can read
this equation which i think is very nice and elegant rather than just trying to plug in
numbers and see what comes out so using the trig that we learned about last time this again comes
from a 30 60 90 triangle you can see that the real part is negative one half and then the
imaginary part is the square root of three over two so even before working it out i can know with
confidence that if i were to go through the painstaking process of taking negative one half
plus the square root of three over two and cubing that i'm going to get back one i don't have to go
through that process to know that that's going to happen which is pretty magical this also answers
for us a mystery that we had in the last lecture if you guys remember what we did is we pulled up
desmos so let's go on back let's go on over to chrome let's open up a desmos tab and let's get
rid of whatever else was going on in here and what we played with was the idea that if you take a
cosine graph and then if you square it the shapes look remarkably similar you have this bizarre
relationship where squaring cosine looks like squishing it and more specifically we were able
to play around and say if you double the frequency of that cosine wave and then you manipulate it in
some other ways we're going to shift it up and then we divide it by two this is all something we
did last time we got an identity between them but this raised an interesting question what on earth
does cosine of 2x have to do with cosine of x squared well now with complex numbers we can
actually know the answer we can work this out we know that if you rotate around by theta degrees
okay if we call that number z then when we rotate around another theta degrees this new number is z
squared right and z is what i was calling c is of theta which we could expand out as saying cosine
of theta plus i sine of theta and we can work out that square nearly algebraically
we take cosine of theta plus i sine of theta
the real part of that is going to come from two products of the real part so it's going to be
cosine squared of theta but then also two parts of the imaginary and because of that i it becomes
negative one so we'll end up with negative sine squared of theta and then the imaginary part is
going to come from you know i might as well just write this out in full cosine theta plus i sine
i realize i'm kind of running against the edge which is why i was hesitant to do this
but basically that cosine squared comes from taking the cosine times the cosine the negative
sine squared comes from taking i sine times negative i sine our remaining terms are going
to be that cosine plus i sine so cosine theta times sine of theta
and then there's going to be an i i'll just write it out times i and then we get exactly the same
thing sine of theta times cosine of theta times i so sine of theta times cosine of theta
times i which we could factor out this whole last part ends up just being two times the cosine of
theta times the sine of theta right all of that times i so what we've done here is basically said
there's two ways to think about cosine theta plus i sine theta squared one of them is oh of course
it doubles the angle right so that's going to be cosine of two theta on the other hand algebraically
it's equal to deep breath cosine squared theta minus sine squared theta plus two cosine theta
sine theta i now that might seem like a big pain but the big pain is showing us an identity it's
showing us the double angle identity so what we found here just to summarize on the real part
is that the cosine of two theta the real part of what happens when we rotate by that twice
when we rotate by that twice is equal to cosine squared of theta minus sine squared of theta
now from another trig identity that we were working with last time sine squared of theta
is actually the same as taking one minus cosine squared this was the alternate way of expressing
the pythagorean theorem so we can get everything written in terms of cosines and what we have
is now two times cosine pardon the messiness of the handwriting here by the way two times cosine
of theta all minus one that is evidently equal to the cosine of two theta and we could rearrange
that further and see what we were playing around with in desmos that this cosine of 2x expression
over here this cosine of 2x expression corresponds with squaring the cosine this was a reflection of
the fact that cosine relates to complex numbers which i think is pretty cool okay and as the very
last thing that i want to mention i want to talk about why we didn't um why nobody really uses this
cis notation right i was saying that cis of alpha is not really standard notation when we're talking
about rotating alpha around the unit circle as a reminder this was my shorthand for cosine plus
i sine the reason is because what you're always going to see instead through electrical
engineering through quantum mechanics through math through all sorts of things is instead the
way that this is written is actually before i show you how it's written no no i'll just i'll
just show you how it's written it's it's it's weird and we're going to talk about it at length
next time but you imagine that you're raising something to a power okay e to the i times alpha
um now this obviously makes a lot of people very uncomfortable first of all if you don't know about
e what is e and then secondly what on earth does it mean to raise something to an imaginary power
so that is a full lecture's worth of material i do want to talk about it next time
but just to to give an indication of why this might not be a totally crazy thing
okay i want you to remember the core property that we wrote down earlier
that when you rotate alpha around the unit circle and then when you rotate another beta
around the unit circle this is the same thing as alpha plus beta which means our cis function
has this kind of interesting property that adding the inputs is the same as multiplying the outputs
so with that i want to ask one final quiz question to try to relate this to other functions that you
might be familiar with and at this point it might be halfway obvious where we're going with this
but as the very final question to cue you up for where we're going to go next time
and maybe appreciate the relationship at play here and why it's not that crazy
i want you to answer which of the following functions satisfies f of a plus b is equal to f
of a times f of b okay
so i'm being told by the way that um when i advance the questions too quickly it kind of
reveals the answer of the next one which happened all throughout last lecture and you guys certainly
told me about it again this is one of those things where like this is what happens with live
production we thought we had fixed that um usually you know this is a very weird process for me
because usually when i make videos you catch some kind of error so you edit out the error then you
put out the video this is an experience for me is much more like all right world here it is raw
here are the errors as they come i hope you enjoy watching them happen because there's no editing
it does not get clipped out this is math presentation raw all right so as we do this
it looks like a pretty pretty strong consensus i'll give you a little bit more time to submit
the answers
all right and with that let's go ahead and take a look so the question is what function has this
property where adding the inputs looks like multiplying by the outputs so uh 2700 of you
correctly answered that two to the x an exponential function behaves this way looks like the most
common second answer was a that logarithms which makes sense there's an identity in logarithms that
looks very similar it's basically the opposite so if we were to you know write this out i might say
two to the a times two to the b is equal to two to the a plus b and when we're thinking in terms
of repeated multiplication this makes a lot of sense because one of these is saying multiply in
a copies of two then multiply in b copies of two and the result should be well a plus b copies of
two the rule with logarithms is exactly the opposite and it's because logarithms are the
inverse of multiplication on that front it looks like taking the log of a plus b ends up being the
log of a sorry the log of a times b multiply log of a plus log of b logarithms is another thing
i think we're going to talk about in a later lecture of this series so if you don't know about
them don't worry but to those of you who answered that totally understandable it's because it's a
very similar property but it's just getting mixed up whether the outputs are being added or the
inputs are now what you'll notice is how strange this factor that comes about because two to the
x is defined as repeated multiplication looks very similar to the rule that we found for complex
numbers that sit on the unit circle that multiplying the outputs is the same as adding
the inputs and that should be very suggestive that there might be some kind of unifying theory
between them which of course there is it has everything to do with why we write things as
e to the i theta which i actually think is kind of a bad convention the good thing about it is that
it does make it pretty obvious when you take e to the i theta times e to the i beta sorry e to the i
alpha that you're allowed to just add them it really highlights that fact which otherwise you
kind of have to think through but maybe that's a good thing that you kind of have to think it
through and you're not just blindly applying rules but i'm going to talk all about that next time
we're going to dig deep into uh euler's formula a way that you can try to understand what is this
really saying like computationally it's not talking about repeated multiplication so what
could you do if you are on a desert island with a bunch of paper to just work out by hand the fact
that this is a reasonable expression all of that is to come next time so thank you for joining
apologies for being mildly scattered throughout