You've probably heard of the Heisenberg uncertainty principle from quantum mechanics,
that the more you know about a particle's position, the less certain you can be of its
momentum and vice versa.
Michael here is for you to come away from this video feeling like this is utterly reasonable.
It'll take some time, but I think you'll agree that digging deep is well worth it.
You see, the uncertainty principle is actually one specific example of a much more general
trade-off that shows up in a lot of everyday totally non-quantum circumstances involving
waves.
The plan here is to see what this means in the context of sound waves, which should feel
reasonable, and then Doppler radar, which should again feel reasonable and a little
bit closer to the quantum case, and then for particles, which if you're willing to accept
one or two premises of quantum mechanics, hopefully feels just as reasonable as the
first two.
The core idea here has to do with the interplay between frequency and duration, and I bet
you already have an intuitive idea of this principle before we even get into the math
or the quantum.
If you were to pull up behind a car at a red light, and your turn signals were flashing
together for a few seconds, you might kind of think they have the same frequency, but
at that point for all you know they could fall out of sync as more time passes, revealing
that they actually had different frequencies.
So an observation over a short period of time gave you low confidence over what their frequencies
are.
But, if you were to set it at that red light for a full minute, and the signals continued
to click in sync, you would be a lot more confident that the frequencies are actually
the same.
So that certainty about the frequency information required an observation spread out over time.
And this trade-off right here, between how short your observation can be and how confident
you can feel about the frequency, is an example of the general uncertainty principle.
Similarly, think of a musical note.
The shorter it lasts in time, the less certain you can be about what its exact frequency
is.
In the extreme, I could ask you what the pitch of a clap or shockwave is, and even someone
with perfect pitch would be unable to answer.
And on the flip side, a more definite frequency requires a longer duration signal.
Or rather than talking about definiteness or certainty, it would be a little more accurate
here to say that the short signal correlates highly with a wider range of frequency, and
that the signal correlating strongly with only a narrow range of frequencies must last
for a longer time.
Here, that's the kind of phrase that's made a little clearer when we bring in the
actual math, so let's turn now to talking about the Fourier transform, which is the
relevant construct for analyzing frequencies.
The last video I put out was a visual intuition for this transform, and yes, it would be helpful
if you've seen it, but I'll give a quick recap here to remind ourselves how it went.
Let's say you have a signal, and it plays 5 beats per second over the course of 2 seconds.
The Fourier transform gives a way to view any signal not in terms of the intensity at
each point in time, but instead in terms of the strength of various frequencies within
it.
The main idea was to take this signal and kind of wind it around a circle, as in, imagine
some rotating vector whose length is determined by the height of the graph at each point in
time.
Right now, this little vector is rotating at 0.3 cycles per second, that's the frequency
with which we're winding the graph around the circle.
And for most frequencies, the signal is kind of just averaged out over the circle.
This was the fun part of last video, don't you think?
Just seeing the different patterns that come up as you wind a pure cosine around a circle
like this.
But the key point is what happens when that winding frequency matches the signal frequency,
in this case 5 cycles per second.
As our little vector is rotating around and it draws, all of the peaks line up on one
side and all of the valleys on another side, so the whole weight of the graph is kind of
off-center, so to speak.
The idea behind the Fourier transform is that if you follow the center of mass of the wound-up
graph with frequency f, the position of that center of mass encodes the strength of that
frequency in the original signal.
The distance between that center of mass and the origin captures the strength of that frequency.
And this is something I didn't really talk about in the main video, but the angle of
that center of mass off the horizontal corresponds to the phase of the given frequency.
One way to think of this whole winding mechanism is that it's a way to measure how well your
signal correlates with a given pure frequency.
So remember, when we say the Fourier transform, we're referring to this new function whose
input is that winding frequency, and whose output is the center of mass, thought of as
a complex number.
Or more technically, it's a certain multiple of that center of mass, but whatever, the
overall shape remains the same.
And the graph I'm drawing is just going to be the x-coordinate of that center of mass,
the real part of its output.
If you wanted, you could also plot the distance between the center of mass and the origin,
and maybe that better conveys how strongly each possible frequency correlates with a
signal.
The downside is that you lose some of the nice linearity properties I talked about last
video.
Anyway, point is, this spike above the winding frequency of 5 is the Fourier transform's
way of telling us that the dominant frequency of the signal is 5 beats per second.
And equally importantly, the fact that it's a little bit spread out around that 5 is an
indication that pure sine waves near 5 beats per second also correlate pretty well with
the signal.
And that last idea is key for the uncertainty principle.
What I want you to do is think about how this spread changes as the signal persists longer
or shorter over time.
You've already seen this at an intuitive level, all we're doing right now is just
illustrating it in the language of Fourier transforms.
If the signal persists over a long period of time, then when the winding frequency is
even slightly different from 5, the signal goes on long enough to wrap itself around
the circle and balance out.
So looking at the Fourier plot over here, that corresponds to a super sharp drop-off
in the magnitude of the transform as your frequency shifts away from that 5 beats per
second.
On the other hand, if your signal was localized to a short period of time, then as you adjust
the frequency away from 5 beats per second, the signal doesn't really have as much time
to balance itself out around the circle.
You have to change the winding frequency to be meaningfully different from 5 before that
signal starts to balance out again.
Over on the frequency plot, that corresponds to a much broader peak around the 5 beats
per second.
And that's the uncertainty principle, just phrased a little bit more mathematically.
A signal concentrated in time must have a spread out Fourier transform, meaning it correlates
with a wide range of frequencies, and a signal with a concentrated Fourier transform has
to be spread out in time.
And one other place where this comes up in a really tangible way is Doppler radar.
So with radar, the idea is you send out some radio wave pulse, and the pulse might reflect
off of objects, and the time it takes for this echo signal to return to you lets you
deduce how far away those objects are.
And you can actually take this one step further and make deductions about the velocities of
those objects using the Doppler effect.
Think about sending out a pulse with some frequency.
If this gets reflected off an object moving towards you, then the beats of that wave get
kind of smushed together, so the echo you hear back is going to be a slightly higher
frequency.
Fourier transforms give a neat way to view this.
The Fourier transform of your original signal tells you the frequencies that go into it,
and for simplicity, let's think of that as being dominated by a single pure frequency,
though as you know if it's a short pulse that means our Fourier transform has to be
spread out a little bit.
And now think about the Doppler shift at echo.
By coming back at a higher frequency, it means that the Fourier transform will just look
like a similar plot shifted up a bit.
Moreover, if you look at the size of that shift, you can deduce how quickly the object
was moving.
By the way, there is an important technical point that I'm choosing to gloss over here,
and I've outlined it a little more in the video description.
What follows is meant to be a distilled, if somewhat oversimplified description of the
Fourier tradeoff in this setup.
The salient fact is that time and frequency of that echo signal correspond respectively
to the position and velocity of the object being measured, which is what makes this example
much more closely analogous to the quantum mechanical Heisenberg uncertainty principle.
You see, there is a very real way in which a radar operator faces a dilemma, where the
more certain you can be about the positions of things, the less certain you are about
their velocities.
Here imagine sending out a pulse that persists over a long period of time.
Then that means the echo from some object is also spread out over time.
And on its own that might not seem like an issue.
In practice, there are all sorts of different objects in the field, so these echoes are
all going to start to get overlapped with each other.
Combine that with other noise and imperfections, and this can make the locations of multiple
objects extremely ambiguous.
Instead, a more precise understanding of how far away all these things are would require
having a very quick little pulse confined to a small amount of time.
But think about the frequency representations of such a short echo.
As you saw with the sound example, the Fourier transform of a quick pulse is necessarily
more spread out.
So for many objects with various velocities, that would mean that the Doppler shifted echoes,
despite having been nicely separated in time, are more likely to overlap in frequency space.
So since what you're looking at is the sum of all of these, it can be really ambiguous
how you break it down.
If you wanted a nice clean sharp view of the velocities, you would need to have an echo
that only occupies a very small amount of frequency space.
But for a signal to be concentrated in frequency space, it necessarily has to be spread out
in time.
This is the Fourier tradeoff, you cannot have crisp delineation for both.
And this brings us to the quantum case.
Do you know who else spent some time immersed in the pragmatic world of radio wave transmissions?
A young, otherwise philosophically inclined history major in WWI France, Louis de Broglie.
And this was a strangely fitting post, given his predispositions to philosophizing about
the nature of waves, because after the war, as de Broglie switched from the humanities
to physics, in his 1924 PhD thesis, he proposed that all matter has wave-like properties.
And more than that, he concluded that the momentum of any moving particle is proportional
to the spatial frequency of that wave, how many times that wave cycles per unit distance.
Okay, now that's the kind of phrase that can easily fly into one ear and out the other.
Because as soon as you say matter is a wave, it's easy to throw up your hands and say
physics is just weird.
But really, think about this.
Even if you're willing to grant that particles behave like waves, in some way, whatever that
means, why on earth should the momentum of those particles, the thing we classically
think of as mass times velocity, have anything to do with the spatial frequency of that wave?
Now, being more of a math than a physics guy, I asked a number of people with deeper backgrounds
in physics about helpful intuitions here, and one thing that became clear is that there
is a surprising variety of viewpoints.
Now personally, one thing I found to be interesting was just going back to the source and seeing
how de Broglie framed things in his seminal paper on the topic.
You see, there is a sense in which it's not all that different from the Doppler effect,
where relative movement corresponds to shifts in frequency.
It has a slightly different flavor, since we're not talking about frequency over time,
instead we're talking about frequency over space, and special relativity is going to
come into play.
But I still think it's an interesting analogy.
In his thesis, de Broglie lays out what is, in his own words, a crude comparison for the
kind of wave phenomenon he has in mind.
Imagine many weights hanging from springs, with all of these weights oscillating up and
down in sync, and with most of the mass concentrated towards a single point.
The energy of these oscillating weights is meant to be a metaphor for the energy of a
particle, specifically the E equals mc squared style energy residing in its mass, and de
Broglie emphasized how the conception he had in mind involves the particle being dispersed
across all of space.
The whole premise he was exploring here is that the energy of a particle might have to
do with something that oscillates over time, since this was known to be the case for photons,
and these oscillating weights are meant to be a metaphor for whatever that something
might be.
With Einstein's relatively new theory of relativity in mind, he pointed out that if
you view this whole setup while moving relative to it, all of the weights are going to appear
to fall out of phase.
That's not obvious, and I'm certainly exaggerating the effect in this animation.
It has to do with a core fact from special relativity, that what you consider to be simultaneous
events in one reference frame may not be simultaneous in a different reference frame.
So even though from one point of view, you might see two of these weights as reaching
their peaks and valleys at the same instant, from a different moving point of view, those
events might actually be happening at different times.
Using this more fully requires some knowledge of special relativity, so we'll all just
have to wait for Henry Reich's series on that topic to come out.
Right here our only goal is to get an inkling for why momentum, that thing we usually think
of as mass times velocity, should have anything to do with spatial frequency.
And the basic line of reasoning here is if mass is the same as energy, via E equals mc
squared, and if that energy was carried as some kind of oscillating phenomenon, similar
to how it is for photons, then this sort of relativistic Doppler effect means changes
to how that mass moves corresponds to changes in the spatial frequency.
So what does our general Fourier tradeoff tell us in this case?
Well if a particle is described as a little wave packet over space, then the Fourier transform,
where we're thinking of this as a function over space, not over time, tells us how much
various pure frequencies correspond with this top wave.
So if the momentum is the spatial frequency, up to a constant multiple, then the momentum
is also a kind of wave, namely some multiple of the Fourier transform of the original wave.
So if that original wave was very concentrated around a single point, as we have seen multiple
times now, that means its Fourier transform must necessarily be more spread out, hence
the wave describing its momentum must be more spread out, and vice versa.
Notice that unlike the Doppler radar case, where the ambiguity arose because waves were
being used to measure an object with a definite distance and speed, what we're saying here
is that the particle is the wave.
So the spread out over space and over momentum is not some artifact of imperfect measurement
techniques, it's a spread fundamental to what the particle is, analogous to how a musical
note being spread out over time is fundamental to what it even means to be a musical note.
One pet peeve I have in mainstream references to quantum is that they often treat Heisenberg's
uncertainty principle as some fundamental example of things being unknowable in the
quantum realm, as if it is a core nugget of the universe's indeterminacy.
But really, it's just a tradeoff between how concentrated a wave and its frequency
representation can be applied to the premise that matter is some kind of wave, and hence
spread out.
All of the stuff about randomness and unknowability is still there, but it comes one level deeper
in the way these waves have come to be interpreted.
When you measure these particles, say trying to detect if it's in a given region, whether
or not you find it there appears to be probabilistic, where the probability of finding it is proportional
to the strength of the wave in that region.
So when one of these waves is concentrated near a point, what that actually means is
that we have a higher probability of finding it near that point, that we are more certain
of its location.
And just to beat this drum one more time, since that concentration implies a more spread
out Fourier transform, then the wave describing its momentum would also be more spread out,
so you wouldn't be able to find a narrow range of momenta that the particle has a high
probability of occupying.
I quite like how if you look at the German word for this principle, it might be more
directly translated as the unsharpness relation, which I think more faithfully captures the
Fourier tradeoff at play here without imposing on questions of no ability.
When I think of the Heisenberg uncertainty principle, what makes it fascinating is not
so much that it's a statement about randomness.
I mean yes, that randomness is very thought-provoking and contentious and just plain weird, but
to me equally fascinating is that underpinning Heisenberg's conclusion is that position
and momentum have the same relationship as sound and frequency, as if a particle's
momentum is somehow the sheet music describing how it moves through space.