🎵Music🎵
Welcome back to Lockdown Math. Today we are going to be talking about logarithms and kind of a back to the basics sort of lesson.
The intent is for someone who maybe is not familiar with logarithms yet or who has seen some of the rules but has been confused by them.
And as always, to kick things off, I just want to get a sense of where the audience is at right now.
Because I have a couple suspicions, but I think doing a live poll to see where everyone is might be helpful.
So, if you can go to 3b1b.co. Live, which you can find the link in the description, and you can also just follow the link that's up on screen here,
you'll find a poll. And at the moment it asks what best describes your relationship with logarithms?
a. I've never heard about them before or never learned about them before
b. I've learned about them but sometimes get confused by all of the properties
c. I understand them but wouldn't know how to teach them
and d. I understand them well and could comfortably teach them to someone else to make them understand well too.
So, we've got a good split. This is good and interesting.
Like I said, the intent for this is to create a lesson that I can point people to in the future if they're just not comfortable with logarithms
and I want to be able to say, oh, here's a place that you can go for how I think, you know, how I think you could approach it intuitively.
And for those who are in the camps of, let's say, understanding it but not knowing how to teach it,
I think there's an interesting meta question around logarithms.
Because I was scrolling around a couple of teacher forums before doing this particular lecture
and when people ask what is the hardest topic to teach in high school math
in the sense that students seem to have trouble with it the most, logarithms is one of the most commonly indicated answers
which is interesting and I can guess maybe it's because there's a ton of these properties that you end up having to learn
you know, so if we skip ahead of where we're going to go
you've got all these piles of rules that just look like a bunch of algebra that can be hard to remember
and easy to kind of mix things up in your head
and I think when people have, you know, these sort of nightmarish recollections of what high school math was like
and what logarithms did for them, it's often those particular formulas coming to mind
and what I want to do today is try to talk through one, how to think about them
but also just on the meta level of if you're teaching somebody algebra, what are the points worth emphasizing?
What's the way to get it built in their intuitions?
So let's go ahead and see how people are answering on this one
we've got a pretty even split between three possible categories
alright, so the most common viewer right now answered C, that they understand them but they wouldn't know how to teach them
the second most common are those who said they understand them well and they could comfortably teach them
so this is sort of revealing that, okay, the existing audience on the channel at the moment
people who are into math and they're going to be pretty comfortable with logarithms
and then after that, B, people who are confused by some of the properties
and then at the bottom, people who have never learned about them
now, if you watching are one of the people who answered A, that you've never learned about them
or that you're not comfortable, keep in mind this lecture is actually meant for you
so when we're doing some live quizzing and we're going to have an answer on here
and we're going to have people, you know, answering probably pretty quickly, probably correctly
given that as you can see, most of them are coming in comfortable with logarithms
don't let that be intimidating, don't let that be something that indicates you should be answering quickly
or you should necessarily be getting the right answer
alright, so I think the most intuitive way to think about logs
if you're just going to start off, is to say at a very high level
logarithms are something that can take in a power of 10
and it just spits out the number of zeros at the end of the number
it does more than that, as we'll talk about
but just at the very high level, this is getting a sense for what they do
and I think it's pretty important
because what you're saying here is, hey look, as we walk from 1 to 10 to 100 to 1000 to 10,000
each step we're multiplying by 10
the output of the log, the log of that value, just steps up in these increments of 1
so you could think about this as saying, hmm, when I plug in a number to the log
if that number happens to be a power of 10, I'm just counting the number of zeros
what's log of 1000? oh, it has 3 zeros on it
what's log of a million? oh, it has 6 zeros on it
it's the zero counting function
and I think you can get yourself very far in terms of understanding various properties of logarithms
just by thinking in the back of your mind, ok, when I plug in a power of 10
it's a zero counting function, I plug in a billion, how many zeros are at the end of a billion?
and these numbers are all very intuitive to us, we see them in the news
we anchor our intuitions in terms of how many digits does a number have
and logarithms are just capturing that idea
and in fact, logarithms have been of particular interest in the last couple of months
what's kind of interesting is if you look at this Google Trends chart
that's just looking for logarithmic scale, ok?
people searching for the term logarithmic scale, you'll notice there's kind of an ambient interest
sitting around in September of 2019 up to February of 2020
and for some reason, suddenly there's a strong interest in understanding logarithmic scales from the general public
I wonder why that is?
and we see this sitting around early March or so
and of course this is because this is when the corona outbreak was really starting to kick into high gear
and everyone wanted to understand exponential growth
and a common way that exponential growth is plotted is with what's known as a logarithmic scale
so I actually made a video about this and in it I was creating some animations
and wanted to illustrate this idea of exponential growth
and the main idea here, I'll go ahead and skip back to a different animation
is if you're tracking the numbers, in this case this was the number of recorded cases of COVID-19 outside of mainland China
in the months leading up to March
you could just track what the absolute number is
but the pattern that you'll find is that as you go from one day to the next, you tend to be increasing multiplicatively
it's a little bit like earlier, we were seeing the powers of 10 one step to the next, you're multiplying by some amount
the way that the virus was growing was very similar
from one day to the next, you're multiplying not quite by a constant
but in this case, for this sequence of days, it was around 1.2 in that region, you're multiplying by something
so when you're plotting this, it ends up looking like this classic exponential curve that curves upward
and I can sometimes make it hard to see where it's going or what the overall pattern is
so a common trick is to say, instead of looking at this y-axis that increases linearly
as in here I'm going from 5k to 10k, 10k to 15k, 15k to 20k
each step is additive, we're adding 5,000
instead use a y-axis where each step is multiplicative
so you're going from 10 to 100, 100 to 1000, 1000 to 10, 10,000
all of these are increases by multiplying by 10
and what you can say is the y-axis is now plotting not the total number of cases
but the logarithm of the total number of cases
and this actually makes it kind of easier to see on a plot if you wanted to project out what that trend would do
and it's a little bit of a naive model to say, oh it's going to grow exactly exponentially
but in the early phases of something like this, that is what it is
so I kind of fast-forward in the animation I made for that video
and what's interesting is if back then, I think I posted it on March 6th
if you just found a line of best fit and you stretched it out
and you said, when is that line going to cross a million?
which because the y-axis is growing with multiplicative steps
each time that you step up, you're multiplying by 10
so even if it might seem like the 20,000 cases or so that it was back then is very far from a million
you know, when you understand logarithmic scales, it actually didn't seem that far
it was only 30 days away if you naively just drew out that line
and in fact, fast-forward to around April 5th, which is when that would have predicted
we hit a million cases outside China
that's pretty much the day that it happened
I think plus or minus a day, I don't remember exactly
but it was right in that neighborhood because I remember thinking wow
it was kind of a naive model for the video to even use
and it's shocking that it matched so exactly
thankfully, since then, the growth has stopped being exponential
so if you look at it on a logarithmic plot, instead of going up in a straight line, it starts to taper off
but, point being, any time that you're coming across something in nature
or even in a man-made construct
where what's natural to think about are multiplicative increases
logarithms come in to help you
so let's go ahead and think about what these actually are
how are they defined, okay?
and actually there was a question asked on Twitter right before we started
that I think hits this very perfectly
so Max 182 asks us
additions inverse is subtraction
multiplications inverse is division
but I never truly understood if exponentiations inverse was nth-routing or logarithms
if either one could be, you know
if either one could really be called that way, can they?
that is such a fantastic question, Max
and I think it comes down to the fact that with addition and multiplication
you're not, I'll just draw it out for you actually
this is going to be easiest
if we have some kind of exponential relationship
let's say 10 to the power 3 is equal to 1000
there's three different numbers at play here
showing a relationship between the 10, the 3, and the 1000
and aside from writing it with an exponent
there's two other ways we could write that same relationship
we could also say that the cube root of 1000 is equal to 10
this is asking 1000, what number raised to the third is equal to 1000
that's sort of what the cube root is asking
and another way that you could phrase the exact same thing
is to say the log base 10 of 1000 is equal to 3
three different notations, the same exact relationship
a while ago I made this video about an alternate possible notation
that would center in the idea that you think of this relationship
between the three numbers with a triangle
where you'd have our 10 sitting down here
the power sitting at the top, 10 to the third
and the thing they equal sitting to the lower right
and whenever you want to talk about a function
or an operation between two of these numbers
you indicate which one of them you're leaving out
so to write 10 cubed, we would include the 10 on the lower left
the 3 on the upper right, and then we leave out that bottom one
so this is indicating that we're taking a power, 10 cubed
for that radical, what you would say is
we know what's on the bottom right
something to some power equals 1000
we even know what the power is
something cubed equals that 1000
but the thing we don't know is on the bottom left
that is the sense in which radicals are an opposite of exponentiation
where if the thing you don't know
instead of being on that bottom right is on the bottom left
but what logarithms are, it's an inverse in another sense
because what it's saying is, in this triangle relationship
we know the base, it's 10
we know the power that it should be, 1000
but the thing we don't know is what's in that exponent
so to answer your question maybe even more briefly
we could say that 10 to the x, the inverse of that
the inverse is the log base 10
you know, of y, of some other variable
whereas if you're taking x to the 10th, some unknown raised to a power
the inverse of that is going to be the 10th root of some other value
and on the triangle it's basically asking
which of the things do we consider to be a variable
so are you considering that lower right to be a variable quantity
are you considering that top to be a variable quantity
and what is the unknown
but I really liked this idea of making explicit
how we have three totally different notations for the same exact fact
one of them you're using relative positions of the numbers
one of them we introduce a new symbol, this radical
and one of them we introduce a new word, log
so these three syntactically different ways to communicate the same idea seemed wrong
and so I made this video about an alternate possible notation
and while I don't necessarily think that we should teach logarithms with this triangle
because convention is what it is so it's better to start getting people used to the usual expression
what I do like about it and starting off with it
is when you see and think about this triangle
it's really emphasizing that what the log wants to be is that exponent
every time that you see log of some value
you should think in your mind, okay, whatever this number is
it really wants to be an exponent
it wants to be an exponent
and we'll see more of what that means as we go on
okay, so every time you see a log it wants to be an exponent
this value three and more specifically it should be an exponent sitting on top of whatever that base is
now in terms of convention
for the first part of this video I'm just going to be using log without a base written on it
to be the shorthand for log base 10
because log base 10 will be the most intuitive thing out there
you should know that often in math the convention instead is that log without anything might mean log base e
there's also another notation for that ln for natural log
we're going to talk all about the natural log next time
so don't worry too much about that right now
and there's also yet another convention
often if you're in a computer science setting
log without any added sugar to indicate what it is
defaults to meaning log base 2
so this can sometimes be a source of confusion
but it basically depends on what discipline you're in
in math, not moth, math
people really like a base of e, we'll see why next lecture
in, I don't know, I'll say engineering
but really it's anything where you want good intuition with our normal base 10 number system
log means log base 10
and if you're curious, often in computer science settings
log base 2 comes up all the time
so, like I said, in the back of your mind
if you're trying to think of some of these properties
just resting on the idea that log counts the number of zeros at the end of a number
that can get you a really far way
so we're going to start going through a couple of these properties
and I want to do this just with a set of practiced examples
so we'll transition away from the pole
and this time to the first proper question
and the question asks you which of the following is true
a. the log of 1000 times x is equal to 3 times the log of x
and remember we're using the convention that it's base 10 log
b. log of 1000 times x equals log of x cubed
c. log of 1000 times x equals 3 plus the log of x
d. log of 1000 times x equals 3 to the power of log of x
and e. none of the above
and remember like I said earlier
we should fully expect that all of those people at the beginning who said they understand logs well
they're going to be answering immediately, they're going to be answering correctly
but if you're someone who doesn't, don't let that intimidate you
when you're looking at a problem like this one
what I would encourage you to do is just plug in various powers of 10
and think in terms of the idea that the log function counts the number of zeros
so I'll give you a little moment to think about that
so I'll go ahead and grade it
and as always if that's faster than what you're comfortable with
know that it's only because I want to proceed forward with the lesson
so in this case the correct answer comes out to be
log of 1000 times x is the same as taking 3 plus the log of x
and now let's think about that for a moment
and like I said when you're just getting started with them
I think the best thing to do is just be comfortable plugging in various numbers
and the best numbers to plug in are the ones that are already powers of 10
so if you're asking something like log of 1000 times x
well I don't know, let's just plug in something for x
log of 1000 times 100
well we know how many zeros are going to be in the final answer here
well 1000 times 100 is 100,000
we already intuitively have this idea that when we multiply 2 powers of 10
we're just taking the zeros, the 3 zeros from that 1000
the 2 zeros from that 100 and we're putting them next to each other
so it should be 5 total zeros
but if you really reflect not just on how did the number turn out
but why did it turn out that way
it was the 3 zeros from that 1000 plus the 2 zeros from that 100
which we could also write by saying
the number of zeros in 1000 plus the number of zeros in 100
so this idea that a logarithm of the product of two things
is the sum of the logarithms of those two things
in the context of powers of 10
that's just communicating what's already a super intuitive idea for a lot of us
if you take 2 powers of 10 and you multiply them
you just take all of their zeros and kind of cram them onto each other
so the way I've written things out here
it's actually indicative of a slightly more general fact
which is going to be our very first property of logarithms
which is that if we take the log of A times B
it equals the log of A plus the log of B
now any time you see one of these logarithm rules
if you find yourself squinting your eyes
or you're a little bit confused by how to remember it
just plug in examples
I'm being redundant, I'm saying this a lot
but it's because I think it's very easy to forget
once you're swamped in the algebra itself
and you're sitting on some kind of test and it's just got a lot of symbols
to remind yourself you are okay to just plug in some numbers
that's a fine thing to do
and often it's a great way to yield intuition
so in this case, saying log of A times B and breaking it apart
we could just think, oh, that log of 100 times 1000
which is 5, there's 5 zeros in it
breaks up in terms of the number of zeros in each given part
great, wonderful
so carrying that intuition further
let's try another practice problem
and again, if you know it, great, you'll be able to answer it fine
but maybe think, not just what is the answer
but how would I explain this answer to someone
or how would I try to get a student to come to this answer on their own
without me having to tell them what the answer is
so there's two potential audience members
there's those who are interested in the lesson itself
and then those who are interested in the meta lesson
so our question asks, again, which of the following is true?
a. log of x to the n is equal to n times log of x
b. log of x to the n is equal to log of x to the power n
c. log of x to the n is equal to n plus log of x
or d. log of x to the n is equal to log of n times log of x
or none of the above
so again, take a moment to answer
as people do answer, we'll start to see them roll in
and if you are struggling to think of where to even start
just plug in some powers of 10
and see what intuition you might get from it
so
alright, so it looks like just about everybody is landing on one particular answer
hopefully it's the right answer, like I said, all to be expected
so let's go ahead and see if our majority ended up correct
and they did!
so the correct answer here is a, which it looks like 4,000 of you got
congratulations, telling us that log of x to the power n is equal to n times log of x
so, again, let's say that you're trying to teach this to someone
or if you're trying to come to grips with what it means yourself
I think a fine place to start is plugging something in
and in this case, for log of x to the power n
let's just try it with 100 to the power 3
and you could try it with other ones to see if the patterns you're doing actually work
but if you're thinking it through not in terms of simply seeing what the answer is
but trying to think of why the answer turned out that way
sometimes one example will do
because 100 cubed, we can think of that as taking
well, that's 3 copies of 100
I'm taking 3 copies of 100
and when I multiply all that out
and I think of log as counting the number of zeros
we say, oh, it's going to be some number that just has 6 zeros on it
that's what it means to take 100 times 100 times 100
I can just think of grouping all of those zeros together
to get a million
so this number is going to be 6
but if we think actually why was it 6
not just that's the number of zeros inside the million
where that 6 came from
is that we had 3 copies of that 100
and each of those 100 had 2 different zeros
so that way it's a more general way you can think about it
where if instead of taking 100 cubed
we were looking at 1000 cubed
or 1000 to the n
or x to the power n
you can think that it's whatever that value of n was
the number of copies we were multiplying in
times the number of
well, let's see, it's not x
times the number of zeros
that were in whatever we substituted for x
which in this case was 100
so if instead I had taken something like
log of 10,000 to the power n
this would be the same
as taking n copies of that 10,000
counting the number of zeros in each one of them
which is 4
so it would be n times 4
and of course the general property
that most of you correctly answered
is that you have this lovely little effect
where when you see the log of something raised to a power
that little power hops down in front of it
and you just have log of what was on the inside
now one of the maybe most important
implications of that
I don't know if you'd call it an implication
or if you'd call it a restatement of the definition
if I'm taking log
and I'll just re-emphasize it's base 10
of 10 to the power n
we can kind of think of that little n as hopping down in front
and it becomes n times the log base 10
of 10
which is of course 1
this expression you can think of as either
counting the number of zeros at the end
or more generally it's asking
10 to the what equals 10
and the answer is simply 1
which is very reassuring
because another way that you could go back and just read this original expression
is saying 10 to the what equals 10 to the n
oh well the answer is n
ok
now with every given logarithm property
that we have
so in this case we just found one
log of x to the power n involves that n hopping in front
there's always going to be a mirror image exponential property
and that's another way that we can help to get ourselves
a little bit of intuition for these
so let me just cover up some of the future properties we're going to get to here
try to hide where we're going
what we just found raising something to the n that hops in front
this corresponds to the exponential property
that if I take 10 to the x and raise that whole thing to the power n
that's the same as taking 10 to the n times x
and this gets us to another intuition that you might have for logarithms
which is they kind of they're like exponentiation turned inside out
and here's what I mean by that
the thing sitting on the inside of the log
if I'm taking log of a you should be thinking of that as the whole outer expression
for something that's exponential
in this case the a the thing on the inside corresponds to 10 to the x
the output of the function
whereas the entire thing itself
the log of a
corresponds to what's on the inside over here
just what's the exponent of the 10
so wherever you see a log expression here
you should be thinking that plays the role of an exponent on the right side
and every time you see an exponential
the entire 10 to the x expression
the whole outer component on the right side
that corresponds to something that's sitting on the inside of one of the logs
and we saw this above
the idea that when we're multiplying on the inside
that's adding on the outside
well if logs kind of turn exponentials inside out
that's telling us that multiplying on the outside
multiplying the outputs of the function
is the same as adding on the inside
because each of these logs like log a and log b
is playing the role of the x and the y in the expression on the right
so with that let's keep playing
let's just do a couple more of these and see how many of these properties
that we can build up an intuition for
so this last one, very nice thinking of exponents hopping down
the next one is something that might look a little bit weird
to those who are not necessarily familiar with logarithms
but again, plug in some numbers to gain some intuition for it
and we'll give it a little bit more a moment to pull up
which of the following is true?
log base a of b is negative log base b of a
log base a of b is 1 divided by log base b of a
log base a of b is 1 minus log base b of a
log base b of a is log base a of 1 divided by b
or none of the above
so it's asking what happens when we swap the base
with what's sitting inside of the logarithm
and I'll just give you a minute or two to answer that
so
okay, so it seems like answers have kind of stabilized out there
so let's go ahead and grade things
and in this case, the correct answer of the choices we have
comes out to be b
that the log base a of b involves taking 1 divided by the log base b of a
again, let's think this through both in terms of an example
and then in terms of a more proofy, systematic reason why it should be true
so if we're swapping our bases
let's just start off with
our good old friend log base 10
and let's plug in a nice power of 10 like 1000
counting the number of zeros, we get 3
so let's try swapping the bases and see what this should mean
log base 1000 of 10
okay, well what is this asking?
maybe you think of drawing a little triangle
saying something like we know 1000 to something is equal to 10
1000 to the what equals 10?
well, if 10 cubed is 1000
that is the same thing as saying 10 is equal to 1000
raised to the 1 third
doing the inverse here involves the multiplicative inverse of the exponent
and the way that pans out is that it looks like 1 divided by 3
and that 3 corresponds to the log base 10 of 1000
it's 1 divided by the log base 10 of 1000
so more generally, you might guess
based on this single example that when we swap the base with what's on the inside
it corresponds to taking 1 divided by what's on the outside there
and again, you can think this through in terms of
looking at the corresponding exponential rule
now what happened to my lovely little log and exponentials?
wonderful
so, again let's hide where some of the things
some of the other properties that we'll get to here
and I'll keep it in the same order I had it before
here I was thinking that having it pre-written could keep me a little bit cleaner than usual
but maybe it just involves playing this weird game of paper cutting shuffling around
so what we just found, log base b of a
if you swap those, it's the same as dividing by 1
what this corresponds to, off an exponential land
is if you take b to some power
and say that that equals a
that's the same statement as saying that a to the inverse of that power equals b
again, it's kind of helpful to take a moment and think of the logarithms as turning things inside out
the expression log base b of a is playing the role of that x
and the expression log base a of b is playing the role of whatever sits on top of the a
and then symmetrically, the whole expression b to the power x
is playing the role of the inside on the left, it plays the role of the a
and the whole expression, a to the power of something
plays the role of what's sitting inside the log base a
so you can see, just by plugging in some examples and by corresponding it to the exponential rules
we can already think through three different logarithm rules
which if they were just handed down as pieces of algebra to be memorized
you know, you could memorize them
but it's very easy for them to kind of slip out of your head
and it's also very easy to get frustrated by the task at hand
but you might want to remind yourself that the reason we care about these sorts of things
is understanding the rules of logarithms helps us do math in contexts where it's like a virus growing
where from one day to the next, from one step to the next, things tend to grow multiplicatively
understanding the rules of logarithms helps you to get a better feel for that kind of stuff
so before we do a nice real world example of what that can look like
let me just do one more quiz question in this vein to ask about properties of logarithms
one last one before we transition to a little bit of a real world example
get rid of what we had here
and now, which of the following is true?
log of a plus b is the same as log of a plus log of b
log of a plus b is equal to log of a times log of b
log of a plus b is equal to one divided by log of a plus log of b
or log of a plus b is equal to one divided by log of a times log of b or none of the above
ah, and now we don't have as much consensus, do we?
very interesting, we've got a horse race between two
so I will give you a moment to think this through
while people are answering, actually I have a little question for the audience
so, you know, I was just talking about how we might think in terms of multiplicative growth
and that doesn't just have to be powers of ten, we could also do something like powers of three
where if you're going from one to three to nine to twenty-seven to eighty-one, all of these
we could say that the log base three of these numbers just grows in nice little steps
so log base three of one, three to the what equals one, the answer is zero
in general the log of one, no matter the base, will be zero
log base three of three, three to the what equals three is one
similarly log base three of nine is two
ah, you might wonder what my question is, but it'll help to draw all of these out
and for my own pleasure here, let me just write out one more
log base three of eighty-one is four
now, I've heard that ostensibly if you ask a child, let's say around like five or six years old
what number is halfway between one and nine
you say what number is halfway
their instincts for how to answer are logarithmic
whereas our instincts tend to be more linear
so we often think one and nine, you've got a bunch of evenly spaced numbers between them
two, three, four, five, six, seven, eight
and if you go right halfway in between, you'll land on five
but if you're thinking in terms of multiplicative growth
where to get from one to nine, it's not a matter of adding a bunch of things
but you're growing by a certain amount
you grow by a factor of three, then you grow by another factor of three
supposedly, a kid's natural instinct lines up with saying three
and supposedly this also lines up with
if you have anthropologists studying societies that haven't developed
accounting systems and writing in the same way that modern societies have
they'll answer three for this
so, my question for the audience
if any of you watching right now have access to a small child
let's say, in the range of five years old
see if you can go ask them what number is halfway between one and nine
and if you can, let us know on Twitter what the child says
what their actual answer is
because I don't know why, I'm just a little bit skeptical of whether that actually pans out in practice
I understand this is not a super scientific way to do it
I'm not asking people watching a YouTube livestream to survey their own children
and then tweet the answer
but for my own sake it would be interesting to see some kind of validation there
back to our question
this is the first one that doesn't seem to have a huge consensus in one direction
let's go ahead and grade it to see what the answer turns out to be
great, okay, so
2,400 of you correctly answered that it's none of the above
that log of a plus b doesn't satisfy any of these nice properties
and in general, unless we're going to be working with certain kinds of approximations
especially when the natural log comes into play
we might talk about this next time
adding the inputs of a logarithm is actually a very weird sensation
it's a very weird thing to do
and to get a sense of that weirdness, plug in some powers of ten
if I ask you log of a plus b
what you might start thinking is, okay, let me just plug in some examples
like 10,000 and 100
and I ask myself, if I do this zero counting function of what's in that input
how many zeros are in it?
but it's weird, because when we add 10,100
well, we're no longer at a clean power of ten
and okay, that's fine, you know, often you're taking logarithms of things that aren't clean powers of ten
but it becomes very strange to ask how you express this in terms of log of 100
which was two
and log of 10,000
which was four
because if you look at log of 10,100, it's asking ten to the what is equal to 10,100
you might say, I don't know, it's going to be a little above four
because it's kind of close to 10,000
so the best you might guess here is, oh, this is going to be something that's kind of like the log of 10,000
but that just feels like a coincidence based on the two numbers that we happened to put in
there's not a nice systematic reason coming there
so maybe you guess, oh, if the numbers a and b are very different
it's kind of close to whatever the maximum of them is
but it's very bizarre
and most importantly, for the sake of the quiz
if you just look at the options that it's giving you
if you try this out with any particular numbers, you'll find that none of those actually work
so, all is good
sometimes you get something that looks like it's going to be a nice property
but it doesn't end up being a nice property
and I also think that's important
rather than just finding yourself only working with the various, you know, log of a times b
or log of x to the power n
these things that have a nice rule
sometimes you're out in the mathematical wild, you're working on some problem
you have a logarithm expression and it's adding things in the input
and you want to be able to have familiarity with the fact that that's kind of weird
that you're not going to be able to simplify
but if you, you know, if you hadn't thought about that before
you might wonder, oh, is there just some formula that I haven't seen before
so with all of that, let me go ahead and take a couple questions from the audience
before we transition to a different sort of example
so it looks like Uma Sherma asks
can the base be zero?
that's an interesting question
okay, can the base of a logarithm be zero?
well in terms of our triangle we might think of that as saying
you know, zero to some kind of power x is equal to some other value y
this is something that we could write either by saying zero to the x equals y
or we could write the same thing by saying log base zero of y is equal to x
zero to the what equals x
now the issue here is that zero to anything ends up being zero
right, so if we're just going to be thinking of log base zero of y
for any other input y
you know, you want to input something like one or two or pi
anything you might want, you're asking the question
zero to the what is equal to one or two or pi
or whatever number you might have there
and there's just not going to be an answer
so at best you could try to say
oh yes, log of zero, it's a perfectly valid function
it's only defined on the input zero
but even then you'd have trouble trying to finagle what you want there
because saying zero to the what equals zero
it's like anything applies to it
so your arm is going to be twisted behind your back however you want to make that work
and it corresponds to the fact that the exponential function
with base zero is entirely zero
it doesn't map numbers in a nice one to one fashion onto each other
so that's a great question, can you have a log base zero
now back to the idea of where these things come up in the real world
one example I kind of like is the Richter scale for earthquakes
so the Richter scale gives us a quantification for how strong an earthquake is
and it can be anything from very small numbers up to very large numbers
like I think the largest earthquake ever measured
and this is just a chart that comes from Wikipedia
was a 9.5
and to appreciate just how insane that is
it's worth looking at the relationship between what these numbers mean
and then something like the equivalent amount of TNT
some sort of measure of how much energy there is in it
and then what we can try to do here is
see if we can get an expression for the Richter scale number
in terms of the amount of energy
and why logarithms would be a natural way to describe this
so the key to focus on is as we're taking steps forward
how much do things increase
so for example if we go from two
well in this case it doesn't show us where three is
so maybe we think of taking a step from two up to four
which is kind of like taking two steps
what does that do in terms of the amount of energy
well it looks like it takes us from one metric ton of TNT
which is I guess a large bomb from World War II
and it takes us up to a kiloton
a thousand times as much
which is a small atom bomb
so just two steps on the Richter scale
going from an earthquake of magnitude 2 to an earthquake of magnitude 4
takes us from large bomb from World War II up to the nuclear age
so that is noteworthy
and the first clean step that we get is going from 4 to 5
at least in terms of what this chart is nicely showing us
and evidently a single step up from 4 to 5
corresponds to going from 1 kiloton to 32 kilotons
and that was evidently the size of the city destroying bomb that landed on Nagasaki
so this is maybe one thing that can be counterintuitive about logarithmic scales
if you're just hearing in the news the difference between
oh there was an earthquake that was a 4.0
versus an earthquake that was a 5.0
it's easy to think yeah 4 and 5 those are pretty similar numbers
but evidently in terms of TNT amounts
that corresponds to multiplying by 32 to get from 1 to the next
and going from 2 to 4 was evidently multiplying by about a thousand
and the only reason that's bigger is because here our chart wasn't showing what 3 was
so we were taking two steps
and you can verify for yourself that if you take a step of 32
and then you multiply by another 32 that's actually pretty close to a thousand
so the idea that additive steps on the Richter number
correspond to multiplicative steps in the TNT
seems to suggest that something logarithmic is at play here
and it's a little interesting to just keep going here
and say how much does this grow
partly because of the world phenomena it's describing
yes not a huge surprise that as we take another step
it's multiplying by about 32 again
but reining that in to our intuitions
that's the difference between 32 kilotons a small atom bomb
and then one megaton which we might think of as
not small atom bomb, Nagasaki atom bomb
which I guess is 32 of the Nagasaki atom bombs for one megaton
that is evidently the magnitude of the double string flat earthquake in Nevada USA 1994
I didn't know what that was, thanks Wikipedia
in terms of frequencies by the way I also looked these up
evidently ones that are less than two, those happen all the time
there's like 8000 of those per day
but as soon as we're in the realm of atom bombs
things like 3.5 and 4
those evidently also happen quite frequently somewhere on the earth
there's around 134 of those happening somewhere every day
who knew?
but as we get even more intense into this 5 and 6 range
which were well above the atom bomb scale
now we're only merely at around 2 per day
and I'm sure that a geologist could come in and explain why we all shouldn't be super worried
about the fact that there's two atom bomb equivalent disruptions to the earth's crust happening every day
but presumably it's particularly rare for those to be concentrated on some spot
like a city where lots of people live
now just verifying our thought that each step involves a growth of 32
let's look at what the step from 6 up to 7 looks like
and here it's giving us lots more examples in between
maybe giving the illusion that that's a bigger step than it actually is
and indeed that's the difference between 1 megaton and 32 megatons
so that's multiplying by 32
one of the things I found most interesting on this chart by the way
was look at how far we have to go before we get to the largest nuclear weapon that's ever actually been tested
this was height of the cold war
the Tsar bomb that was 50 megatons
and I believe they actually had original plans to have a 100 megaton bomb
but talked themselves down from that
50 megatons, we're talking start off at that 32 kilotons of the Nagasaki bomb
multiply by 32 to get a megaton
multiply by another 32
so we're talking about a thousand times the strength of the World War II ending explosion
and you're still not at the 50 megatons of what humanity is capable of
and that is evidently the Java earthquake of Indonesia
so 7.0 is not just a little bit bigger than 6.0, it's a lot bigger
and the point here of course is just that when you have a scale giving you multiplicative increases
it's worth appreciating that what look like small steps can actually be huge steps in terms of the energy implied
or the absolute values implied here
so when we're thinking about the fact that there was ever a 9.5
that actually seems absurd given that it's only in the 7.0 range that we're talking about
the largest thermonuclear weapon ever put out
and this is indicative of one area where logarithms tend to come about
it's when humans want to create a scale for something that accounts for a hugely wide variance in how big things can be
so in the case of size of earthquakes
you can have things from what happens just all the time around the Earth, the size of a large hand grenade
and you want that to be on your scale and something to think about
ranging all the way up to the largest disruption that we've seen in human history
and in order to have that in a way that you're not just writing a whole bunch of different digits in your numbers for one case
and a whole bunch of different, a smaller number of digits for your number in another case
it's nice to take logarithms and then just put that on a single scale that basically squishes those numbers between 0 and 10
you see something very similar going on with the decibel scale for music
that one actually works a little bit differently where every time you take a step up of 10 decibels
that corresponds to multiplying by 10
so rather than a step of 1 multiplying by 10, it's a step of 10 that multiplies by 10
so that kind of makes the math of it a little bit screwy
but the idea is the same, that if you're listening to a sound that's 50 decibels versus 60 decibels
it's a lot quieter in terms of the energy being transmitted
and going from, what would it be, 60 to 70 or 70 to 80
those steps, from 60 up to 80, that involves multiplying the amount of energy per square area by a factor of 100
so every time you see a logarithmic scale, know in your mind that that means whatever it's referring to under the hood grows by a huge amount
this is again why we saw a lot of logarithmic scales used to describe the coronavirus outbreak
so how might you describe a relationship like this where every time you grow the Richter scale number by 1, you're multiplying by 32
well, we could think in terms of a log with base 32
I could say if I take the log of, I'm just going to call r, the number for the Richter scale
I might think of this as log base 32 and that's going to correspond to, no no no, I'm doing this wrong
that's not the thing that's logged
we take the log base 32 of the big number, of the TMT number, something that was like 1 megaton
it's 1 million tons
the log base 32, that should correspond to the Richter scale number
but there might be some kind of offset, so we might say that there's some kind of constant s that we're adding to this Richter scale number
and this expression is exactly the same, excuse me for going off the bottom there
this expression is exactly the same as saying 32 to the power of some offset times our Richter scale number
which is the same as taking 32 to that offset, which itself is just some big constant, times 32 to the Richter scale number
so you might think of this as just being some constant times 32 to the power of the number you see
so this way of writing it really emphasizes the exponential growth of it
that if this is what corresponds to the TMT amount that you see, as you increase that r step by step you're multiplying by 32
but another way of communicating the exact same fact is to take the log base 32 of whatever that amount is
alright now the next thing I want to talk about is how we don't always have to worry about how to compute logs of different bases
it's a little weird here that we were talking about log base 32, I referenced earlier how mathematicians really like to have a log with base e
computer scientists really like to have a log with base 2
and it turns out for computational purposes or for also thinking about how these things grow
if you have one log, if you're able to compute one type of log, whether that's base 10, base 2, base e
you can compute pretty much anything else that you want
now to get our intuitions in that direction, let's turn back to our quiz and go to the next question
and I believe that this question is the most, I don't know, this is a halfway reasonable question, this should be nice
this is just going to get us prepared to translate from base 2 context to base 10 context
and it's also a good intuition for understanding powers of 2 to have in general
the relationship that it has with powers of 10
because it's this lovely kind of coincidence of nature that these two sort of
well you'll see what I mean, they play nicely with each other
so our question asks, given the fact that 2 to the 10th is 1024, 1024, which is approximately 1000
so if you're being a little bit loose with your numbers and you're just making approximations
2 to the 10th, basically 1000, which of the following is closest to being true?
log base 2 of 10 is approximately 0.3
log base 2 of 10 is approximately, sorry, log base 10 of 2 is approximately 0.3
log base 2 of 10 is approximately 1 third
or log base 10 of 2 is approximately 1 third
which of these is closest to being true based on the fact that 2 to the 10th is essentially 1000?
I'll give you a little moment for that
interesting that we've got kind of a split on this one
so I'm wondering if they're going to be numerically pretty similar
or if they're going to be conceptually similar
or if there's even a difference between those two
so since answers keep rolling in, I'm going to give this a little bit more time
so anyone at home watching, hopefully you already have a pencil and paper out
to be noodling through these yourself, that is the spirit of the lectures that we're doing
if you don't, now is the time to take out a pencil and paper
and see if you can think this one through and write it out
some of the problems that we're going to build to here definitely will require pencil and paper
so now is as good a time as any
and if you're watching this in the future, even if you can't participate in the live poll
I really do think it's a lot of fun to kind of throw your own hat into the mix
even if it's not going to contribute to one of the numbers that you see growing on the screen
I'll give you a little bit more time here as the answers seem to continue rolling in
so now is the time to take out your pencil and paper
and see if you can think this one through
and write it out
so now is as good a time as any
and if you can think this one through
then you can think this one through
and write it out
so now is as good a time as any
and if you can think this one through
and then do your Move
Ok, so I'll go ahead and grade it now
and let's see how people did on this one
so the correct answer is B
which is that the log base 10 of 2 Welcome!
tender. Not at all a unanimous decision here. Looks like it was D, which is that
the log base 10 of 2 is around 1 third. So that's good, they're very numerically
similar, right? That it's either 0.3 or around 1 third, which is 0.3333 repeating.
But the question was asking which one is closest to being true, and let's see how
we can think about this. So it points out that you have a power of 2, which is
1024, awfully close to a power of 10, about 10 cubed. And the question is how
we can leverage this to understand something like log base 2 of 10, or log
base 10 of 2. As we saw earlier, those are just the reciprocals of each other. So
what does this mean? If log base 2 of 10 is equal to x, that's the same thing as
saying 2 to the x is equal to 10, right? It's asking us 2 to the what equals 10.
So what we have here is an expression 10 cubed is approximately equal to 2 to
the 10. So what I might write out is we know that 2 to the 10, instead of writing
it as a 10, I'm going to write that 10 as 2 to the x, where x is the number such
that 2 to the x is approximate is equal to 10. So if that cubed is the same as 2
to the 10th, this is, I'll just write out the full details, the same as saying 2
to the 3x is equal to 2 to the 10th. And exponentiation is a nice one-to-one
function, so it's okay to just say whatever is going on in the input, if the
outputs are the same, the inputs must also be the same. You can't do that with
every function. People seem to think you can do that with any function, but you
just can't. And what that means is that x is about 10 thirds, okay?
Which, great, so log base 2 of 10 is about 10 thirds. So if we looked at our answers
though, that's not actually any of the options. We've got various things asking
log base 2 of 10 being around 0.3 or 1 third, so it looks like instead we should
try to re-express this as log base 10 of 2. And well enough, what we saw earlier is
that log base 2 of 10, we could also say log base 10 of 2 is just 1 over that
amount, 1 over x. And you can see this pretty easily by writing 2 is equal to
10 to the 1 over x. If we're asking 10 to the what equals 2, the answer is 1 over
what we just got there. So log base 10 of 2 is 1 divided by this amount, which is
3 tenths, which is 0.3. Great. So this is kind of a nice constant to think about
because there's this wonderful pattern that happens when we're looking at
powers of 2. So if I ask what is the log base 2 of a thousand, like we just saw,
it's approximately the case that 2 to the power 10 is equal to a thousand. And
because we're doing things at logs I'm just going to be writing it in that way.
Log 2 of a thousand is approximately 10. Similarly log base 2 of a million, well
let's see, if we have to multiply 2 by itself about 10 times to get to a
thousand, we should have to multiply it by itself around 20 times to get up to a
million. And indeed log base 2 of a million is approximately 20. It's a
little bit smaller but this is kind of a nice approximation to have in your mind.
And then similarly, you'll see why I'm writing out this as a pattern in just a
moment, if we wanted to go up to a billion, saying how many times do I have
to multiply 2 by itself to get to a billion, this is about 30. And any
computer scientist out there who's thought about, you know, just how much is
a kilobyte or a megabyte or a gigabyte, they'll be familiar with the idea that
powers of 2 are nice and close to these powers of 10, or more specifically powers
of a thousand. Now what I want to do is just write all of the same things with
log base 10, not approximately equal to, this is actually equal to 3. Log base
10 of a thousand is equal to 3. Log base 10, well you tell me, what's log base 10
of a million? It's counting the number of zeros, it ends up being about 6. And log
base 10 of a billion, counting the number of zeros, it ends up being 9. Now
the reason I wanted to write all of this out is to just emphasize an interesting
pattern here, which is we're just growing by these increments, right, as we go from
a thousand to a million to a billion with log base 2, we're stepping up by
steps of 10, but when we're playing the same game with 10, we're stepping up by
these increments of 3. So there's this nice relationship, and in fact for all of
them, to go from log base 2 to log base 10, it seems like we're just multiplying
by 0.3. So 10 times 0.3 is 3. 20, we scale down by that same amount. 30, we scale
down by that same amount. Okay? Now this is an intuition worth remembering. If you
have your numbers described with one base, it's basically the same as
describing them with another base, but there's some rescaling constant. Okay? And
then the next question is going to start getting us at that direction, but it's
going to be framed in a way that just looks like a whole pile of algebra, and
again I will encourage you to plug in numbers if you want to to gain a little
intuition for it. So as our third to last question, this will be a long lecture, we
have which of the following is true? And then just a whole pile of various
possible ways to combine log base C of B times log base C of A. Does that equal
log base B of A? And rather than me reading them out to you, I'll just
let you look through them, plug in some numbers. I'll give you a
meaningful time on this one because it's not obvious unless you're
already familiar with logarithms, and it's worth thinking through a little bit.
We have an outstanding question from the audience, which is does the bar length
of the pole use some kind of log function? And helpfully it looks like
Ben Eater has gone ahead and directly answered in the form of the code
involved, where the chart max is the raising 2 to the power of a
ceiling of a log base 2 of the maximum attempt count, which I think is to say
unraveling. If you're looking at the maximum number, I'm not great at
Vanna Whiting this thing, if you look at the maximum number in our poll, it's
asking what's the log base 2 of that, so as it crosses different powers of 2 then
that rescales it, and yes, yes is the answer. What a fantastically apropos
question. Thank You Karen. All right so answers are still rolling in, and I think
like I said I just want to give you some more time to think this through because
it looks like a big pile of algebra. Plug in some numbers to see what seems to
work well and see which answer fits.
you
okay so even if you are still thinking about it I'm gonna go ahead and grade it
here and then start talking about why it's true and then also why we should
care why this is an operation that actually tells us something so the
correct answer which it looks like around 1700 of you got congratulations is
log base C of B times log base B of A is equal to log base C of A great now
that's just a big ol pile of things why would that be true how do we think about
it now phase one like I said we might plug in an example but let's try to
actually think about why the example holds so let me pull out we've got this
as one more of the log rules this is just repeating the end what the correct
answer turned out to be where we've got an expression for log base C of B log
base B of A and this ends up being log base C of A it's gotten rid of the B's
which is kind of interesting so some examples you might plug in here would be
things like let's use a different color let's use green instead of C I'm gonna
go ahead and plug in 10 log base 10 of 100 which is kind of asking how many
times does 10 go into an 100 in a multiplicative sense how many times do I
multiply 10 by itself to get to 100 where the answer is 2 and then log of
100 of let's plug in another power of 10 it'll be nice if it's also a power of
100 so I'll do a million so this one is asking 10 100 to the what equals a
million how many times do I multiply a hundred by itself to get to a million
how many times does a hundred go into a million phrasing the same thing ten
different ways now the claim is that this is the same thing as taking log
base 10 of a million that if I ask how many times does 10 go into 100 and how
many times does 100 go into a million multiplying those should give me the
answer to how many times 10 goes into a million now just checking the numbers
this certainly works 10 goes into a hundred two times 100 goes into a
million three times in a multiplicative sense in that a hundred cubed is equal
to a million and indeed how many times does 10 go into a million well six now
we could think of this property in terms of the corresponding exponent rule which
is going to look a little bit stranger but it's actually just saying the
entirely the same thing so here we're if we have a base of C and a base of B and
we're trying to relate those to each other the whole statement is equal to
saying that um suppose that B to the X is equal to a got some number B you
raise it to some number X and equals a suppose it's also the case that C to the
Y equals B those two together are the same as saying C to the XY equals a now
that's kind of a mouthful to say out loud but if you plug in some numbers to
translate what all of that is really saying in the context of the example we
just did saying if you can write a hundred is ten squared and if you can
write a million as a hundred cubed well that lets you write a million in terms
of a power of ten okay so sort of asking this question how many times does one
number go into another but letting you layer it on top of each other now if we
rearrange that expression we get what is probably the second most important of
all of our log rules the most important is this top one that when you multiply
the inputs you add the outputs but the second most important which is known as
the change of base formula lets us rate that if you want the log base B of some
value a then for whatever C you want it doesn't actually matter what log you
have in your pocket if you use that other log and you take the log C of a
divided by the log C of B that gives you log base B of a okay so just as an
example here what this would look like is let's say I wanted to be able to
compute log base 100 of things I just really want to it's not a button on my
calculator but I would love to be able to do it and I want to do it in with an
input like a million well even if I don't have the log base 100 button on my
calculator what I can do is say I'll use the log base 10 button and evaluate
what's on the inside here which at least positionally it's kind of above the 100
it has a higher altitude as we write it so this can line up with the notation a
little bit that it sits on the numerator and on the bottom I use the log base 10
button that's in my calculator on the base on the 100 and then I can evaluate
both of those and it'll give me the answer in this case it gets you 6 divided
by 2 which will be 3 and if we really just think through what this is saying I
know I've said it many different times but it's a it's a convoluted enough way
to write things but an intuitive enough fact that I think just coming at it from
a bunch of different angles can be important because like I said this is
probably the second most important log rule we're asking how many times does 100
go into a million in a multiplicative sense how many times they multiply by
itself but division is asking that same question in an additive sense if I say
how many times does the log of 100 go into the log of a million that's what
division means it's saying how many times do I add this bottom number to
itself to get to the top but anything additive in the logarithm realm is the
same as anything multiplicative in terms of what's inside the parentheses so both
of the left-hand side and the right-hand side are just saying how many times does
100 go into a million but going about that in different ways so this is
extremely nice because it actually lets us compute things next time we're going
to talk all about the natural logarithm which is log base e often written ln and
turns out this is much easier to compute there's nice math behind it such that if
you want to come up with an algorithm that your calculator can use it's
actually a lot easier to think of log base e of numbers so anytime that you
need to go to some kind of calculator I don't know let's say we popped over to
something like Desmos always happy to have as a friend and you wanted to
compute log base 10 of some number you know let's say we're doing log base 10
of 57 and it looks like that's you know it should make sense it's between 1 and
2 because 57 was between 10 and 100 what's going on under the hood how is it
actually figuring this out it's going to use somewhere in there a change of base
formula which is going to be that the natural log of 57 divided by the natural
log of 10 is the same thing these are two different ways of writing it so if
you know one logarithm you know all of the logarithms okay and well let's just
use that fact to answer one more of our quiz questions and this will be the
second to last quiz question so thank you all for sticking it through I think
we will be I think you'll be pleased by the last question because the last
question will actually be like a fun problem-solving puzzle II thing and it
will involve a lot of what we've used up to this point kind of a culminating
thing so before that though just to make sure that we've got the instincts of
change of base down what do we have use the approximation that log base 2 of 10
is around 10 thirds so using that approximation which of the following is
approximately true log base 2 of X is about 10 thirds of log base 10 of X log
base 2 of X is log base 10 of 10 thirds of X log base 2 of X is log base 10 of X
to the power 10 thirds or log base 2 of X is 10 thirds times the log base 10 of
X and finally none of the above so I'll give you a moment to think about that
you might want to think to the chart that we were drawing earlier and
thinking about log base 2 and log base 10 as we're looking at powers of 1000
and how each of those grows that can leverage some of the intuition but I'll
let you think about it stop talking
you
while answers are rolling in it looks like a number of people have been asking
on Twitter about basically how complex numbers play into this so you know we've
got Jamil asking what if the base is imaginary we've got Kalkan asking what
about complex bases since e to the X is walking around the spiral wouldn't it
hit every complex number we won't hit every complex number but your instinct
that it's hitting multiple things is pretty spot-on doesn't make sense to
talk about logs with imaginary numbers by Nitya so to all of these questions
it's actually a very nuanced question the short answer is yes complex log
rhythms absolutely exist but each one of them has multiple different outputs so a
good a good analogy here is how if we have the square root function if I ask
something like the square root of 5 you know we have the convention that you
always do the positive amount but that doesn't quite feel honest it feels like
the right answer is to specify that there's two different outputs for the
square root function two solutions to x squared equals 25 and this is actually
true in complex numbers as well one of the things we talked about in a complex
number lecture was that you can take the square root of I and you actually get
root 2 over 2 plus root 2 over 2 I but that there's two solutions you can do
plus or minus this value and so you could say that the square root function
isn't a function but it's a multi-valued function it always has two different
outputs now something funky happens when we have exponents at play so if you're
just like someone who hasn't seen this stuff don't worry we talked about it in
previous lectures I'm obviously jumping around on the complexity level a lot
here where if in lecture five I'm talking about like Euler's formula with
complex numbers and compound interest and like how that plays into physics and
then lecture six we're back to the basics of logarithms I acknowledge that
might be a little bit jarring to potential audience members but just
continuing on with the answer if you note that e to the 2 pi times you know
some number times I this basically walks you around a circle so that the
output will walk around a circle and just keep repeating as n goes from 0 up
to 1 it'll walk around one cycle and end up back where you started as n goes from
1 to 2 you'll end up back where you started so for example e to the 0 sits
here e to the I pi is at negative 1 but e to the 2 pi I is also at 1 same with
e excuse me same with e to the 4 pi I that also equals 1 so in general if you
wanted to ask something like what is the log base e of 1 you know the one hand we
want to say the log of log base anything of 1 should be 0 because
anything to the power 0 equals that 1 but if we're letting complex numbers
into the mix you would have to honestly say well 2 pi I is another pretty good
answer to this question because e to the 2 pi I also equals 1 and same with 4 pi
I and you could even go in the negative direction and in general n times pi
times 2 times I kind of wrote that in a weird order for any integer in feels
like a valid answer to this question so there's a couple ways that you can deal
with that in math and before we get back to our usual lesson just on logarithm
rules this is interesting enough I kind of want to pull it up let's see what if
we have complex logarithm great Wikipedia always to our aid probably
it'll have a nice like visual of some kind for us look such fancy color
diagrams what I want okay this is what I want wonderful let's zoom out a little
bit great so there's this notion of what's called a Riemann surface that's
basically trying to capture the idea that you have a function with multiple
outputs and intuitively maybe you can understand what it's getting at where
the input would be something on the XY plane and the output there's just many
different outputs sitting there so when you have a complex logarithm you have to
account for that but it's used it's actually a very useful idea to do but it
takes a lot more nuance than than you might expect so with all of that
hopefully that helped at least partially answer some of people's questions same
same by the way with logarithms with based negative numbers because if you're
asking like negative 1 to the X and really noodling on what that means it's
it gets you into the realm of complex numbers so you have to deal with the
same multiple output idea now answers are rolling in more slowly so this seems
like a fine time to grade things and the answer turns out to be you rescale it if
you want to go from log base 2 of something to log base 10 of something it
involves rescaling and one way you could think about this is with the change of
base formula so let's say we have now let's get rid of our E stuff let's say
you have log base 2 of X but we want to write it in terms of log base 10 we can
write that as log base 10 of X divided by log base 10 of 2 saying how many
times does 2 go into X in a multiplicative sense is the same as
saying how many times does the log of 2 go into the log of X in an additive sense
okay and well what is 1 divided by the log base 10 of 2 so we're going to keep
our log base 10 of X out here and from what we found earlier we found that log
base 10 of 2 was approximately 3 tenths was approximately 0.3 so when we divide
by it that should get us 10 thirds okay and this lines up with what we were
looking at a little bit earlier with powers of 1000 let's see where was it
where was it great so when we're converting from log base 10 of something
up to log base 2 you know here we were thinking of multiplying the top by 0.3
to get to the bottom but you could also think of multiplying by 10 thirds to get
to the top anytime you have log base 10 of some number you just rescale it and
you have log base 2 of that number and the rescaling constant comes from the
log base 2 of 10 or vice versa log base 10 of 2 so that's change of base like I
said it's very important it lets you put everything into a nice universal
language and that should be all of the hint that you need for the last question
which is a challenge question on this one so if anyone's been watching and
they've been like I know logarithms I've got this completely down let me pull up
the last question which came up on let's see it's not the AMC but it's what
whatever the predecessor to the AMC was I believe so it's you know it's gonna
involve a little cleverness and manipulation we've got this long
sequence of fractions okay you take 1 divided by the log base 2 of a hundred
factorial and remember 100 factorial is 100 times 99 times 98 on the way all the
way down to 1 so 1 divided by the log base 2 of that plus 1 divided by the log
base 3 of 100 factorial plus 1 divided by log base 4 of 100 factorial on and on
and on up until 1 divided by the log base 100 of 100 factorial so this looks
rather intimidating right certainly adding fractions is never fun adding a
hundred fractions seems even worse dealing with a bunch of logs of different
bases seems like a pain and the factorial is playing into this so I'm
just gonna give you you know given that this is the wind down time I'm gonna
give you two or three minutes to start thinking about this and if you don't get
it it's totally fine we're gonna walk through what the answer is but I'm just
gonna let people think about this final challenge question before we call it a
day
you
so I'm gonna give you a little bit more time on this one because it's definitely
it's definitely fun to work out and I think if you know how to start then
great but if you don't know how to start just letting yourself kind of work with
a couple of the different rules that we've worked out before change of base
comes into play if you'd like to use that and just kind of keep manipulating
and if it feels like you're getting something that's a little too messy see
if you come at it from a different angle and because answers are rolling in a
little bit more slowly now what I'm gonna do is just start to describe the
explanation here and then come back to grade it in just a moment here so the
expression that we have looks like I just started writing it out while you
guys were working on it 1 divided by log base 2 of 100 factorial plus 1
divided by log base 3 of 100 factorial and before you even start the fact that
the thing on the inside of the log involves a big product of stuff should
actually feel good because logs like to take in things that look like products
because of the most important property that we have which is the idea that it
turns products into addition okay so right away you know that you're probably
going to use that second thing you notice is that it's uncomfortable to
have all of these different bases log base 2 of something log base 3 of
something log base 100 of something so translating it all into the common
language should be helpful how does change of base work well asking how many
times does to go into a hundred factorial is the same as asking how many
times does the log of 2 divide into the log of a hundred factorial it doesn't
even matter what logarithm you use this log could be base 10 base e base 2
doesn't matter this change of base formula still holds now what that means
for our expression is instead of taking 1 divided by log base 2 of 100 factorial
I could write that as log of 2 divided by so let me draw a little dividing line
between what I'm doing here log of 2 divided by log of a hundred factorial
okay and then similarly log of 3 divided by log of 100 factorial so all I'm doing
here is taking the reciprocal so instead of taking log of 100 factorial
over log of 2 I've inverted it log of 2 over 100 factorial because that's what
this reciprocal is doing so with that as the beginning I'm going to go ahead and
just grade this lock in the answers and see how see how everyone's doing so it
looks like awesome around 1796 we always we always draw a little bit north of
Ramanujan's number around 1800 of you answered that it's one which is correct
congratulations 70 of you answered 100 which we can maybe see where where that
our error would have come from those of you that answered zero that's
interesting it would imply that somehow you have cancellation at play because
these are all positive numbers so thinking one of them was negative so you
could probably gut check against the idea that it would be zero 41 of you
want me to come up with a number fun numerical fact about 69 but I won't 28
of you said 2 and I think yeah I think that's I think the the difference
between 1 and 100 maybe would be interesting to try to analyze but if we
go back to our answer I realize it may be a little bit confusing how I've written
this this isn't this is not a big fraction this was just a dividing line
between not ironically trying not to confuse my fractions with each other so
rewriting our expression up on the top here as we add all of these things and
we can continue up until log of 100 all divided by log of 100 factorial the key
is that now all of the denominators are the same so we can add the numerators no
more plus sign is just going to equal something that top is going to look like
log of 2 plus log of 3 plus on and on up to log of 100 all divided by the log of
100 factorial and it seems like the only little contention among those answering
the question is whether this should simplify to be 1 or should it simplify
to be a hundred and really the way we can think about this is to just break
down that bottom part in terms of what a factorial means I'll go ahead and do
this on the bottom part since I didn't manage my paper real estate very
effectively here the log of 100 times 99 times 98 on and on times 2 times 1 is
the same as adding all of them and you can probably see this mostly cancels out
with the top the only question you might have though is that in the factorial
and we keep multiplying down until we get that one which doesn't really make
a difference but before you think about it too much you might wonder hang on you
know on the bottom I'm multiplying everything and I'm adding this log of 1
but on the top from what we found before I never saw that log of 1 does that make
any difference and the answer is no because log of 1 is saying 10 to the
power of what equals 1 and the answer is 0 so in fact taking the log of 100
factorial is the same as adding the logs of all the numbers from 2 up to 100 and
it simplifies down to 1 so to those of you who got it congratulations to those
of you who feel like you maybe have better intuitions for change of base
formulas for the fact that logarithms turn multiplication into addition that's
my hope in the next time with this as a foundation of logarithms that can be
pointed back to what I would love to talk about is what's known as the
natural logarithm log base e and try to give an instinct for why that's
something that we care about okay why is it that mathematicians just seem to
really love the number e sitting in the base of their logarithms what does that
buy for them why does it show up in nature so that will happen on Friday at
the same time as this lecture and I look forward to seeing everyone there
you