Suppose I give you two different lists of numbers, or maybe two different functions,
and I ask you to think of all the ways you might combine those two lists to get a new list of
numbers, or combine the two functions to get a new function. Maybe one simple way that comes to mind
is to simply add them together term by term. Likewise with the functions, you can add all
the corresponding outputs. In a similar vein, you could also multiply the two lists term by term
and do the same thing with the functions. But there's another kind of combination just as
fundamental as both of those, but a lot less commonly discussed, known as a convolution.
But unlike the previous two cases, it's not something that's merely inherited from an
operation you can do to numbers. It's something genuinely new for the context of lists of numbers
or combining functions. They show up all over the place, they are ubiquitous in image processing,
it's a core construct in the theory of probability, they're used a lot in solving differential
equations, and one context where you've almost certainly seen it, if not by this name, is
multiplying two polynomials together. As someone in the business of visual explanations, this is
an especially great topic, because the formulaic definition in isolation and without context can
look kind of intimidating, but if we take the time to really unpack what it's saying, and before that
actually motivate why you would want something like this, it's an incredibly beautiful operation.
And I have to admit, I actually learned a little something while putting together the visuals for
this project. In the case of convolving two different functions, I was trying to think of
different ways you might picture what that could mean, and with one of them I had a little bit of
an aha moment for why it is that normal distributions play the role that they do in
probability, why it's such a natural shape for a function. But I'm getting ahead of myself, there's
a lot of setup for that one. In this video, our primary focus is just going to be on the discrete
case, and in particular building up to a very unexpected but very clever algorithm for computing
these. And I'll pull out the discussion for the continuous case into a second part.
It's very tempting to open up with the image processing examples, since they're visually the most
intriguing, but there are a couple bits of finickiness that make the image processing case
less representative of convolutions overall, so instead let's kick things off with probability,
and in particular one of the simplest examples that I'm sure everyone here has thought about at
some point in their life, which is rolling a pair of dice and figuring out the chances of seeing
various different sums. And you might say, not a problem, not a problem. Each of your two dice has
six different possible outcomes, which gives us a total of 36 distinct possible pairs of outcomes,
and if we just look through them all we can count up how many pairs have a given sum.
And arranging all the pairs in a grid like this, one pretty nice thing is that all of the pairs
that have a constant sum are visible along one of these different diagonals. So simply counting how
many exist on each of those diagonals will tell you how likely you are to see a particular sum.
And I'd say, very good, very good, but can you think of any other ways that you might visualize
the same question? Other images that can come to mind to think of all the distinct pairs that have
a given sum? And maybe one of you raises your hand and says, yeah, I've got one. Let's say you picture
these two different sets of possibilities each in a row, but you flip around that second row. That way
all of the different pairs which add up to seven line up vertically like this. And if we slide that
bottom row all the way to the right, then the unique pair that adds up to two, the snake eyes,
are the only ones that align. And if I schlunk that over one unit to the right, the pairs which
align are the two different pairs that add up to three. And in general, different offset values of
this lower array, which remember I had to flip around first, reveal all the distinct pairs that
have a given sum. As far as probability questions go, this still isn't especially interesting,
because all we're doing is counting how many outcomes there are in each of these categories.
But that is with the implicit assumption that there's an equal chance for each of these faces
to come up. But what if I told you I have a special set of dice that's not uniform? Maybe
the blue die has its own set of numbers describing the probabilities for each face coming up,
and the red die has its own unique distinct set of numbers. In that case, if you wanted to figure out,
say, the probability of seeing a two, you would multiply the probability that the blue die is a one
times the probability that the red die is a one. And for the chances of seeing a three,
you look at the two distinct pairs where that's possible, and again, multiply the corresponding
probabilities, and then add those two products together. Similarly, the chances of seeing a four
involves multiplying together three different pairs of possibilities and adding them all
together. And in the spirit of setting up some formulas, let's name these top probabilities a1,
a2, a3, and so on, and name the bottom ones b1, b2, b3, and so on. And in general, this process,
where we're taking two different arrays of numbers, flipping the second one around,
and then lining them up at various different offset values, taking a bunch of pairwise
products and adding them up, that's one of the fundamental ways to think about what a convolution
is. So just to spell it out a little more exactly, through this process, we just generated
probabilities for seeing two, three, four, on and on up to 12, and we got them by mixing together
one list of values, a, and another list of values, b. In the lingo, we'd say the convolution of those
two sequences gives us this new sequence, the new sequence of 11 values, each of which looks like
some sum of pairwise products. If you prefer, another way you could think about the same
operation is to first create a table of all the pairwise products, and then add up along all these
diagonals. Again, that's a way of mixing together these two sequences of numbers to get us a new
sequence of 11 numbers. It's the same operation as the sliding windows thought, just another perspective.
Putting a little notation to it, here's how you might see it written down. The convolution of a
and b, denoted with this little asterisk, is a new list, and the nth element of that list looks like
a sum, and that sum goes over all different pairs of indices, i and j, so that the sum of those
indices is equal to n. It's kind of a mouthful, but for example, if n was 6, the pairs we're going
over are 1 and 5, 2 and 4, 3 and 3, 4 and 2, 5 and 1, all the different pairs that add up to 6.
But honestly, however you write it down, the notation is secondary in importance to the visual
you might hold in your head for the process. Here, maybe it helps to do a super simple example, where
I might ask you what's the convolution of the list 1, 2, 3, with the list 4, 5, 6. You might picture
taking both of these lists, flipping around that second one, and then starting with its
lid all the way over to the left. Then the pair of values which align are 1 and 4, multiply them
together, and that gives us our first term of our output. Slide that bottom array one unit to the
right, the pairs which align are 1 and 5, and 2 and 4, multiply those pairs, add them together, and that
gives us 13, the next entry in our output. Slide things over once more, and we'll take 1 times 6,
plus 2 times 5, plus 3 times 4, which happens to be 28. One more slide, and we get 2 times 6,
plus 3 times 5, and that gives us 27, and finally the last term will look like 3 times 6.
If you'd like, you can pull up whatever your favorite programming language is, and your
favorite library that includes various numerical operations, and you can confirm I'm not lying to
you. If you take the convolution of 1, 2, 3, against 4, 5, 6, this is indeed the result that you'll get.
We've seen one case where this is a natural and desirable operation, adding up to probability
distributions, and another common example would be a moving average. Imagine you have some long list
of numbers, and you take another smaller list of numbers that all add up to 1. In this case, I just
have a little list of 5 values, and they're all equal to 1 5th. Then if we do this sliding window
convolution process, and kind of close our eyes and sweep under the rug what happens at the very
beginning of it, once our smaller list of values entirely overlaps with the bigger one,
think about what each term in this convolution really means. At each iteration, what you're doing
is multiplying each of the values from your data by 1 5th, and adding them all together, which is
to say you're taking an average of your data inside this little window. Overall, the process
gives you a smoothed out version of the original data, and you could modify this starting with a
different little list of numbers, and as long as that little list all adds up to 1, you can still
interpret it as a moving average. In the example shown here, that moving average would be giving
more weight towards the central value. This also results in a smoothed out version of the data.
If you do kind of a two-dimensional analog of this, it gives you a fun algorithm for blurring
a given image. And I should say the animations I'm about to show are modified from something
I originally made for part of a set of lectures I did with the Julia Lab at MIT for a certain
OpenCourseWare class that included an image processing unit. There we did a little bit more
to dive into the code behind all of this, so if you're curious I'll leave you some links. But
focusing back on this blurring example, what's going on is I've got this little 3x3 grid of
values that's marching along our original image, and if we zoom in, each one of those values is 1
9th, and what I'm doing at each iteration is multiplying each of those values by the
corresponding pixel that it sits on top of. And of course in computer science we think of colors
as little vectors of three values, representing the red, green, and blue components.
When I multiply all these little values by 1 9th and I add them together, it gives us an average
along each color channel, and the corresponding pixel for the image on the right is defined to be
that sum. The overall effect, as we do this for every single pixel on the image, is that each one
kind of bleeds into all of its neighbors, which gives us a blurrier version than the original.
In the lingo we'd say that the image on the right is a convolution of our original image with a
little grid of values. Or more technically maybe I should say that it's the convolution with a 180
degree rotated version of that little grid of values. Not that it matters when the grid is
symmetric, but it's just worth keeping in mind that the definition of a convolution, as inherited from
the pure math context, should always invite you to think about flipping around that second array.
If we modify this slightly we can get a much more elegant blurring effect by choosing a different
grid of values. In this case I have a little 5x5 grid, but the distinction is not so much its size.
If we zoom in we notice that the value in the middle is a lot bigger than the value towards
the edges, and where this is coming from is they're all sampled from a bell curve, known as a Gaussian
distribution. That way when we multiply all of these values by the corresponding pixel that
they're sitting on top of, we're giving a lot more weight to that central pixel and much less towards
the ones out at the edge. And just as before the corresponding pixel on the right is defined to be
this sum. As we do this process for every single pixel it gives a blurring effect which much more
authentically simulates the notion of putting your lens out of focus or something like that.
But blurring is far from the only thing that you can do with this idea. For instance take a look at
this little grid of values, which involves some positive numbers on the left and some negative
numbers on the right, which I'll color with blue and red respectively. Take a moment to see if you
can predict and understand what effect this will have on the final image. So in this case I'll just
be thinking of the image as grayscale instead of colored, so each of the pixels is just represented
by one number instead of three. And one thing worth noticing is that as we do this convolution
it's possible to get negative values. For example at this point here if we zoom in the left half of
our little grid sits entirely on top of black pixels, which would have a value of zero, but the
right half of negative values all sit on top of white pixels, which would have a value of one.
So when we multiply corresponding terms and add them together the results will be very negative,
and the way I'm displaying this with the image on the right is to color negative values red and
positive values blue. Another thing to notice is that when you're on a patch that's all the same
color everything goes to zero since the sum of the values in our little grid is zero. This is very
different from the previous two examples where the sum of our little grid was one, which let us
interpret it as a moving average and hence a blur. All in all this little process basically
detects wherever there's variation in the pixel value as you move from left to right,
and so it gives you a kind of way to pick up on all the vertical edges from your image.
And similarly if we rotated that grid around so that it varies as you move from the top to the
bottom this will be picking up on all the horizontal edges, which in the case of our
little pie creature image does result in some pretty demonic eyes. This smaller grid by the
way is often called a kernel, and the beauty here is how just by choosing a different kernel you can
get different image processing effects, not just blurring your edge detection but also things like
sharpening. For those of you who have heard of a convolutional neural network the idea there is to
use data to figure out what the kernels should be in the first place as determined by whatever
the neural network wants to detect. Another thing I should maybe bring up is the length of the
output. For something like the moving average example you might only want to think about the
terms when both of the windows fully align with each other, or in the image processing example
maybe you want the final output to have the same size as the original. Now convolutions as a pure
math operation always produce an array that's bigger than the two arrays that you started with,
at least assuming one of them doesn't have a length of one. Just know that in certain
computer science contexts you often want to deliberately truncate that output.
Another thing worth highlighting is that in the computer science context this notion of flipping
around that kernel before you let it march across the original often feels really weird and just
uncalled for, but again note that that's what's inherited from the pure math context where like
we saw with the probabilities it's an incredibly natural thing to do. And actually I can show you
one more pure math example where even the programmers should care about this one because
it opens the doors for a much faster algorithm to compute all of these. To set up what I mean by
faster here let me go back and pull up some python again and I'm going to create two different
relatively big arrays. Each one will have a hundred thousand random elements in it and I'm
going to assess the runtime of the convolve function from the numpy library. And in this case
it runs it for multiple different iterations, tries to find an average, and it looks like on
this computer at least it averages at 4.87 seconds. By contrast if I use a different
function from the scipy library called fftconvolve which is the same thing just implemented
differently that only takes 4.3 milliseconds on average, so three orders of magnitude improvement.
And again even though it flies under a different name it's giving the same output that the other
convolve function does, it's just doing something to go about it in a cleverer way.
Remember how with the probability example I said another way you could think about the convolution
was to create this table of all the pairwise products and then add up those pairwise products
along the diagonals. There's of course nothing specific to probability anytime you're convolving
two different lists of numbers you can think about it this way. Create this kind of multiplication
table with all pairwise products and then each sum along the diagonal corresponds to one of your
final outputs. One context where this view is especially natural is when you multiply together
two polynomials. For example let me take the little grid we already have and replace the top
terms with 1, 2x, and 3x squared and replace the other terms with 4, 5x, and 6x squared.
Now think about what it means when we're creating all of these different pairwise products between
the two lists. What you're doing is essentially expanding out the full product of the two
polynomials I have written down and then when you add up along the diagonal that corresponds
to collecting all like terms which is pretty neat expanding a polynomial and collecting like terms
is exactly the same process as a convolution. But this allows us to do something that's pretty cool
because think about what we're saying here. We're saying if you take two different functions and you
multiply them together which is a simple pointwise operation that's the same thing as if you had
first extracted the coefficients from each one of those assuming they're polynomials and then taken
a convolution of those two lists of coefficients. What makes that so interesting is that convolutions
feel in principle a lot more complicated than simple multiplication and I don't just mean
conceptually they're harder to think about I mean computationally it requires more steps to perform
a convolution than it does to perform a pointwise product of two different lists. For example let's
say I gave you two really big polynomials say each one with a hundred different coefficients
then if the way you multiply them was to expand out this product you know filling in this entire
100 by 100 grid of pairwise products that would require you to perform 10,000 different products
and then when you're collecting all the like terms along the diagonals that's another set of around
10,000 operations. More generally in the lingo we'd say the algorithm is O of n squared meaning for two
lists of size n the way that the number of operations scales is in proportion to the square
of n. On the other hand if I think of two polynomials in terms of their outputs for example
sampling their values at some handful of inputs then multiplying them only requires as many
operations as the number of samples since again it's a pointwise operation and with polynomials
you only need finitely many samples to be able to recover the coefficients. For example two outputs
are enough to uniquely specify a linear polynomial. Three outputs would be enough to uniquely specify
a quadratic polynomial. And in general if you know n distinct outputs that's enough to uniquely
specify a polynomial that has n different coefficients. Or if you prefer we could phrase
this in the language of systems of equations. Imagine I tell you I have some polynomial but I
don't tell you what the coefficients are, those are a mystery to you. In our example you might think of
this as the product that we're trying to figure out. Then suppose I say I'll just tell you what
the outputs of this polynomial would be if you inputted various different inputs like 0, 1, 2, 3, on and on,
and I give you enough so that you have as many equations as you have unknowns. It even happens to
be a linear system of equations, so that's nice. And in principle at least, this should be enough to
recover the coefficients. So the rough algorithm outline then would be whenever you want to convolve
two lists of numbers you treat them like they're coefficients of two polynomials. You sample those
polynomials at enough outputs, multiply those samples point-wise, and then solve the system
to recover the coefficients as a sneaky backdoor way to find the convolution. And as I've stated it
so far at least, some of you could rightfully complain "Grant, that is an idiotic plan". Because
for one thing just calculating all these samples for one of the polynomials we know already takes
on the order of n squared operations, not to mention solving that system is certainly going
to be computationally as difficult as just doing the convolution in the first place. So, like, sure
we have this connection between multiplication and convolutions, but all of the complexity happens in
translating from one viewpoint to the other. But there is a trick, and those of you who know about
Fourier transforms and the FFT algorithm might see where this is going. If you're unfamiliar with these
topics, what I'm about to say might seem completely out of the blue. Just know that there are certain
paths you could have walked in math that make this more of an expected step. Basically the idea is
that we have a freedom of choice here. If instead of evaluating at some arbitrary set of inputs like
0, 1, 2, 3, on and on, you choose to evaluate on a very specially selected set of complex numbers.
Specifically the ones that sit evenly spaced on the unit circle, what are known as the roots of
unity. This gives us a friendlier system. The basic idea is that by finding a number where taking its
powers falls into this cycling pattern, it means that the system we generate is going to have a lot
of redundancy in the different terms that you're calculating, and by being clever about how you
leverage that redundancy, you can save yourself a lot of work. This set of outputs that I've written
has a special name, it's called the discrete Fourier transform of the coefficients. And if you want to
learn more I actually did another lecture for that same Julia MIT class all about discrete
Fourier transforms. And there's also a really excellent video on the channel reducible talking
about the fast Fourier transform, which is an algorithm for computing these more quickly. Also
Veritasium recently did a really good video on FFT's, so you've got lots of options. And that fast
algorithm really is the point for us. Again because of all this redundancy there exists a method to go
from the coefficients to all of these outputs, where instead of doing on the order of n squared
operations, you do on the order of n times the log of n operations, which is much much better as you
scale to big lists. And importantly this fft algorithm goes both ways. It also lets you go
from the outputs to the coefficients. So bringing it all together, let's look back at our algorithm
outline. Now we can say whenever you're given two long lists of numbers and you want to take their
convolution, first compute the fast Fourier transform of each one of them, which in the back
of your mind you can just think of as treating them like they're the coefficients of a polynomial
and evaluating it at a very specially selected set of points. Then multiply together the two results
that you just got point-wise, which is nice and fast, and then do an inverse fast Fourier transform,
and what that gives you is the sneaky backdoor way to compute the convolution that we were looking
for. But this time it only involves O of n log n operations. That's really cool to me! This very
specific context where convolutions show up, multiplying two polynomials, opens the doors for
an algorithm that's relevant everywhere else where convolutions might come up. If you want to add
probability distributions, do some large image processing, whatever it might be. And I just think
that's such a good example of why you should be excited when you see some operation or concept in
math show up in a lot of seemingly unrelated areas. If you want a little homework here's
something that's fun to think about. Explain why when you multiply two different numbers, just
ordinary multiplication the way we all learn in elementary school, what you're doing is basically
a convolution between the digits of those numbers. There are some added steps with carries and the like,
but the core step is a convolution. In light of the existence of a fast algorithm, what that means is
if you have two very large integers, then there exists a way to find their product that's faster
than the method we learn in elementary school. That instead of requiring O of n squared operations
only requires O of n log n, which doesn't even feel like it should be possible. The catch is that
before this is actually useful in practice, your numbers would have to be absolutely monstrous.
But still, it's cool that such an algorithm exists. Next up we'll turn our attention to the
continuous case with a special focus on probability distributions.