I recently had a lot of fun making simulations for
how the electric field responds to a moving charge.
It was all for a longer video on YouTube that covers the fundamentals of what light is,
but here I just thought I'd share with you some of the pretty
animations that came out of it.
The full electric field is three-dimensional.
It associates each point in space with a little vector telling you what force
would be applied to a unit charge if it were sitting at that point in space.
The 3D fields are fun to look at, but they are a bit busy,
so often it's easier to just show a slice of that field, say on the xy plane.
In the main video I talk about the underlying law used to make these simulations.
It's not actually Maxwell's equations, which are the
fundamental laws underlying electricity and magnetism.
Instead I'm coding in another intermediate law,
something that you can derive from Maxwell's equations,
but which is a little easier to wrap your mind around,
both for the sake of making the animations and also for the sake of
the student trying to understand what's going on.