Take 1 plus 1 fourth plus 1 ninth plus 1 sixteenth and so on where you're adding the inverses of the next square number
What does this sum approach as you keep adding on more and more terms?
Now this is a challenge that remained unsolved for 90 years after it was initially posed until finally it was Euler who found the answer
Super surprisingly to be pi squared divided by 6. I mean isn't that crazy? What is pi doing here?
And why is it squared? We don't usually see it squared in honor of Euler whose hometown was basil
This infinite sum is often referred to as the basil problem
But the proof that I'd like to show you is very different from the one that Euler had
I've said in a previous video that whenever you see pi show up
There will be some connection to circles and there are those who like to say that pi is not fundamentally about circles and
Insisting on connecting equations like these ones with a geometric intuition
stems from a stubborn insistence on only understanding pi in the context where we first discovered it and
That's all well and good
But whatever your own perspective holds as fundamental the fact is pi is very much tied to circles
So if you see it show up there will be a path somewhere in the massive interconnected web of mathematics
Leading you back to circles and geometry
The question is just how long and convoluted that path might be and in the case of the basil problem
It's a lot shorter than you might first think and it all starts with light
Here's the basic idea
Imagine standing at the origin of a positive number line and putting a little lighthouse on all of the positive integers one two
three four and so on that first lighthouse has some
Apparent brightness from your point of view some amount of energy that your eye is receiving from the light per unit time and
Let's just call that a brightness of one
For reasons I'll explain shortly
the apparent brightness of the second lighthouse is
1 fourth as much as the first and the apparent brightness of the third is 1 9th as much as the first and then
1 16th and so on and you can probably see why this is useful for the basil problem
It gives us a physical representation of what's being asked
Since the brightness received from the whole infinite line of lighthouses is going to be 1 plus 1 4th plus 1 9th
Plus the 16th and so on
So the result that we are aiming to show is that this total brightness is equal to pi squared divided by 6
times the brightness of that first lighthouse
And at first that might seem useless
I mean, we're just re-asking the same original question
But the progress comes from a new question that this framing raises are there ways that we can rearrange these lighthouses
That don't change the total brightness for the observer
And if so, can you show this to be equivalent to a setup that's somehow easier to compute
To start let's be clear about what we mean when we reference apparent brightness to an observer
Imagine a little screen which maybe represents the retina of your eye or a digital camera sensor or something like that
You could ask what proportion of the rays coming out of the source hit that screen or phrase differently
What is the angle between the ray hitting the bottom of that screen and the ray hitting the top?
Or rather since we should be thinking of these lights as being in three dimensions. It might be more accurate to ask
What is the angle the light covers in both directions perpendicular to the source?
In spherical geometry you sometimes talk about the solid angle of a shape
Which is the proportion of a sphere it covers as viewed from a given point
You see the first of two places this story we're thinking of screens is going to be useful is in understanding the inverse square law
Which is a distinctly three-dimensional phenomenon
think of all of the rays of light hitting a screen one unit away from the source as
You double the distance those rays will now cover an area with twice the width and twice the height
So it would take four copies of that original screen to receive the same rays at that distance
And so each individual one receives 1 fourth as much light
This is the sense in which I mean a light would appear 1 fourth as bright two times the distance away
Likewise when you're three times farther away
You would need nine copies of that original screen to receive the same rays
so each individual screen only receives 1 9th as much light and
This pattern continues because the area hit by a light increases by the square of the distance the brightness of that light
decreases by the inverse square of that distance and
As I'm sure many of you know this inverse square law is not at all special to light
It pops up whenever you have some kind of quantity that spreads out evenly from a point source
whether that's sound or heat or radio signal things like that and
Infinite array of evenly spaced lighthouses physically implements the basel problem
But again what we need if we're going to make any progress here is to understand how we can
manipulate setups with light sources like this without changing the total brightness for the observer and
The key building block is an especially nice way to transform a single lighthouse into two
Think
Of an observer at the origin of the XY plane and a single lighthouse sitting out somewhere on that plane
Now draw a line from that lighthouse to the observer and then another line
perpendicular to that one at the lighthouse
Now place two lighthouses where this new line
intersects the coordinate axes
Which I'll go ahead and call lighthouse a over here on the left and lighthouse B on the upper side
It turns out and you'll see why this is true in just a minute the brightness that the observer
Experiences from that first lighthouse is equal to the combined brightness experienced from lighthouses A and B together
And I should say by the way that the standing assumption throughout this video is that all lighthouses are equivalent
They're using the same light bulb emanating the same power all of that
So in other words assigning variables to things here if we call the distance from the observer to lighthouse a little a
And the distance from the observer to lighthouse B little B and the distance to the first lighthouse H
We have the relation 1 over a squared plus 1 over b squared equals 1 over h squared
This is the much less well-known
Inverse Pythagorean theorem which some of you may recognize from math ologer's most recent and I'll say most excellent
video on the many cousins of the Pythagorean theorem
Pretty cool relation don't you think and
if you're a mathematician at heart you might be asking right now how you prove it and
There are some straightforward ways where you express the triangles area in two separate ways and apply the usual Pythagorean theorem
But there is another quite pretty method that I'd like to briefly outline here that falls much more nicely into our storyline because again
It uses intuitions of light and screens
Imagine scaling down the whole right triangle into a tinier version and think of this miniature
Hypotenuse as a screen receiving light from the first lighthouse
If you reshape that screen to be the combination of the two legs of the miniature triangle like this
Well, it still receives the same amount of light, right?
I mean the rays of light hitting one of those two legs are precisely the same as the rays that hit the hypotenuse
Then the key is that the amount of light from the first lighthouse that hits this left side
the limited angle of rays that end up hitting that screen is
Exactly the same as the amount of light over here coming from lighthouse a which hits that side
it'll be the same angle of rays and
Symmetrically the amount of light from the first house hitting the bottom portion of our screen is
The same as the amount of light hitting that portion from lighthouse B
Why you might ask well, it's a matter of similar triangles
This animation already gives you a strong hint for how it works
And we've also left a link in the description to a simple
GeoGebra applet for those of you who want to think this through in a slightly more interactive environment and in playing with that
One important fact here that you'll be able to see is that the similar triangles only apply in the limiting case for a very tiny
screen
The inverse Pythagorean theorem
Alright buckle up now because here's where things get good
We've got this inverse Pythagorean theorem, right?
And that's going to let us transform a single lighthouse into two others without changing the brightness
experienced by the observer
With that in hand and no small amount of cleverness we can use this to build up the infinite array that we need
Picture yourself at the edge of a circular lake directly opposite a lighthouse
We're going to want it to be the case that the distance between you and the lighthouse
Along the border of the lake is one so we'll say the lake has a circumference of two
now the apparent brightness is one divided by the diameter squared and
In this case the diameter is that circumference 2 divided by pi so the apparent brightness works out to be
pi squared divided by 4
Now for our first transformation draw a new circle twice as big so circumference 4 and
Draw a tangent line to the top of the small circle
then replace the original lighthouse with two new ones where this tangent line intersects the larger circle an
Important fact from geometry that we'll be using over and over here
Is that if you take the diameter of a circle and form a triangle with any point on the circle?
The angle at that new point will always be 90 degrees
the significance of that in our diagram here is that it means the inverse Pythagorean theorem applies and
the brightness from those two new lighthouses equals the brightness from the first one namely pi squared divided by 4 as
The next step draw a new circle twice as big as the last with a circumference 8
Now for each lighthouse take a line from that lighthouse through the top of the smaller circle
Which is the center of the larger circle and consider the two points where that intersects with the larger circle
Again, since this line is a diameter of that large circle
Then the lines from those two new points to the observer are going to form a right angle
Likewise by looking at this right triangle here whose hypotenuse is the diameter of the smaller circle
You can see that the line from the observer to that original lighthouse is at a right angle
With a new long line that we drew
Good news, right?
because that means we can apply the inverse Pythagorean theorem and that means that the apparent brightness from the original lighthouse is the same as
the combined brightness from the two newer ones and
Of course, you can do that same thing over on the other side
drawing a line through the top of the smaller circle and getting two new lighthouses on the larger circle and
Even nicer these four lighthouses are all going to be evenly spaced around the lake
Why?
Well, the lines from those lighthouses to the center are at 90 degree angles with each other
So since things are symmetric left to right that means that the distances along the circumference are 1, 2, 2, 2, and 1
Alright, you might see where this is going, but I want to walk through this for just one more step
You draw a circle twice as big so circumference of 16 now and for each lighthouse
You draw a line from that lighthouse through the top of the smaller circle
Which is the center of the bigger circle and then create two new lighthouses where that line intersects with the larger circle
Just as before because the long line is a diameter of the big circle
those two new lighthouses make a right angle with the observer, right and
Just as before the line from the observer to the original lighthouse is
Perpendicular to the long line and those are the two facts that justify us in using the inverse Pythagorean theorem
But what might not be as clear is that when you do this for all of the lighthouses to get eight new ones on the
Big lake those eight new lighthouses are going to be evenly spaced
This is the final bit of geometry proofiness before the final thrust
To see this remember that if you draw lines from two adjacent lighthouses on the small lake to the center
They make a 90 degree angle
If instead you draw lines to a point anywhere on the circumference of the circle that's not between them the very useful
inscribed angle theorem from geometry tells us that this will be
Exactly half of the angle that they make with the center in this case 45 degrees
But when we position that new point at the top of the lake
These are the two lines which define the position of the new lighthouses on the larger lake
What that means then is that when you draw lines from those eight new lighthouses into the center
They divide the circle evenly into 45 degree angle pieces
and that means the eight lighthouses are evenly spaced around the circumference with the distance of two between each one of them and
Now just imagine this thing playing on at every step doubling the size of each circle and
Transforming each lighthouse into two new ones along a line drawn through the center of the larger circle
at every step the apparent brightness to the observer remains the same pi squared over 4 and
at every step the lighthouse has remained evenly spaced with a distance 2 between each one of them on the circumference and
In the limit what we're getting here is a flat horizontal line with an infinite number of lighthouses
evenly spaced in both directions and
Because the apparent brightness was pi squared over 4 the entire way that will also be true in this limiting case
And
This gives us a pretty awesome infinite series the sum of the inverse squares 1 over n squared
Where n covers all of the odd integers 1 3 5 and so on but also negative 1 negative 3 negative 5 off in the leftward direction
Adding all of those up is going to give us pi squared over 4
That's amazing and it's the core of what I want to show you and
Just take a step back and think about how unreal this seems
The sum of simple fractions that at first sight have nothing to do with geometry nothing to do with circles at all
Apparently gives us this result that's related to pi
Except now you can actually see what it has to do with geometry
the number line is kind of like a limit of ever-growing circles and
As you sum across that number line making sure to sum all the way to infinity on either side
It's sort of like you're adding up along the boundary of an infinitely large circle and a very loose
But very fun way of speaking
But wait, you might say this is not the sum that you promised us at the start of the video
And well, you're right. We do have a little bit of thinking left
First things first, let's just restrict the sum to only being the positive odd numbers which gets us pi squared divided by 8
Now the only difference between this and the sum that we're looking for that goes over all the positive integers odd and even is
That it's missing the sum of the reciprocals of even numbers what I'm coloring in red up here
Now you can think of that missing series as a scaled copy of the total series that we want
Where each lighthouse moves to being twice as far away from the origin one gets shifted to two two gets shifted to four
three gets shifted to six and so on and
Because that involves doubling the distance for every lighthouse. It means that the apparent brightness would be decreased by a factor of four and
That's also relatively straightforward algebra going from the sum over all the integers to the sum over the even integers
Involves multiplying by 1 4th
And what that means is that going from all the integers to the odd ones would be multiplying by 3 4ths
Since the evens plus the odds have to give us the whole thing
So if we just flip that around that means going from the sum over the odd numbers to the sum over all positive integers
requires multiplying by 4 thirds
So taking that pi squared over 8 multiplying by 4 thirds bada boom bada bing
We've got ourselves a solution to the basil problem
Now this video that you just watched was primarily written and animated by one of the new three blue one brown team members Ben Hambricht
An addition made possible. Thanks to you guys through patreon