E raised to pi with an i.
We've been taught by a lot that you've got minus one.
Can we glean what this means?
For such words are absurd.
How to treat the repeat of a feat pi i times.
This is bound to confound till your mind redefines
these amounts one can't count which surmount our friend E.
Numbers act as abstract functions which slide the ridge
to the space in its place with a grace when they sum.
Multiplied they don't slide acting a second way they
rotate and dilate but keep straight the same plane.
Now what we write as E to the X won't perplex when
you know it's for show that X goes up and right.
It does not as you thought repeat E product E.
It functions with gumption on functions we've now seen.
It turns slide side to side into growths and shrinks both.
Up and downs come around as turns round which is key.
This is why pi times i which slides north is brought
forth and returned we have learned as a turn halfway round.
Minus one matched by none turns this way and we're done.