It's honestly an honor to be here. Many thanks to the faculty for including me.
Welcome to all of the parents and the friends who were able to come and more
than anything congratulations to the class of 2023. I was sitting essentially
where you are right now about eight years ago. I was receiving the same
degree and in the time since then I devoted myself to trying to share math
with others mainly through YouTube but also through some other avenues and what
I want to talk to you about today is a small way that my relationship with math
has changed during that time and a way that I hope that it continues to change.
The change is personal but it's something that might just apply to you
too and if so it might actually help in shaping your future. I was reflecting
before today on what it was that pulled me into the subject in the first place.
Why is it that I fell in love with the subject? Why is it that I chose to major
in it when I was here? Why is it that I've spent the last eight years in this
sort of weird unorthodox career path of explaining it online? And you see there's
a story that I think a lot of us tell and the story is centered on things like
the inescapable beauty of the subject or the fact that it's very charming just
how well applied it is to not just physics and not just computer science
but a plethora of different technical fields. But that story at least for me
would gloss over another factor that might be just as influential but which
is a lot more awkward to talk about. Ego. I don't know if you remember what it was
like to be a child. If you remember what it was like maybe in elementary school
and the way it came across to us. If I look back to my earliest memories of
math I think I was very lucky because it felt to me like a game and I think this
had to do with how my dad would present it to me. But in the context of school it
had a very different character. It felt competitive. I don't think this was the
intention of the teachers. I don't think it was the intention of any of the
adults around. But there was a certain unspoken assumption that the subject was
supposed to be hard. That many of us were going to struggle with it. And no
doubt thanks to the games that I would play with my dad I was one of the
fortunate ones who found it a little bit easier. And because I found it a little
bit easier I think I came to like the subject not because it was beautiful and
not because it was useful and not even because it was playful but frankly
because of that childish self-satisfaction that comes from
feeling like you're doing well at something that the adults tell you
you're supposed to be doing well at. And for a long time in school this sort of
kicked off a positive feedback loop. I spent a lot of time with the subject
because I liked it. I liked it because I felt good at it. And to the extent that I
actually wasn't any good at it it was because I was spending so much time with
it. And I don't want to suggest that this is true for everyone who likes math and
I also don't want to suggest that this is the the kind of loop that doesn't
have struggles involved with it. Because there absolutely are struggles any way
that you learn math. It's more that if I'm honest the forces that kept me
pushing through some of the struggles and putting in the time and the practice
and the effort that's necessary to get better at the subject were at least in
part motivated by a desire to be seen as being good at it. And you know I was a
teenager it's hard to escape a little bit of ego but ego is an awkward motive
to talk about. And if I'm fair the beauty in the application really did play some
role. It's not like they weren't there at all but they came in a lot later. Because
of this positive feedback loop I was spending time in the subject I would
chat with my teachers after school about it. I would go to local math circles
events. I learned what a mathematician was. I would read books about problem
solving. And in that kind of immersion it's hard not to fall in love with the
actual beauty of the subject. So even if the passion began for these slightly
more self-centered and slightly more childish reasons that started to give
away to something a little bit purer something more like an aesthetic sense
something a little more outward focused. It's a little like a fossil where you
know the organic molecules slowly start to give way for a longer term sturdier
mineral that'll be there be there to the end. For me it became a little bit
less about perceived success and a little bit more about the subject itself.
But that's not actually the change that I want to talk to you about. This shift
in motivation the fossilization process probably happened maybe towards the end
of high school started my time here at Stanford. But what I want to talk about
is how analogous to the way that the new minerals of a fossil still take on the
same general shape as the original bone. I think there might have been some
lingering after effects associated with the less pure original motivations for
the subject. See while I was here at Stanford I remember a lot of my peers
would use the word interesting. Now why is it that you chose to go to that
internship that you did this summer or why did you choose to work with this
professor that you did? Oh it seemed like they were working on very interesting
problems. But what does the word interesting mean? Interesting to whom? I
think if I was to look back on myself and how I was using the word at least
part of what I meant by it was that a problem seemed hard. It seemed
recognizably hard but not so hard that I couldn't sink my teeth into it a little
bit. Utility had a strange backseat for me and it really was about the challenge
in and of itself. And I don't think this was just me. If we fast forward by the
time I was making YouTube videos for a long time one of the most popular videos
on the channel was one that had the title the hardest problem on the hardest
test which admittedly is blatant clickbait. And it was about a problem
from the Putnam and between you and me it wasn't really the hardest problem
that the Putnam's ever shown but it was positioned as number six. But if we think
about the fact that it was clickbait why would that work? Why is it that something
on the order of 10 million people outside the usual subscriber base were
curious to click on a topic not because it was beautiful or not because it
promised anything useful but merely because it promised that something was
challenging. Now to be fair sometimes difficulty does correspond with
something that's useful maybe there's a field that's blocked by a puzzle that
nobody knows how to solve and if someone could solve it it would unlock more
utility in that field. But the question is whether the reason for caring about
the problem fundamentally was about that utility or if it was about the fact that
it's widely recognized to be challenging and because of what that might imply for
the person who does solve it and how they might be perceived. So I'll give you
another example for where you know origins of a slightly more youthful and
competitive spirited motivation for math might have had these lingering after
effects even after that motivation was no longer the dominant one. When I
started making videos about math I was actually a senior here at Stanford when
I very first began I was uploading them to a channel that I had given the very
strange name of three blue and brown and at that time I cared a lot about the
content seeming very different from traditional lessons out there. I cared a
lot that it was showing something students wouldn't see in the usual
linear track of school and I think I cared a lot about being perceived as
providing something that was original something that was distinct. Now if we
contrast this after I graduated I spent time working at Khan Academy and there
the goal was very explicitly to make content that met students where they are
then. I made a couple hundred pieces of content mostly centered around
multivariable calculus and I was choosing topics not based on originality or a
desire to stand out more than anything I was choosing topics simply because
they were on the list of what students had asked to know about what they needed
to know and the feedback in both categories of these videos was positive
but with a different character and one of them was a lot deeper. Those on early
three blue and brown felt like people watching a shared sport something that
we all enjoyed watching together but those on Khan Academy had a very
different flavor they were characterized more than anything by gratitude. I felt
that I actually helped people and they found them genuinely useful. So later on
on three blue and brown I started to prioritize lessons that met learners
where they were. I did a series about linear algebra I did a series about
calculus people asked if I could explain what is a Fourier transform or how do
neural networks work and so I obliged. Now the topics weren't original you know
there's lots and lots of other videos and pieces of content online that
explained those but these are by far the ones that have received the most
gratitude in that time and which have accounted for any success that I've
found since then. There's always room for novelty in the specific approach after a
topic is chosen but the thing that took me an embarrassingly long time to really
learn the lesson that took a long time to genuinely sink in is that when topics
are chosen primarily because of how they'll help people and concerns like
novelty and originality and whether something is capital I interesting are
all relevant only insofar as they help the goal of meeting a learner where they
are. That's when the reach feels genuinely meaningful and for what it's
worth I do think that shift in focus is probably what made the difference
between videos being a hobby and videos being a career. Now for every one of you
who's sitting here right now whatever it is that you choose to do moving forward
with the math that you've learned here and the other skills that you've learned
here the future fulfillment that you derive from that work is going to have
as much to do with how you evaluate what's worth working on as it does with
the strengths that you're bringing to the table. The future mark that your work
leaves on the world has as much to do with how you're evaluating what you're
working on as it does anything else and my advice to you right now and you're at
this very pivotal juncture in your life is to be especially mindful of where
that evaluation function comes from. If after today you're going into industry
you might ask yourself how are you choosing where to work? How did you
choose who to work with? How are you choosing what to build? If you are going
into academia ask yourself if it's for the right reasons and how you'll choose
which problems to work on. How much of it depends on the way that you'll be
perceived for solving the problems and how much depends on the value that other
people will find from it. Now if you're going into teaching, well honestly if
you're going into teaching you're probably wiser than the rest of us so I
don't have much to say. See in the last eight years I felt a shift in my own
evaluation function. Hardness in and of itself that doesn't cut it. Originality
for its own sake is hollow and math still has an intrinsic beauty but
honestly these days that beauty is all the more potent if there's at least a
whisper of something genuinely useful in sight. I can't tell you what the right
evaluation function is for you. I can suggest that it probably will matter
more when it depends less on yourself and it depends a little bit more on
others and what you're doing for them but what I am sure of is that time spent
right now today seriously reassessing where the evaluation function comes from
stands to make your future richer. So congratulations once again all of us
here are anxiously awaiting what that future looks like for each and every one
of you.