Turning to chapter 2, advanced problems, problem number 10 asks this seemingly innocent question.
Find the number of subsets of the set 1 up to 2000, the sum of whose elements is divisible
by 5.
That might take a little moment to parse, but to illustrate let me show it on a much
simpler example, where we have the set 1, 2, 3, 4, 5.
This has 2 to the 5th, or 32 distinct subsets, which look like this.
If you compute the sum of each of those subsets, and you organize them by which ones have the
same sum, you'll see that 8 of those subsets have a sum which is divisible by 5.
So the answer here would be 8.
The case with all the subsets of 1 up to 2000 is obviously way, way bigger, and you might
be able to guess at a rough estimate for the answer, but the challenge is to compute the
exact answer.
I really love this problem, and the full video I did on this question covers a really beautiful
and surprising way you can think about it.
It uses one of those tools that mathematicians keep in their belt that legitimately feels
like magic the first time you see it.