Two, then four, then eight, and then sixteen.
It's very nice.
Before I go on with this particular pattern, there's a fun story about it.
A little known fact.
Do you guys know the song Hallelujah, the one popular from Trent?
Yeah, okay. We all know the song.
Lots of different artists have played it.
The original artist was Leonard Cohen.
He was the one who wrote the lyrics.
Few people know, he actually went through many, many different iterations
of what the song would be.
And ultimately it ended up as this biblical devastation of love.
But one of the earlier versions was about this particular pattern in math.
It's true. 100% true.
Leonard Cohen was a low-key math buff.
And I thought it might be fun, just because I don't want the original version to get lost in the annals of history,
to share with you guys what this would have sounded like,
if history had turned out that way, if he didn't make it about love and religion and all of those great things.
So welcome to the stage yet again,
to accompany on keynote Matt Parker.
Wonderful.
And I know I know Leonard Cohen, but just imagine if you're watching Shrek and when they get to that typical moment
when you don't think love is going to hold, you've actually heard the proper original.
Well I heard there was a sequence of chords
Splits the circle to one, two, then four
And points seem to cut in powers of two
Yeah, it was run like this
With fourth and fifth
But something's up
We go out at six
It's awesome 31
I had a piece for you
I'll make it for you
Yeah
When your faith is strong you still need proof
What's your faith?
Death can lead to a dew
Each integral up on the left is pi over two
Yeah
I think that's true
For the next, which is terrible like a drum
We've shown that it's off by a hair
It's a subtle slip but it's true
I had a piece for you
I'll make it for you
Now take a prime and write it in Facebook
It's just like you had before
This prime gives a new prime
With this rule, yeah
Or does it though?
It'll eventually find new primes or not
So send design patterns hold
Then they're broken
How they fool you
They rule you
That's it, I'm just guitarring