In my video on the circle division problem, I referenced Euler's characteristic formula,
and here I would like to share a particularly nice proof of this fact. It's very different
from the inductive proof, typically given, but I'm not trying to argue that this is somehow
better or easier to understand than other proofs. Instead, I chose this topic to illustrate
one example of the incredible notion of duality, and how it can produce wonderfully elegant
math. First, let's go over what the theorem states. If you draw some dots and some lines
between them, that is, a graph, and if none of these lines intersect, which is to say
you have a planar graph, and if your drawing is connected, then Euler's formula tells us
that the number of dots minus the number of lines plus the number of regions these lines
cut the plane into, including that outer region, will always be 2. Because Euler was originally
talking about 3D polyhedra when he found this formula, which was only later reframed in terms
of planar graphs, instead of saying dots, we say vertices, instead of saying lines, we say edges,
and instead of saying regions, we say faces. Hence, we write Euler's discovery as V minus
E plus F equals 2. Before describing the proof, I need to go through three pieces of graph theory
terminology. Cycles, spanning trees, and dual graphs. If you are already familiar with some
of these topics and don't care to see how I describe them, feel free to click the appropriate
annotation and skip ahead. Imagine a tiny creature sitting on one of the vertices. Let's name him
Randolph. If we think of edges as something Randolph might travel along from one vertex to
the next, we can sensibly talk about a path as being a sequence of edges that Randolph could
travel along, where we don't allow him to backtrack on the same edge. A cycle is simply a path that
ends on the same vertex where it begins. You might be able to guess how cycles will be important for
our purposes, since they will always enclose a set of faces. Now imagine that Randolph wants access
to all other vertices, but edges are expensive, so he'll only buy access to an edge if it gives
him a path to an untouched vertex. This frugality will leave him with a set of edges without any
cycles, since the edge finishing off a cycle would always be unnecessary. In general, a connected
graph without cycles is called a tree, so named because we can move things around and make it look
like a system of branches, and any tree inside a graph which touches all the vertices is called
a spanning tree. Before defining the dual graph, which runs the risk of being confusing, it's
important to remember why people actually care about graphs in the first place. I was actually
lying earlier when I said a graph is a set of dots and lines. Really, it's a set of anything with any
notion of connection, but we typically represent those things with dots and those connections with
lines. For instance, Facebook stores an enormous graph where vertices are accounts and edges are
friendships. Although we could use drawings to represent this graph, the graph itself is the
abstract set of accounts and friendships, completely distinct from the drawing. All sorts of things are
undrawn graphs, the set of English words considered connected when they differ by one letter,
mathematicians considered connected if they've written a paper together, neurons connected by
synapses. Or, maybe, for those of us reasoning about the actual drawing of a graph on the plane,
we can take the set of faces this graph cuts the plane into and consider two of them connected if
they share an edge. In other words, if you can draw a graph on the plane without intersecting
edges, you automatically get a second, as of yet undrawn, graph whose vertices are the faces and
whose edges are, well, edges of the original graph. We call this the dual of the original graph. If
you want to represent the dual graph with dots and lines, first put a dot inside each one of the faces.
I personally like to visualize the dot for that outer region as being a point somewhere at infinity
where you can travel in any direction to get there. Next, connect these new dots with new lines that
pass through the centers of the old lines, where lines connected to that point at infinity can go
off the screen in any direction, as long as it's understood that they all meet up at the same one
point. But keep in mind, this is just the drawing of the dual graph, just like the representation
of Facebook accounts and friendships with dots and lines is just a drawing of the social graph.
The dual graph itself is the collection of faces and edges. The reason I stress this point is to
emphasize that edges of the original graph and edges of the dual graph are not just related,
they're the same thing. You see, what makes the dual graph all kinds of awesome is the many ways
that it relates to the original graph. For example, cycles in the original graph correspond to
connected components of the dual graph, and likewise, cycles in the dual graph correspond
with connected components in the original graph. Now for the cool part. Suppose our friend Randolph
has an alter ego, Mortimer, living in the dual graph, traveling from face to face instead of
from vertex to vertex, passing over edges as he does so. Let's say Randolph has bought all the
edges of a spanning tree and that Mortimer is forbidden from crossing those edges. It turns
out the edges that Mortimer has available to him are guaranteed to form a spanning tree of the dual
graph. To see why, we only need to check the two defining properties of spanning trees. They must
give Mortimer access to all faces and there can be no cycles. The reason he still has access to
all faces is that it would take a cycle in Randolph's spanning tree to insulate him from
a face, but trees cannot have cycles. The reason Mortimer cannot traverse a cycle in the dual graph
feels completely symmetric. If he could, he would separate one set of Randolph's vertices from the
rest, so the spanning tree from which he is banned could not have spanned the whole graph.
So not only does the planar graph have a dual graph, any spanning tree within that graph always
has a dual spanning tree in the dual graph. Here's the kicker. The number of vertices in
any tree is always one more than the number of edges. To see this, note that after you start with
the root vertex, each new edge gives exactly one new vertex. Alternatively, within our narrative,
you could think of Randolph as starting with one vertex and gaining exactly one more for each edge
in what will become a spanning tree. Since this tree covers all vertices in our graph,
the number of vertices is one more than the number of edges owned by Randolph. Moreover,
since the remaining edges make up a spanning tree for Mortimer's dual graph, the number of edges he
gets is one more than the number of vertices in the dual graph, which are faces of the original
graph. Putting this together, it means the total number of edges is two more than the number of
vertices plus the number of faces, which is exactly what Euler's formula states.