Egy korábbi videóban beszéltem
systems of equations, and I sort of brushed
a lineáris 00:00:15,800
aside the discussion of actually computing
solutions to these systems.
--&gt; 00:00:19,690 3-ról, ami
And while it’s true that number-crunching
is something we typically leave to the computers,
egy jó lakmuszpapír
digging into some of these computational methods
arra vonatkozóan, hogy
valóban érted-e, mi történik,
this is really where the rubber meets the
00:00:31,680 óta --&gt;
road.
00:00:32,680 00:00:32,680 --&gt; 00:00:36,379
Here I want to describe the geometry behind
a certain method for computing solutions to
8 9 Ha
these systems, known as Cramer’s rule.
nem ismeri vagy
The relevant background needed here is an
understanding of determinants, dot products,
rozsdásodott, feltétlenül nézze meg
and of linear systems of equations, so be
a megfelelő videókat
ezekről a témákról.
De először!
Előre el kell
is not the best way for computing solutions
mondanom, hogy a
to linear systems of equations.
Cramer-szabály 00:00:56,379 --&gt;
Gaussian elimination, for example, will always
be faster.
00:00:58,010 00:00:58,010 --&gt;
So why learn it?
00:01:01,950 16 17
Think of this as a sort of cultural excursion;
it’s a helpful exercise in deepening your
segít a lineáris
knowledge of the theory of these systems.
algebrából származó ötletek
Wrapping your mind around this concept will
megszilárdításában, mint
például a determináns
seeing how they relate to each other.
és a lineáris
Also, from a purely artistic standpoint, the
ultimate result is just really pretty to think
rendszerek, by 00:01:19,960
about, much more so that Gaussian elimination.
--&gt; 00:01:24,619 22
Alright, so the setup here will be some linear
system of equations, say with two unknowns,
23 nagyobb számú
x and y, and two equations.
ismeretlent és ugyanannyi
In principle, everything we’re talking about
egyenletet tartalmazó rendszereket
fog működni.
De az egyszerűség
to hold in our heads.
kedvéért egy kisebb
So as I talked about in a previous video,
you can think of this setup geometrically
példa szebb
as a certain known matrix transforming an
unknown vector, [x; y], where you know what
00:01:46,349 --&gt; 00:01:50,599
the output is going to be, in this case [-4;
29 -2].
Ne feledje, ennek a
you how the matrix acts as a transform, each
mátrixnak az oszlopai
one telling you where the basis vectors of
the input space land.
00:02:06,250 --&gt; 00:02:10,899 33
So this is a sort of puzzle, what input [x;
y], is going to give you this
Az itt kapott
output [-4; -2]?
válasz típusa attól
Remember, the
függhet, hogy a transzformáció
összenyom-e vagy sem
all of space into a lower dimension.
00:02:44,299 --&gt; 00:02:46,080 00:02:46,080
That is if it has zero determinant.
--&gt; 00:02:51,849 39
In that case, either none of the inputs land
on our given output or there are a whole bunch
40 a teljes
of inputs landing on that output.
n-dimenziós tér, amelyben elkezdődött;
But for this video we’ll limit our view
to the case of a non-zero determinant, meaning
minden bemenet egy
the output of this transformation still spans
és csak egy kimenetre
kerül 00:03:12,549 --&gt;
and every output has one and only one input.
00:03:14,840 44 számolja
One way to think about our puzzle is that
we know the given output vector is some linear
ki, hogy pontosan mi
combination of the columns of the matrix;
x*(the vector where i-hat lands) + y*(the
is az x
vector where j-hat lands), but we wish to
és az y.
Első lépésként hadd
is wrong, but in the right direction.
mutassak be egy
The x-coordinate of this mystery input vector
is what you get by taking its dot product
ötletet, hogy
with the first basis vector, [1; 0].
00:03:18,829 --&gt; 00:03:23,340
Likewise, the y-coordinate is what you get
by dotting it with the second basis vector,
48 49 a
[0; 1].
pontszorzatok a
So maybe you hope that after the transformation,
rejtélyvektor átalakított változatával
a transzformált 00:03:41,939
versions of the basis vectors will also be
--&gt; 00-val:
these coordinates x and y.
03:43,590 00:03:43,590 --&gt;
That’d be fantastic because we know the
transformed versions of each of these vectors.
00:03:50,400 55 Az
There’s just one problem with this: it’s
not at all true!
átalakulás előtt
For most linear transformations, the dot product
és után nagyon
eltérő lesz.
Például lehet, hogy
pointing in the same direction, with a positive
két vektora általában
dot product, which get pulled away from each
other during the transformation, in such a
00:04:04,959 --&gt; 00:04:09,270
way that they then have a negative dot product.
60 61 merőleges
Likewise, if things start off perpendicular,
with dot product zero, like the two basis
marad a transzformáció
vectors, there’s no guarantee that they
után, megőrizve a
nullapontos szorzatot.
Az általunk
certainly aren’t preserved.
vizsgált példában
They tend to get bigger since most vectors
are getting stretched.
pontszorzatok 00:04:27,140
In fact, transformations which do preserve
dot products are special enough to have their
--&gt; 00:04:30,950
own name: Orthonormal transformations.
66 egymásra
These are the ones which leave all the basis
merőleges vektor
egységnyi hosszúsággal.
Gyakran úgy gondolja ezeket, mint forgatási mátrixokat.
A merev mozgásnak felel
squishing or morphing.
meg, nyújtás nélkül,
Solving a linear system with an orthonormal
matrix is very easy: Since dot products are
00:04:53,000 --&gt; 00:04:58,920 73
preserved, taking the dot product between
the output vector and all the columns of your
szorzat a bemeneti
matrix will be the same as taking the dot
vektor és az összes
bázisvektor között, ami
the coordinates of the input vector.
ugyanaz, mint a 00:05:13,599
So, in that very special case, x would be
the dot product of the first column with the
--&gt; 00 :05:18,690
output vector, and y would be the dot product
of the second column with the output vector.
77 a legtöbb
Now, even though this idea breaks down for
lineáris rendszerben, valami irányába
mutat, amit keresnünk
geometric understanding for the coordinates
kell: Van-e alternatív 00:05:37,780
of our input vector which remains unchanged
after the transformation?
--&gt; 00:05:42,780 81
If your mind has been mulling over determinants,
you might think of this clever idea: Take
vektor, az i-hat és
the parallelogram defined by the first basis
a rejtélyes bemeneti
vektor [x; y].
Ennek a paralelogrammának a
1, times the height perpendicular to that
területe az alapja,
base, which is the y-coordinate of our input
vector.
00:05:59,990 --&gt; 00:06:03,460
So, the area of this parallelogram is sort
of a screwy roundabout way to describe the
86 koordinátákról beszélni,
vector’s y-coordinate; it’s a wacky way
de fuss velem.
Valójában, hogy pontosabbak
think of the signed area of this parallelogram,
legyünk, 00:06:19,690 --&gt;
in the sense described by the determinant
video.
00:06:22,440 90 meg
That way, a vector with negative y-coordinate
would correspond to a negative area for this
kell nézni a
parallelogram.
vektor által átfogott
Symmetrically, if you
paralelogrammát és a
második bázisvektort, a
will be the x-coordinate of the vector.
j-hat területét 00:06:45,099
Again, it’s a strange way to represent the
x-coordinate, but you’ll see what it buys
-- &gt; 00:06:49,370
us in a moment.
95 96 pontszorzatát
Here’s what this would look like in three-dimensions:
Ordinarily the way you might think of one
a harmadik szabványos
of a vector’s coordinate, say its z-coordinate,
bázisvektorral, a k-hattal
vennénk fel.
00:07:11,870 --&gt; 00:07:13,569
creates with the other two basis vectors,
00:07:13,569 --&gt;
i-hat and j-hat.
00:07:20,030 102 Ennek
If you think of the square with area 1 spanned
by i-hat and j-hat as the base of this guy,
a vektornak
its volume is the same its height, which is
the third coordinate of our vector.
a másik koordinátája
Likewise, the wacky way to think about any
a paralelepipedon
létrehozása e
all the basis vectors other than the one you’re
vektor és 00
looking for, and get its volume.
között: 07:34,950
Or, rather, we should talk about the signed
volume of these parallelepipeds, in the sense
--&gt; 00:07:37,900 00:07:37,900
described in the determinant video, where
the order in which you list the three vectors
--&gt; 00:07:42,490
matters and you’re using the right-hand
107 szabály.
Így a negatív koordináták továbbra is értelmesek.
Oké, akkor miért
and volumes like this?
gondolja a
As you apply some matrix transformation, the
areas of the parallelograms don’t stay the
koordinátákat területnek
same, they may get scaled up or down.
00:07:56,000 --&gt;
But(!), and this is a key idea of determinants,
all these areas get scaled by the same amount.
00:08:02,039 112
Namely, the determinant of our transformation
113 mátrixnak.
Például, ha
spanned by the vector where your first basis
megnézi a
vector lands, which is the first column of
the matrix, and the transformed version of
paralelogramma 00:08:17,850
[x; y], what is its area?
--&gt; 00:08:22,850
Well, this is the transformed version of that
parallelogram we were looking at earlier,
117 118
whose area was the y-coordinate of the mystery
bemeneti vektort.
Tehát a területe
transformation multiplied by that value.
lesz a
So, the y-coordinate of our mystery input
vector is the area of this parallelogram,
meghatározó a 00:08:39,080
spanned by the first column of the matrix
and the output vector, divided by the determinant
--&gt; 00:08:44,590
of the full transformation.
122 rejtélyes bemeneti
And how do you get this area?
vektor landolásánál,
Well, we know the coordinates for where the
ez egy lineáris
egyenletrendszer lényege.
Tehát hozzon létre egy
the same as that of our matrix, and whose
mátrixot, amelynek első
second column is the output vector, and take
its determinant.
oszlopa 00:09:05,670 --&gt;
So look at that; just using data from the
output of the transformation, namely the columns
00:09:11,250 129 vektor,
of the matrix and the coordinates of our output
így visszaállíthatjuk rejtélyes
bemeneti vektorunk y-koordinátáját.
Hasonlóképpen, ugyanaz az ötlet kaphatja meg az x-koordinátát.
Nézd meg azt a
which encodes the x-coordinate of the mystery
paralelogrammát, amelyet korán
input vector, spanned by the input vector
and j-hat.
definiáltunk 00:09:32,580 --&gt;
The transformed version of this guy is spanned
by the output vector and the second column
00:09:36,420 135, megszorozva
of the matrix, and its area will have been
a mátrix determinánsával.
Tehát a rejtély bemeneti
is this area divided by the determinant of
vektorunk x-koordinátája 00:09:52,000
the transformation.
--&gt; 00:09:53,980 00:09:53,980
Symmetric to what we did before, you can compute
the area of that output parallelogram by creating
--&gt; 00:09:58,900 140
a new matrix whose first column is the output
vector, and whose second column is the same
tér, az eredeti lineáris
as the original matrix.
rendszerünkben látható számok
So again, just using data from the output
vissza tudja állítani
az x-koordinátát 00:10:13,600
of our mystery input vector.
--&gt; 00:10:18,440 145
This formula for finding the solutions to
a linear system of equations is known as Cramer’s
146 értéke 4+2, ami
rule.
6, az alsó
Here, just to sanity check ourselves, plug
in the numbers here.
determináns pedig 2,
The determinant of that top altered matrix
tehát az x-koordinátának
3-nak kell lennie.
És valóban, visszatekintve arra
we started with, it’s x-coordinate is 3.
a bemeneti vektorra
Likewise, Cramer’s rule suggests the y-coordinate
should be 4/2, or 2, and that is indeed the
00:10:35,910 --&gt; 00:10:43,850 151,
y-coordinate of the input vector we started
with here.
és nagyon ajánlom,
The case with three dimensions is similar,
hogy álljon meg, és
gondolja végig magát.
Tessék, adok egy kis lendületet.
Megvan ez az ismert
a 3x3 matrix, and a known output vector, given
transzformáció, amelyet a
by the right side of our linear system, and
we want to know what input vector lands on
00:11:02,780 --&gt; 00:11:07,580 157
this output vector.
158 vektor adja,
If you think of, say, the z-coordinate of
the input vector as the volume of this parallelepiped
mi történik ennek a
spanned by i-hat, j-hat, and the mystery input
paralelepipedonnak a térfogatával
a transzformáció után?
Hogyan lehet kiszámítani az új térfogatot?
Tényleg, álljon meg egy
the details of generalizing this to higher
pillanatra, és gondolja
dimensions; finding an expression for each
coordinate of the solution to larger linear
végig 00:11:32,200 --&gt;
systems.
00:11:37,330 164 165
Thinking through more general cases and convincing
yourself that it works is where all the learning
néhány haver a
will happen, much more so than listening to
YouTube-on járja át
újra az érvelést.