What you're looking at right now is something called quaternion multiplication, or rather
you're looking at a certain representation of a specific motion happening on a four-dimensional
sphere being represented in our three-dimensional space, one which you'll understand by the
end of this video.
Quaternions are an absolutely fascinating and often underappreciated number system from
math.
Just as complex numbers are a two-dimensional extension of the real numbers, quaternions
are a four-dimensional extension of complex numbers.
But they're not just playful mathematical shenanigans, they have a surprisingly pragmatic
utility for describing rotation in three dimensions, and even for quantum mechanics.
The story of their discovery is also quite famous in math.
The Irish mathematician William Rowan Hamilton spent much of his life seeking a three-dimensional
number system, analogous to the complex numbers.
And as the story goes, his son would ask him every morning whether or not he had figured
out how to divide triples, and he would always say no, not yet.
But on October 16, 1843, while crossing the Broom Bridge in Dublin, he realized, with
a supposed flash of insight, that what he needed was not to add a single dimension to
the complex numbers, but to add two more imaginary dimensions, three imaginary dimensions describing
space and the real numbers, sitting perpendicular to that in some kind of fourth dimension.
He carved the crucial equation describing these three imaginary units into the bridge,
which today bears a plaque in his honor showing that equation.
Now you have to understand, our modern notion of vectors with their dot product and the
cross product and things like that didn't really exist in Hamilton's time, at least
not in a standardized form.
So after his discovery, he pushed hard for quaternions to be the primary language with
which we teach students to describe three-dimensional space, even forming an official quaternion
society to proselytize his discovery.
Unfortunately, this was balanced with mathematicians on the other side of the fence, who believed
that the confusing notion of quaternion multiplication was not necessary for describing three dimensions,
resulting in some truly hilarious old-timey trash talk legitimately calling them evil.
It's even believed that the Mad Hatter scene from Alice in Wonderland, whose author you
may know was an Oxford mathematician, was written in reference to quaternions, that
the chaotic table placement changes were mocking their multiplication, and that certain
quotes were referencing their non-commutative nature.
Fast forward about a century, and the computing industry gave quaternions a resurgence among
programmers who work with graphics and robotics and anything involving orientation in 3D space.
And this is because they give an elegant way to describe and compute 3D rotations, which
is computationally more efficient than other methods, and which also avoids a lot of the
numerical errors that arise in these other methods.
The 20th century also brought quaternions some more love from a completely different
direction, quantum mechanics.
The special actions that quaternions describe in four dimensions are actually quite relevant
to the way that two-state systems like spin of an electron or the polarization of a photon
are described mathematically.
What I'll show you here is a way to visualize quaternions in their full four-dimensional
glory.
It would surprise me if this approach was fully original, but I can say that it's
certainly not the standard way to teach quaternions, and that the specific four-dimensional right-hand
rule image I'd like to build up to is something I haven't seen elsewhere.
Building up an understanding for this visual will take us meaningful time, but once you
have it, there is a very natural and satisfying intuition for how to think about quaternion
multiplication.
It won't be until the next video that I show you how exactly quaternions describe
orientation in three dimensions, which is for some people the whole reason we care about
it, but once we're able to go at it armed with the image of what they're doing to
a 4D hypersphere, there's a pleasing understanding to be had for the otherwise opaque formulas
characterizing this relationship.
The structure here will be to start by imagining teaching complex numbers to someone who only
understands one dimension, then describing 3D rotations to someone who only understands
two dimensions, and ultimately to represent what quaternions are doing up in four dimensions
within the constraints of our 3D space.
Our first character is Linus the Linelander, whose mind can only grasp the one-dimensional
geometry of lines and the algebra of real numbers.
We're going to try to describe complex numbers to Linus, and it's really important for
you to empathize with him as much as you can during this, because in a few minutes you're
going to be in his shoes.
On the one hand, you could define complex numbers purely algebraically.
You say each one is expressed as some real number plus some other real number times i,
where i is a newly invented constant whose defining property is that i times i equals
negative one.
Then you say to Linus, to multiply two complex numbers, you just use the distributive property,
what many people learn in school as FOIL, and you apply this rule that i times i equals
negative one to simplify things down further.
And that's fine, that totally works, and the standard textbook way to introduce quaternions
is analogous to this, showing the algebraic rules and calling it done.
But I think something is missing if we don't at least try to show Linus the geometry of
complex numbers, and what complex multiplication looks like, since the problems in math and
physics where complex numbers are shockingly useful often leverage this spatial intuition.
You and I, who understand two dimensions, might think of it like this.
When you multiply two complex numbers, z times w, you can think of z as a sort of function
acting on w, rotating and stretching it in some way.
I like to think of this by broadening the view and asking, what does z do to the entire
plane?
You can think of that bird's eye view action by imagining using one hand to fix the number
zero in place, and using another hand to drag the point at one up to z, since anything times
zero is zero, and anything times one is itself.
In two dimensions, there is one and only one stretching rotating action on the plane that'll
do this.
This is also how I'll have you thinking about quaternion multiplication later on,
where the number on the left acts as a kind of function to the one on the right, and we'll
understand this function by seeing how it acts by transforming space, although instead
of rotating 2d space, it does a sort of double rotation in 4d space.
By the way, if you want to review thinking about complex numbers as a kind of action,
a good warmup for this video might be the one I did on e to the pi i explained with
introductory group theory.
Now Linus the line lander is pretty comfortable with the idea of stretching, that's what
multiplication by real numbers looks like.
Maybe it's a little weird for him to think about stretching in multiple dimensions, but
it's not fundamentally different.
The difficult thing to communicate to Linus is rotation.
Specifically, focus on the unit circle of the complex plane, all the numbers a distance
1 from 0.
Since multiplication by these numbers corresponds to pure rotation, how would you explain to
Linus the look and feel of multiplying by these numbers?
At first, that might seem impossible, rotation is just such an intrinsically two-dimensional
idea.
But, on the other hand, rotation involves only one degree of freedom, a single number,
the angle, specifies a given rotation uniquely.
So in principle, it should be possible to associate the set of all rotations to the
one-dimensional continuum that is Linus's world.
And there are many ways you could do this, but the one I'm going to show you is called
a stereographic projection, it's a special way to map a circle onto a line, or a sphere
into a plane, or even a 4D hypersphere into 3D space.
For every point on the unit circle, draw a line from negative 1 through that point,
and wherever it intersects the vertical line through the circle's center, that's where
the point of the circle gets projected.
So for example, the point at 1 gets projected into the center of the line, the point i actually
stays fixed in place, as does negative i.
All of the points on that 90 degree arc between 1 and i will get projected somewhere in the
interval between where 1 landed and where i landed.
As you continue farther around the circle on the arc between i and negative 1, the projected
points end up farther and farther away at an increasing rate.
Similarly, if you come around the other way towards negative 1, the projected points end
up farther and farther on the other end of the line.
This line of projected points is what we show to Linus, labeling a few key points, like
1 and i and negative 1 all for reference.
Technically, the point at negative 1 has no projection under this map, since the tangent
line to the circle at that point never crosses the vertical line.
But what we say is that negative 1 ends up at the point at infinity, a special point
you imagine adding to the line where you would approach it if you walk infinitely far along
the line in either direction.
It's important to remember, and remind Linus, that what he's seeing is only the complex
numbers that are a distance 1 from the origin, the unit circle.
Linus doesn't see most numbers, like 0, or 1 plus i, or negative 2 minus i, but that's
okay, because right now we just want to describe complex numbers z where multiplying by z has
the effect of a pure rotation, so he only needs to understand the unit circle.
For example, when we take the number i and multiply it by any other complex number w,
the effect is to rotate by 90 degrees counterclockwise, and when we apply this action to the circle
being projected down to the line for Linus, what does he see?
Well, it's a bit of a strange morphing action on the line, one which I want you to become
familiar with for something we'll see later on.
It's easiest to understand by following a few key reference points.
i times 1 is i, so that means the number 1 should move up to i.
i times i is negative 1, so the point at i slides off to infinity.
i times negative 1 is equal to negative i, so that point at infinity kind of comes back
around from the bottom to the position 1 unit below the center.
i times negative i is 1, so the point at negative i slides up to 1.
Even though this is kind of a weird motion, it lets us communicate some important ideas
to Linus.
For example, multiplying by i four times, which corresponds to rotating by 90 degrees
four times in a row, gets us back to where we started.
i to the fourth equals 1.
To get more of a feel for things, let me just show the circle rotated at various different
angles.
On both the left and right half of the screen, I'm putting a hand on the point that started
at the number 1 to help us and help Linus keep track of the overall motion.
Next, let's introduce Felix the Flatlander, who only understands two-dimensional geometry.
Imagine trying to explain rotations of a sphere to Felix.
In the spirit of transitioning from complex numbers to quaternions, let's extend the
complex numbers with its horizontal axis of real numbers and its vertical axis of imaginary
numbers with a third axis, defined by some newly invented constant, j, sitting one unit
away from zero, perpendicular to the complex plane.
Instead of having this new axis in the z-direction, like you might expect, for a better analogy
with how we'll visualize quaternions, we'll want to orient things so that the i and j
axes sit in the x and y directions, with the real number line aligned along the z-direction.
Every point in 3D space is described as some real number plus some real number times i
plus some real number times j.
As it happens, it's not possible to define a notion of multiplication for a 3D number
system like this that would satisfy the usual algebraic properties that make multiplication
a useful construct.
Perhaps I'll outline why this is the case in a follow-on video, but staying focused
on our current goal, think about describing 3D rotations in this coordinate system to
Felix the Flatlander.
The unit sphere consists of all those numbers which are a distance 1 from 0 at the origin,
meaning the sum of the squares of their coordinates is 1.
We can't show all of 3D space to Felix, but what we can do is project this 2D surface
to him and give him a feel for what reorientations of the sphere look like under that projection.
Analogous to what we did before, stereographic projection will associate almost every point
on the unit sphere with a unique point on the horizontal plane defined by the i and
the j axes.
For each point on the sphere, draw a line from negative 1 at the south pole through
that point and see where it intersects the plane.
So the point 1 at the north pole ends up at the center of the plane.
All of the points of the northern hemisphere get mapped somewhere inside the unit circle
of the i-j plane, and that unit circle which passes through i,j,-i,-j actually stays fixed
in place.
And that's an important point to make note of.
Even though most points and lines and patches that Felix the Flatlander sees are warped
projections of the real sphere, this unit circle is the one thing he has which is an
honest part of our unit sphere, unaltered by projection.
All of the points in the southern hemisphere get projected outside that unit circle, each
getting farther and farther away as you approach negative 1 at the south pole.
And again, negative 1 has no projection under this mapping, but what we say is that it ends
up at some point at infinity.
That point at infinity is something such that no matter which direction you walk on the
plane, as you go infinitely far out, you'll be approaching that point.
It's analogous to how if you walk any direction away from the north pole, you're approaching
the south pole.
Now let me just pull up a view of what Felix sees in two dimensions.
As I rotate the sphere in various ways, the lines of latitude and longitude drawn on that
sphere get projected into various circles and lines in Felix's space.
And the way I've done things up here, the checkerboard pattern on the surface of the
sphere is accurately reflected in the projected view you see with Felix, and the pinker view
represents where the point that started at the north pole ends up after the rotation,
and the yellow circle represents where the equator ended up after the projection.
The more you put yourself in Felix's shoes right now, the easier quaternions will be
in a moment, and as with Linus, it helps to focus on a few key reference objects rather
than trying to see the whole sphere.
This circle, passing through 1, i, negative 1, and negative i, gets mapped onto a line
which Felix sees as the horizontal axis.
It's important to remind Felix that what he sees is not the same thing as the i-axis.
Remember, we're only projecting the numbers that have a distance 1 from the origin, so
most points on the actual i-axis, like 0, 2i, 3i, etc., are completely invisible to
Felix.
Similarly, the circle that passes through 1, j, negative 1, and negative j gets projected
onto what he sees as a vertical line.
In general, any line Felix sees comes from some circle on the sphere that passes through
negative 1.
In some sense, a line is just a circle that passes through the point at infinity.
Now think about what Felix sees as we rotate the sphere.
A 90 degree rotation about the j-axis brings 1 to i, i to negative 1, negative 1 to negative
i, and negative i to 1.
So what Felix the Flatlander sees is an extension of the rotation that Linus the Linelander
was seeing.
Notice also that this action rotates the i, j unit circle to the position where the 1,
j unit circle used to be.
So what Felix sees is his yellow unit circle getting transformed into a vertical line,
while the red vertical line gets transformed into the unit circle.
Of course, from our perspective, we know this is all just rigid motion, no actual stretching
or morphing is taking place.
All of that is just an artifact of the projection.
Similarly, a rotation about the i-axis involves moving 1 to j, j to negative 1, negative 1
to negative j, and negative j to 1.
This rotation turns the i, j unit circle into the 1, i unit circle, which to Felix looks
like the unit circle getting transformed into a horizontal line.
A rotation about the real axis is actually quite easy for Felix to understand, since
the whole projection simply gets rotated about the origin, where the only points staying
fixed in place are 1 at the origin and negative 1 off at infinity.
In the same way that the complex numbers included the real numbers with a single extra quote
unquote imaginary dimension, represented by the unit i, and that the not-actually-a-number
system thing we had in three dimensions included a second imaginary direction, j, the quaternions
include the real numbers together with three separate imaginary dimensions, represented
by the units i, j, and k.
Each of these three imaginary dimensions is perpendicular to the real number line, and
they're all perpendicular to each other somehow.
So in the same way that complex numbers are represented as a pair of real numbers, each
quaternion can be written using four real numbers, and it lives in four-dimensional
space.
You often think of this as being broken up into a real or scalar part, and then a 3D
imaginary part.
And Hamilton used a special word for quaternions that had no real part and just i, j, k components,
a word which was previously somewhat foreign in the lingo of math and physics, vector.
On the one hand, you could just define quaternion multiplication by giving the rules for how
i, j, and k multiply together, and saying that everything must distribute nicely.
This is analogous to defining complex multiplication by saying that i times i is negative 1, and
then distributing and simplifying products.
And indeed, this is how you would tell a computer to perform quaternion multiplication, and
the relative compactness of this operation compared to say matrix multiplication is what's
made quaternion so useful for graphics programming and many other things.
There's also a rather elegant form of this multiplication rule written in terms of the
dot product and the cross product, and in some sense, quaternion multiplication subsumes
both of these notions, at least as they appear in three dimensions.
But just as a deeper understanding for complex multiplication comes from understanding its
geometry that multiplying by a complex number involves a combination of scaling and rotating,
you and I are here for the four-dimensional geometry of quaternion multiplication.
And just as the magnitude of a complex number, its distance from zero, is the square root
of the sum of the squares of its component, that same operation gives you the magnitude
of a quaternion.
And multiplying one quaternion, q1, by another, q2, has the effect of scaling q2 by the magnitude
of q1, followed by a very special type of rotation in four dimensions.
And those special 4D rotations, the heart of what we need to understand, correspond
to the hypersphere of quaternions, a distance 1 from the origin, both in the sense that
the quaternions whose multiplying action is a pure rotation live on that hypersphere,
and in the sense that we can understand this weird 4D action just by following points on
the hypersphere, rather than trying to look at all the points in the inconceivable stretches
of four-dimensional space.
Analogous to what we did for Linus and Felix, we stereographically project this hypersphere
into 3D space.
This label in the upper right is going to show a given unit quaternion, and this little
pink dot will show where that quaternion gets projected in our 3D space.
Just as before, we're projecting from the number negative 1, which sits on the real
number line that is somehow perpendicular to all of our 3D space, and beyond our perception.
Just as before, the number 1 ends up projected straight into the center of our space.
And in the same way that i and negative i were fixed in place for Linus, and that the
3D space and 3D space get a whole sphere passing through i, j, and k on that unit hypersphere
which stays in place under the projection.
So what we see as a unit sphere in our 3D space represents the only unaltered part of
the hypersphere of quaternions getting projected down onto us.
It's something analogous to the equator of a 3D sphere, and it represents all of the
unit quaternions whose real part is zero, what Hamilton would have described as unit
vectors.
The unit quaternions with positive real parts, between 0 and 1, end up somewhere inside this
unit sphere, closer to the number 1 in our 3D space, which should feel analogous to how
the northern hemisphere got mapped inside the unit circle for Felix.
On the other hand, all the unit quaternions with negative real part end up somewhere outside
that unit sphere.
The number negative 1 is sitting off at the point at infinity, which you can easily find
by walking in any direction.
Keep in mind, even though we see the projection of some of these quaternions as being closer
or farther from the origin of our 3D space, everything you're looking at represents
a unit quaternion, so everything you're looking at really has the same magnitude,
the same distance from the number 0.
And that number 0 itself is nowhere to be found in this picture.
Like all other non-unit quaternions, it's invisible to us.
In the same way that for Felix, the circle passing through 1, i, negative 1, and negative
i got projected into a line through the origin, when we see this line through the origin passing
through i and negative i, we should understand that it really represents a circle.
Likewise, up on the hypersphere, invisible to us, there is a unit sphere passing through
1, i, j, negative 1, negative i, and negative j, and that whole sphere gets projected into
the plane that we see passing through 1, i, negative i, j, negative j, and negative 1,
off at infinity, what you and I might call the xy plane.
In general, any plane that you see here really represents the projection of a sphere somewhere
up on the hypersphere which passes through the number negative 1.
The action of taking a unit quaternion and multiplying it by any other quaternion from
the left can be thought of in terms of two separate 2D rotations, happening perpendicular
to and in sync with each other in a way that could only ever be possible in four dimensions.
As a first example, let's look at multiplication by i.
We already know what this does to the circle that passes through 1 and i, which we see
as a line.
1 goes to i, i goes to negative 1, off at infinity, negative 1 comes back around to
negative i, and negative i goes to 1.
Remember, just like what Linus saw, all of this is the stereographic projection of a
90 degree rotation.
Now look at the circle passing through j and k, which is in a sense perpendicular to the
circle passing through 1 and i.
It might feel weird to talk about two circles being perpendicular to each other, especially
when they have the same center and radius and don't touch each other at all, but nothing
could be more natural in four dimensions.
You can think of the action of i on this perpendicular circle as obeying a certain right-hand rule,
if you'll excuse the intrusion of my ghostly green-screen hand into our otherwise pristine
platonic mathematical stage.
You let that thumb of your right hand point from the number 1 to i, and you curl your
fingers.
The j-k circle will rotate in the direction of that curl.
How much?
Well, by the same amount as the 1i circle rotates, which is 90 degrees in this case.
This is what I meant by two rotations perpendicular to and in sync with each other.
So j goes to k, k goes to negative j, negative j goes to negative k, and negative k goes
to j.
This gives us a little table for what the number i does to the other quaternions, but
I want this not to be something you memorize, but something you could close your eyes and
you could really see.
Computationally, if you know what a quaternion does to the numbers 1, i, j, and k, you know
what it does to any arbitrary quaternion, since multiplication distributes nicely.
In the language of linear algebra, 1, i, j, and k form a basis of our 4-dimensional space,
so knowing what our transformation does to them gives us the full information about what
it does to all of space.
Geometrically, a 4-dimensional creature would be able to look at those two perpendicular
rotations I just described, and understand that they lock you into one and only one rigid
motion for the hypersphere.
We might lack the intuitions of such a hypothetical creature, but we can maybe try to get close.
Here's what the action of repeatedly multiplying by i looks like on our stereographic projection
of the ijk sphere.
It gets rotated into what we see as a plane, then gets rotated further back to where it
used to be, though the orientation is reversed now, then gets rotated again into what we
see as a plane, and after the fourth iteration, it ends up right back where it started.
As another example, think of a quaternion like q equals negative square root of 2 over
2 plus square root of 2 over 2 times i, which if we pull up a picture of a complex plane,
is a 135 degree rotation away from 1 in the direction of i.
Under our projection, we see this along the line from 1 to i somewhere outside the unit
sphere.
If that sounds weird, just remember how Linus would have seen this same number.
The action of multiplying this q by all other quaternions will look to us like dragging
the point at 1 all the way to this projected version of q, while the jk circle gets rotated
135 degrees, according to our right-hand rule.
Multiplication by any other quaternion is completely similar.
For example, let's see what it looks like for j to act on other quaternions by multiplication
from the left.
The circle through 1 and j, which we see projected as a line through the origin, gets rotated
90 degrees, dragging 1 up to j, so j times 1 is 1 and j times j is negative 1.
The circle perpendicular to that one, passing through i and k, gets rotated 90 degrees according
to this right-hand rule, where you point your thumb from 1 to j, so j times i is negative
k, and j times k is i.
In general, for any other unit quaternion you see somewhere in space, start by drawing
the unit circle passing through 1, q, and negative 1, which we see in our projection
as a line through the origin.
Then draw the circle perpendicular to that 1 on what we see as the unit sphere.
You rotate the first circle so that 1 ends up where q was, and rotate the perpendicular
circle by the same amount according to the right-hand rule.
One thing worth noticing here is that order of multiplication matters.
It's not, as mathematicians would say, commutative.
For example, i times j is k, which you might think of in terms of i acting on the quaternion
j, but if you think of j as acting on i, j times i, it rotates i to negative k.
In fact, commutativity, this ability to swap the order of multiplication, is a way more
special property than a lot of people realize.
And most groups of actions on some space don't have it.
It's like how in solving a Rubik's cube, order matters a lot, or how rotating a cube
about the z-axis and then about the x-axis gives a different final state from rotating
it about the x-axis, then about the z-axis.
And last, as one final but rather important point, so far I've shown you how to think
about quaternions as acting by left multiplication, where when you read an expression like i times
j, you think of i as a kind of function morphing all of space, and j as one of the points it's
acting on.
But you can also think of them as a different sort of action, by multiplying from the right,
where in this expression, j would be acting on i.
In that case, the rule for multiplication is very similar.
It's still the case that 1 goes to j, and j goes to negative 1, etc., but instead of
applying the right-hand rule to the circle perpendicular to the 1j circle, you would
use your left hand.
So either way, i times j is equal to k, but you can either think about this with your
right hand curling the number j to the number k as your thumb points from 1 to i, or as
your left hand curling i to k as its thumb points from 1 to j.
Understanding this left-hand rule for multiplication from the other side will be extremely useful
for understanding how unit quaternions describe rotation in three dimensions.
And so far, it's probably not clear how exactly quaternions do describe 3D rotation.
I mean, if you consider one of these actions on the unit sphere, passing through i, j, and k,
it doesn't leave that sphere in place, it morphs it out of position.
So the way that this works is slightly more complicated than a single quaternion product.
It involves a process called conjugation, and I'll make a full follow-on video all
about it so that we have the time to go through some examples.
In the meantime, for more information on the story of quaternions and their relation to
orientation in 3D space, Quanta, a mathematical publication I'm sure a lot of you are familiar
with, just put out a post in a kind of loose conjunction with this video.
Link in the description.
If you enjoyed this, consider sharing it with some friends, and if you felt like the narrative
structure here was actually helpful for understanding, maybe reassure those friends who would be
turned off by a large timestamp that good math is actually worth the time.
And many thanks to the patrons among you.
I actually spent way longer than I care to admit on this project, so your patience and
support is especially appreciated this time around.