In un video precedente, ho
systems of equations, and I sort of brushed
parlato della linearità 00:00:15,800
aside the discussion of actually computing
solutions to these systems.
--&gt; 00:00:19,690 3 è
And while it’s true that number-crunching
is something we typically leave to the computers,
una buona cartina di
digging into some of these computational methods
tornasole per capire se effettivamente
capisci o meno cosa
this is really where the rubber meets the
sta succedendo, dal momento
road.
che 00:00:31,680 --&gt; 00:00:32,680
Here I want to describe the geometry behind
a certain method for computing solutions to
00:00:32,680 --&gt; 00:00:36,379 8 9
these systems, known as Cramer’s rule.
assicurati di guardare i
The relevant background needed here is an
understanding of determinants, dot products,
video pertinenti su questi
and of linear systems of equations, so be
argomenti se non hai
familiarità o sei arrugginito.
Ma prima!
Dovrei dire subito che
is not the best way for computing solutions
la regola di
to linear systems of equations.
Cramer 00:00:56,379 --&gt;
Gaussian elimination, for example, will always
be faster.
00:00:58,010 00:00:58,010 --&gt;
So why learn it?
00:01:01,950 16 17
Think of this as a sort of cultural excursion;
it’s a helpful exercise in deepening your
aiuta a consolidare le
knowledge of the theory of these systems.
idee dell&#39;algebra lineare,
Wrapping your mind around this concept will
come il determinante
e i sistemi
seeing how they relate to each other.
lineari, entro 00:01:19,960
Also, from a purely artistic standpoint, the
ultimate result is just really pretty to think
--&gt; 00:01:24,619 22 23
about, much more so that Gaussian elimination.
funzionerà con sistemi
Alright, so the setup here will be some linear
system of equations, say with two unknowns,
con un numero
x and y, and two equations.
maggiore di incognite
In principle, everything we’re talking about
e lo stesso
numero di equazioni.
Ma per semplicità,
to hold in our heads.
un esempio più
So as I talked about in a previous video,
you can think of this setup geometrically
piccolo è più
as a certain known matrix transforming an
unknown vector, [x; y], where you know what
carino 00:01:46,349 --&gt;
the output is going to be, in this case [-4;
00:01:50,599 29 -2].
Ricorda, le colonne di
you how the matrix acts as a transform, each
questa matrice indicano
one telling you where the basis vectors of
the input space land.
00:02:06,250 --&gt; 00:02:10,899 33
So this is a sort of puzzle, what input [x;
y], is going to give you this
il tipo di
output [-4; -2]?
risposta che ottieni
Remember, the
qui può dipendere dal
fatto che la
all of space into a lower dimension.
trasformazione schiaccia o meno
That is if it has zero determinant.
00:02:44,299 --&gt; 00:02:46,080
In that case, either none of the inputs land
on our given output or there are a whole bunch
00:02:46,080 --&gt; 00:02:51,849
of inputs landing on that output.
39 40 l&#39;intero spazio
But for this video we’ll limit our view
to the case of a non-zero determinant, meaning
n-dimensionale in cui
the output of this transformation still spans
è iniziato; ogni input
arriva a uno
and every output has one and only one input.
e un solo
One way to think about our puzzle is that
we know the given output vector is some linear
output 00:03:12,549 --&gt; 00:03:14,840
combination of the columns of the matrix;
x*(the vector where i-hat lands) + y*(the
44 calcola cosa
vector where j-hat lands), but we wish to
sono esattamente xey.
Come primo passaggio,
is wrong, but in the right direction.
lasciatemi mostrare un&#39;idea
The x-coordinate of this mystery input vector
is what you get by taking its dot product
che 00:03:18,829 --&gt;
with the first basis vector, [1; 0].
00:03:23,340 48 49
Likewise, the y-coordinate is what you get
by dotting it with the second basis vector,
i prodotti scalari
[0; 1].
con la versione
So maybe you hope that after the transformation,
trasformata del vettore
misterioso con la
versions of the basis vectors will also be
trasformata 00:03:41,939 --&gt;
these coordinates x and y.
00: 03:43,590 00:03:43,590
That’d be fantastic because we know the
transformed versions of each of these vectors.
--&gt; 00:03:50,400 55
There’s just one problem with this: it’s
not at all true!
prima e dopo
For most linear transformations, the dot product
la trasformazione sarà
molto diverso.
Ad esempio, potresti avere
pointing in the same direction, with a positive
due vettori che
dot product, which get pulled away from each
other during the transformation, in such a
generalmente 00:04:04,959 --&gt;
way that they then have a negative dot product.
00:04:09,270 60 61 rimarranno
Likewise, if things start off perpendicular,
with dot product zero, like the two basis
perpendicolari dopo la
vectors, there’s no guarantee that they
trasformazione, preservando il
prodotto punto zero.
Nell&#39;esempio che stavamo
certainly aren’t preserved.
guardando, i prodotti
They tend to get bigger since most vectors
are getting stretched.
scalari 00:04:27,140
In fact, transformations which do preserve
dot products are special enough to have their
--&gt; 00:04:30,950 66
own name: Orthonormal transformations.
vettori perpendicolari
These are the ones which leave all the basis
tra loro con
lunghezze unitarie.
Spesso si pensa a queste come a matrici di rotazione.
Corrispondono al movimento rigido,
squishing or morphing.
senza allungamento, 00:04:53,000 --&gt;
Solving a linear system with an orthonormal
matrix is very easy: Since dot products are
00:04:58,920 73 prodotti tra
preserved, taking the dot product between
the output vector and all the columns of your
il vettore di input
matrix will be the same as taking the dot
e tutti i vettori
base, che equivale a
the coordinates of the input vector.
trovare 00:05:13,599 --&gt; 00
So, in that very special case, x would be
the dot product of the first column with the
:05:18,690 77 nella
output vector, and y would be the dot product
of the second column with the output vector.
maggior parte dei sistemi
Now, even though this idea breaks down for
lineari, ci indica la
direzione di qualcosa da
geometric understanding for the coordinates
cercare: esiste un vettore
of our input vector which remains unchanged
after the transformation?
alternativo 00:05:37,780 --&gt; 00:05:42,780
If your mind has been mulling over determinants,
you might think of this clever idea: Take
81 vettore, i-hat e
the parallelogram defined by the first basis
il misterioso vettore di
input [X; y].
L&#39;area di questo parallelogramma
1, times the height perpendicular to that
è la sua base,
base, which is the y-coordinate of our input
vector.
00:05:59,990 --&gt; 00:06:03,460 86
So, the area of this parallelogram is sort
of a screwy roundabout way to describe the
per parlare di coordinate,
vector’s y-coordinate; it’s a wacky way
ma corri con me.
In realtà, per essere
think of the signed area of this parallelogram,
più precisi, dovresti
in the sense described by the determinant
video.
00:06:19,690 --&gt; 00:06:22,440 90
That way, a vector with negative y-coordinate
would correspond to a negative area for this
guardare il parallelogramma
parallelogram.
formato dal vettore e
Symmetrically, if you
dal secondo vettore
base, j-hat, la sua
will be the x-coordinate of the vector.
area 00:06:45,099 --
Again, it’s a strange way to represent the
x-coordinate, but you’ll see what it buys
&gt; 00:06:49,370 95 96
us in a moment.
sarebbe prendere il
Here’s what this would look like in three-dimensions:
Ordinarily the way you might think of one
suo prodotto scalare con
of a vector’s coordinate, say its z-coordinate,
il terzo vettore
base standard, k-hat.
Ma invece, considera il
creates with the other two basis vectors,
parallelepipedo che 00:07:11,870
i-hat and j-hat.
--&gt; 00:07:13,569 00:07:13,569
If you think of the square with area 1 spanned
by i-hat and j-hat as the base of this guy,
--&gt; 00:07:20,030 102
its volume is the same its height, which is
the third coordinate of our vector.
un&#39;altra coordinata di
Likewise, the wacky way to think about any
questo vettore è
quella di formare
all the basis vectors other than the one you’re
il parallelepipedo tra
looking for, and get its volume.
questo vettore e
Or, rather, we should talk about the signed
volume of these parallelepipeds, in the sense
00: 07:34,950 --&gt;
described in the determinant video, where
the order in which you list the three vectors
00:07:37,900 00:07:37,900 --&gt;
matters and you’re using the right-hand
00:07:42,490 107 regola.
In questo modo le coordinate negative hanno ancora senso.
Ok, allora perché
and volumes like this?
pensare alle
As you apply some matrix transformation, the
areas of the parallelograms don’t stay the
coordinate come ad
same, they may get scaled up or down.
aree 00:07:56,000
But(!), and this is a key idea of determinants,
all these areas get scaled by the same amount.
--&gt; 00:08:02,039 112
Namely, the determinant of our transformation
113 matrice.
Ad esempio, se
spanned by the vector where your first basis
guardi il
vector lands, which is the first column of
the matrix, and the transformed version of
parallelogramma 00:08:17,850
[x; y], what is its area?
--&gt; 00:08:22,850 117
Well, this is the transformed version of that
parallelogram we were looking at earlier,
118 vettore
whose area was the y-coordinate of the mystery
di input.
Quindi la sua area
transformation multiplied by that value.
sarà il determinante
So, the y-coordinate of our mystery input
vector is the area of this parallelogram,
dei 00:08:39,080 --&gt; 00:08:44,590
spanned by the first column of the matrix
and the output vector, divided by the determinant
122 misteriosi vettori
of the full transformation.
di input, questo
And how do you get this area?
è il punto centrale
Well, we know the coordinates for where the
di un sistema
lineare di equazioni.
Quindi, creando una matrice la
the same as that of our matrix, and whose
cui prima colonna è
second column is the output vector, and take
its determinant.
00:09:05,670 --&gt; 00:09:11,250 129
So look at that; just using data from the
output of the transformation, namely the columns
vettore, possiamo recuperare la
of the matrix and the coordinates of our output
coordinata y del nostro
misterioso vettore di input.
Allo stesso modo, la stessa idea può darti la coordinata x.
Guarda quel parallelogramma che
which encodes the x-coordinate of the mystery
abbiamo definito all&#39;inizio
input vector, spanned by the input vector
and j-hat.
00:09:32,580 --&gt; 00:09:36,420 135
The transformed version of this guy is spanned
by the output vector and the second column
moltiplicato per il
of the matrix, and its area will have been
determinante della matrice.
Quindi la coordinata x
is this area divided by the determinant of
del nostro misterioso vettore
the transformation.
di input 00:09:52,000 --&gt;
Symmetric to what we did before, you can compute
the area of that output parallelogram by creating
00:09:53,980 00:09:53,980 --&gt; 00:09:58,900
a new matrix whose first column is the output
vector, and whose second column is the same
140 spazio, i numeri
as the original matrix.
che vediamo nel nostro
So again, just using data from the output
sistema lineare originale, noi
può recuperare la coordinata
of our mystery input vector.
x 00:10:13,600 --&gt; 00:10:18,440
This formula for finding the solutions to
a linear system of equations is known as Cramer’s
145 146 è 4+2,
rule.
che è 6, e
Here, just to sanity check ourselves, plug
in the numbers here.
il determinante inferiore è
The determinant of that top altered matrix
2, quindi la coordinata
x dovrebbe essere 3.
E infatti, guardando indietro
we started with, it’s x-coordinate is 3.
a quel vettore di
Likewise, Cramer’s rule suggests the y-coordinate
should be 4/2, or 2, and that is indeed the
input 00:10:35,910 --&gt;
y-coordinate of the input vector we started
with here.
00:10:43,850 151 e ti
The case with three dimensions is similar,
consiglio vivamente di fermarti
a pensarci attentamente.
Ecco, ti do un piccolo slancio.
Abbiamo questa trasformazione nota,
a 3x3 matrix, and a known output vector, given
data dal vettore
by the right side of our linear system, and
we want to know what input vector lands on
00:11:02,780 --&gt; 00:11:07,580
this output vector.
157 158, cosa
If you think of, say, the z-coordinate of
the input vector as the volume of this parallelepiped
succede al volume
spanned by i-hat, j-hat, and the mystery input
di questo parallelepipedo
dopo la trasformazione?
Come puoi calcolare quel nuovo volume?
Davvero, fermati e prenditi
the details of generalizing this to higher
un momento per
dimensions; finding an expression for each
coordinate of the solution to larger linear
riflettere 00:11:32,200 --&gt;
systems.
00:11:37,330 164 165
Thinking through more general cases and convincing
yourself that it works is where all the learning
qualche tizio su
will happen, much more so than listening to
YouTube spiega di
nuovo il ragionamento.